<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="102" cos="Austria-Hungary">    
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Phönix C.1]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Phönix C.I was developed as a replacement for the Hansa-Brandenburg C.II armed reconnaissance aircraft. Construction was typical for the era, consisting of wood framing throughout with a thin wood veneer covering the fuselage, sheet metal surrounding the engine and fabric covering over the remainder of the craft. The machine's rudder was unique. Most of the surface area of the rudder was below the horizontal tail. The rudder area above the horizontal tail was small, unobtrusive and gave the rear gunner an excellent field of fire.

Preproduction flight trials in late 1917 proved the new Phönix C.I to be fast, tough and maneuverable with an outstanding rate of climb and excellent handling properties. The aircraft was especially effective when flying at high altitudes, an attribute which lead to its extensive deployment in high-altitude photographic reconnaissance sorties. 

Production aircraft began equipping units of the Austro-Hungarian Air Force in the late spring of 1918. Flying largely over the Italian front, the C.Is immediately received praise from their crews. In June of 1918, a  Phönix C.I flown by Feldwebel (Sergeant) Max Kauer with Arnold Barwig as observer/gunner was attacked by a SPAD XIII fighter flown by Italy's leading air ace, Major Francesco Barraca. In the ensuing engagement the Italian was shot down and killed. This event proved that the Phönix C.I was not only a fine reconnaissance platform but also a dangerous opponent for the Allies' best fighter aircraft even when flown by their best aces. 

Production of the Phönix C.I was terminated at the end of the war by which time just over 100 had been delivered to the Austro-Hungarian Air Force. Terms within the Armistice demanded that Austria-Hungary surrender all of its Phönix C.I aircraft to the victorious Allied nations.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Flik (Squadron) 17/D, Austro-Hungarian Air Force Airdrome, San Godega di Urbano, Italian Front, September, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Phönix Flugzeugwerke A.G.
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Austria-Hungary<br /><b>Power plant:</b> One Hiero, 6 cylinder inline liquid cooled piston engine of 230 hp (172 kW)<br /><b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 110 mph (177 km/h)  
Ceiling: 17,715 feet (5,400 m)
Endurance: 3 hours, 30 minutes  
Empty Weight: 1,808 pounds (820 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,734 pounds (1,240 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 36 feet 1 inch (11.00 m)
Length: 24 feet 8 inches (7.52 m)
Height: 9 feet 8 inches (2.95 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Armament: One fixed forward-firing  8 mm (.310 inch) Schwarzlose machine gun mounted on the starboard side of the forward fuselage, one similar weapon on flexible mount in rear cockpit, 160 lbs of bombs  
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>
</holtPlane>
