<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="103" cos="Austria-Hungary">    
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Phönix D.I (Type 8) (Imperial Navy)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[In 1917, the Austrian arm of the Albatros Company  changed its name to Phönix Flugzeugwerke AG. The firm's senior engineer, Edmund Sparmann, designed the Phönix D.I in an effort to provide the Austro-Hungarian Air Force with an improved fighter. The D.I incorporated several unusual features for a fighter aircraft of the time. These included inward-sloping intra-plane struts on the wings, a 200 hp (149 kW) engine and dual forward-firing machine guns which were completely enclosed in the fuselage. 

The first production machines entered service with the Austro-Hungarian Air Force in February of 1918. Their performance proved adequate but not truly outstanding. Despite a more powerful engine, the aircraft still suffered from a poor power to weight ratio, which contributed to their poor performance characteristics. Nonetheless, the fighter became the favored aircraft for several Austro-Hungarian air aces during 1918. The D.I's production was limited to only 140 machines -120 for the <i>K.u.K. Luftfahrttruppen</i> (the Austrian Air Force) and 20 for the Austrian Navy.

Production of the Phönix D.I was terminated in mid 1918 in favor of the Phönix D.II and D.IIa. Both aircraft had lighter structures, and substantially improved performance. The The D.IIa was also fitted with a more powerful 230 hp (172 kW) engine. After World War I, Edmund Sparmann developed a series of Phönix fighters for the Swedish Air Force, which would prove even more successful than his World War I Phönix fighters.

The most colorful Phönix D.Is (like the one modeled here) were those in service with the Austro-Hungarian Navy. The Navy variants were deployed from a base at Altura in the defense of the Austro-Hungarian naval bases at Pola and Cattaro, which were frequent targets of Italian bombers.
 <br/><b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> Like many Austro-Hungarian aircraft of World War I, the prototype of this Navy Phönix D.I model had red and white wing and tail stripes, replicating the colors of the monarchy's coat of arms, a copy of which is displayed on the rudder of the aircraft.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified Austro-Hungarian Naval Flik (Squadron), Altura Airdrome, Austria, June, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Phönix Flugzeugwerke A.G.
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Austria-Hungary<br /><b>Power plant:</b> One Hiero, 6 cylinder inline liquid cooled piston engine of 200 hp (149 kW)<br /><b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 113 mph (182 km/h)   
Ceiling: 19,685 feet (6000 m) 
Endurance: 2 Hours    
Empty Weight: 1,411 pounds (640 kg)            
Loaded Weight: 1,775 pounds (805 kg)  
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 32 feet 0 inches (9.75 m)
Length: 21 feet 9 inches (6.65 m)
Height: 9 feet 2 inches (2.79 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed forward firing synchronized 8mm (.315 inches) Schwarzlose machine guns enclosed in forward fuselage
<b>Crew:</b>0]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

