<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="104" cos="Austria-Hungary">    
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Phönix D.I (Type 8) (Imperial Aviation Troops)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[In 1917, the Austrian arm of the Albatros Company changed its name to Phönix Flugzeugwerke AG. The firm's senior engineer, Edmund Sparmann, designed the Phönix D.I in an effort to provide the Austro-Hungarian Air Force with an improved fighter. The D.I incorporated several unusual features for a fighter aircraft of the time. These included inward-sloping intra-plane struts on the wings, a 200 hp (149 kW) engine and dual forward-firing machine guns which were completely enclosed in the fuselage. 

The first production machines entered service with the Austro-Hungarian Air Force in February of 1918. Their performance proved adequate but not truly outstanding. Despite a more powerful engine, the aircraft still suffered from a poor power to weight ratio, which contributed to their poor performance characteristics. Nonetheless, the fighter became the favored aircraft for several Austro-Hungarian air aces during 1918. The D.I's production was limited to only 140 machines -120 for the K.u.K. Luftfahrttruppen [the Austrian Air Force] and 20 for the Austrian Navy. 

Production of the Phönix D.I was terminated in mid 1918 in favor of the Phönix D.II and D.IIa. Both aircraft had lighter structures, and substantially improved performance. The The D.IIa was also fitted with a more powerful 230 hp (172 kW) engine. After World War I, Edmund Sparmann developed a series of Phönix fighters for the Swedish Air Force, which would prove even more successful than his World War I Phönix fighters. 

The Air Force and Naval versions of the Phönix D.1 were each painted in distinct ways. The Naval Phönix D.1 (included elsewhere in this collection) incorporated red and white stripes on its wings and tail-the colors of the Austro-Hungarian coat-of-arms. The Air Force version (like the model displayed here) used a camouflage paint scheme of stippled brown on its upper surfaces. ]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Flik (squadron) 14 J, Austro-Hungarian Air Force, Italian Front, May 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Phönix Flugzeugwerke A.G.
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Austria-Hungary<br /><b>Power plant:</b> One Hiero, 6 cylinder inline liquid cooled piston engine of 200 hp (149 kW)<br /><b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed 113 mph (182 km/h) at sea level   
Ceiling: 19,685 feet (6,000 m) 
Range:  Endurance 3 Hours    
Empty Weight: 1,441 pounds (654 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,775 pounds (805 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span 32 feet 0 inches (9.75 m)   
Length 21 feet 7 inches (6.58 m) 
Height 9 feet 2 inches (2.79 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed forward firing synchronized Schwarzlose 8mm machine guns
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>
</holtPlane>