<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="105 " cos="Austria-Hungary"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Phönix D.IIa]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Phönix D.IIa was the last in the series of fighter aircraft designed and built by the Austro-Hungarian firm Phönix Flugzeugwerke that were deployed in operational combat during World War I. The design work was completed by Phönix's chief engineer, Edmund Sparmann. The machine borrowed much from its predecessor, the Phönix D.I and externally the two looked much alike. Although widely used by the Austro-Hungarian Air Force, pilots often complained that the Phönix D.I was overweight for its power plant, giving the aircraft only mediocre performance. 

To produce a better fighter, Sparmann designed the D.II variant. While having the same 200 hp Hiero engine as the D.I, the D.II was lightened by nearly 176 lbs. Weight was removed from the fighter through the alteration of its internal wood framing and its fuselage. The wings and tail surfaces were also lightened. The result was a marked improvement in the fighter's aerodynamic handling. For even better performance, Sparmann and his engineer colleague, Ing Kirste, upgraded the D.II's power plant to a 230 hp engine, thus creating the Phoniz D.IIa (modeled here). Shortages of the 230 hp Hiero engines required that some 20% of the D.IIa fighters be delivered with the smaller Hiero 200 hp power plants. But even these smaller 200 hp D.IIa fighters were clearly superior to their predecessor, the D.I. 

The new D.IIa aircraft began supplying Austro-Hungarian fighter units in late May of 1918 and remained in operational service with both the Austro-Hungarian Army and Navy until the end of the War. While probably the best fighter built by the Austro-Hungarian Empire during World War I, the D.IIa was not the equal of the newer Albatros or Fokker fighters in service with the German Air Force during 1918. Neither was it equal to the S.P.A.D. and Sopwith fighters flying for the Allies.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> The factory fresh Phönix D.IIa modeled here was the machine flown during the final days of World War I on the Austro-Hungarian/Italian front by the Austrian pilot Karf Teichmann.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Flik (squadron) 17 J, Austro-Hungarian Air Force, Feltre Airdrome, Feltre, Austria, October, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Phönix Flugzeugwerke A.G.
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Austria-Hungary<br /><b>Power plant:</b> One Hiero, 6 cylinder inline liquid cooled piston engine of 230 hp (172 kW)<br /><b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 115 mph (185 km/h) 
Ceiling: 19,685 feet (6,000 m)
Endurance: 3 hours 
Empty Weight: 1,402 pounds (636 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,920 pounds (871 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span 32 feet 2 inches (9.80 m) 
Length 22 feet 2 inches (6.75 m) 
Height 8 feet 8 inches (2.65 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 8mm (0.32 inch) Schwarzlose machine guns housed internally in the forward fuselage 
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

