<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="108" cos="Austria-Hungary"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Brandenburg C.I]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[Early in World War I both Germany and its ally, the Austro-Hungarian Empire, designated their reconnaissance aircraft as type "C" machines. This policy extended throughout the War. The Brandenburg C.I was one of the more successful of these reconnaissance aircraft. It was designed in late 1915 by Ernst Heinkel the famous German aeronautical engineer. Upon completion of its design, production was shifted to the Austrian firm Phönix Flugzeug-Werke A.G. and the Hungarian, Ungarische Flugzeugfabrik A.G. One of the earliest production variants of is modeled here. 

Production aircraft entered service with the Austro-Hungarian Air Force in early 1916. During the entire production run of the aircraft, which extended to the end of the War, no less than eighteen different variations of the machine were built. Externally all the variants appeared identical differing only in minor structural details and their increasingly more powerful engines. Framing of all the variants was of wood with a varnished wood veneer covering the fuselage and an aluminum casement around the engine. Intra-wing struts were metal, not wood, and were cantered inward - both were uncommon features for aircraft of the era. 

The machines were widely deployed in reconnaissance, observation, artillery-spotting and light bombing duties along all sectors of the Western, Italian and Russian fronts. They were highly regarded and became the favorites of their crews due to their excellent handling, agility, durability and dependability. The installation of ever more powerful engines continually improved the performance of the successive variants - a factor which engendered even greater crew approval. The Brandenburg C.I continued in constant service and became the "reconnaissance work horse" of the Austro-Hungarian Air Force until the War's conclusion in November of 1918.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified reconnaissance flik (squadron) of the Austro-Hungarian Air Force, Western Front, spring, 1916.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Hansa und Brandenburgische Flugzeugwerke AG
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Austria-Hungary<br /><b>Power plant:</b> One Austro-Daimler, 6 cylinder liquid cooled inline piston engine of 160 hp (119 kW)<br /><b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 87 mph (140 km/h) at sea level
Ceiling: 19,028 feet (5,800 m)
Range: Endurance 3 hours 
Empty Weight: 1,790 pounds (812 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,888 pounds (1,310 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 40 feet 2 inches (12.24 m) 
Length: 27 feet 8 inches (8.43 m) 
Height: 10 feet 11 inches (3.33 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing 8 mm (0.32 inch) Schwarzlose machine gun in an enclosed metal housing mounted in the center of the upper wing firing over the propeller arc, one similar drum fed weapon in an open flexible mount in rear cockpit, 60 kg (132 pounds) of bombs
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

