<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="105" cos="Austria-Hungary"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Lohner C.I]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[During World War I there were more different types of reconnaissance aircraft designed and placed into service than fighter and bomber types combined. Although fighters and bombers captured the imagination of the public, their impact on the outcome of the War has been questioned by some historians. On the other hand, the information provided to military leaders by reconnaissance aircraft had a significant impact on many major battles. Knowing the numbers, position and movement of enemy troops and supplies proved vital to the successful outcome of some land battles. It is not, therefore, surprising that the generals of both sides kept constant pressure on their respective aviation industries to provide new and better reconnaissance aircraft. 

One of the earliest reconnaissance types to enter service with the Austro-Hungarian Air Force was the Lohner C.I, modeled here. It was designed by the pioneer Austrian aeronautical engineer, Jacob Lohner, the founder and owner of a firm which was famous for building naval flying boats. The Lohner C.I's construction was of wood framing throughout with a varnished wood veneer covering the fuselage. Its wings and tail structures were covered with a doped fabric. Painted aluminum sheeting completely enclosed the engine and the top of the forward fuselage and the radiator was mounted in front of the upper wing. 

The Lohner C.I first flew in late 1915 and production aircraft began equipping combat units on the Western, Italian, Balkan and Eastern Fronts in the first weeks of 1916. The machine proved sluggish in flight. It lacked agility and had a poor rate of climb, which made it easy prey for the machineguns of Allied fighters. The C.I fared better on the Balkan Front where there was less fighter opposition. On the Western Front, even when accompanied by a fighter escort, its losses became prohibitive. After barely a year in service Lohner C.I aircraft were withdrawn from active reconnaissance roles and were replaced by better performing machines, primarily the much superior Hansa-Brandenburg C.I. The Lohner C.I aircraft were relegated to Austro-Hungarian flight schools where they were employed as two-seat trainers.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified reconnaissance flik (squadron) of the Austro-Hungarian Air Force, Balkan Front, May, 1916.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Lohnerwerke GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Austria-Hungary<br /><b>Power plant:</b> One Austro-Daimler, 6 cylinder liquid-cooled inline piston engine of 160 hp (119 kW)<br /><b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 85 mph (137 km/h) 
Ceiling: 11,482 feet (3,500 m)
Range: Endurance 3 hours
Empty Weight: 2,998 pounds (1,360 kg)
Loaded Weight: Not documented
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 44 feet 1 inch (13.44 m) 
Length: 30 feet 3 inches (9.22 m) 
Height: 10 feet 8 inches (3.25 m)
<b>Armament:</b> 8 mm (0.32 inch) Schwarzlose machine gun in flexible mount in rear cockpit
<b>Crew:</b>2 ]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

