<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="110" cos="Austria-Hungary"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Lloyd C.V (Series 46)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The design and construction of the Lloyd C.V began in early 1916. The Austrian aircraft company Ungarische Lloyd Flugzeug und Motorenfabrik developed the Lloyd C.V as an armed reconnaissance aircraft for spotting and controlling artillery fire. Some of these machines included early wireless radios for communicating with the ground artillery units for which they were spotting.

The Lloyd C.V included a number of unusual features. While most aircraft of the era were covered with a doped fabric, the Lloyd C.V's wings and fuselage were covered with a skin of fine wood veneer. This resulted in an aerodynamically efficient surface but led to condensation problems within the sealed wing structures. Condensation caused the wing structure to warp. 

Efforts to correct this problem never fully resolved the issue. The radiator for the aircraft's liquid-cooled engine was placed immediately behind the propeller in the direct line of the pilot's forward vision. As a result, the pilot was forced to lean out the side of the cockpit in order to see ahead during flight. Some Lloyd C.Vs (like the one modeled here) also included a "coffin-like" structure on the top of their upper wing, which housed a fixed forward firing machine gun. While the placement of the machine gun on the top of the upper wing was common among early World War I aircraft the addition of a surrounding enclosure was not. 

Lloyd C.Vs saw extensive service as reconnaissance aircraft with the Central Powers on the Eastern Front before Russia's withdrawal from World War I. Due to a relatively short range of operation they saw less use on the Western Front and because of poor performance at high altitudes; they saw very little service on the mountainous Italian Front. At the height of their service, 12 Fliks (squadrons) of the Austro-Hungarian Air Force were equipped with the Lloyd C. V. There were two major versions of the aircraft, the Lloyd C.V Series 46 with a 185 hp (138 kW) Daimler engine and the Series 46.5 with 220 hp (164 kW) Benz engine. ]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Flik (squadron) 13 D, Austro-Hungarian Air Force, Halic, Eastern Front, October, 1917.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Ungarische Lloyd Flugzeug und Motorenfabrik
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Austria-Hungary<br /><b>Power plant:</b> One Benz liquid-cooled piston engine of 220 hp (164 kW)<br /><b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 106 mph (170 km/h) 
Climb: 9,843 feet (3000 m) in 16 minutes 15 seconds
Endurance: 2 Hours 
Empty Weight: 1,900 pounds (820 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,613 pounds (1185 kg) 
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 36 feet 9 inches (11.19 m)
Length: 23 feet 8 inches (7.22 m)
Height: 9 feet 10 inches (3.00 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed forward-firing Schwarzlose 7.9mm (0.311 inch) machine gun in closed cabinet on top of upper wing, one Schwarzlose 7.9mm (0.311 inch) machine gun in a flexible mount in rear cockpit 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

