<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="111" cos="Turkey"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Albatros C.I (L6)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Albatros C.I was the first in a series of "C"reconnaissance aircraft built by the German aviation firm Albatros Werke GmbH. Albatros's aircraft distinguished themselves and were widely deployed during the entirety of the conflict. The C.I, which was designed by famous German aeronautical engineer Ernst Heinkel, utilized conventional wood & fabric construction with thin sheet metal surrounding the engine and forward fuselage. 

The C.I entered service with Germany in early 1915, but despite its success, was replaced by the improved Albatros C.III beginning in early 1916. Rather than retire the design, Germany then began supplying its C.Is to the Ottoman Empire. The Ottomans Empire, which had controlled the Middle East for generations, was disintegrating. The Turks desperately needed aircraft with which to patrol the vast desert areas of the empire and to conduct aerial attacks against a British-supported Arab insurrection. The Germans shipped numbers of their redundant Albatros C. I aircraft to Turkey in order to ensure that the Ottoman Empire remained an effective ally. 

The Turkish C.Is required modification to function in the desert environment. The aircraft's radiators were enlarged to allow for greater heat exchange and metal shutters were fitted over the radiators to keep out desert sand. The usual single forward firing machine gun was augmented with a second weapon and a light bomb load was provided for ground attack. Modified C.Is remained in service with the Turkish Air Force throughout the Middle East theater until the War's end. The aircraft modeled here is one of these modified Albatros C.Is in service with the Ottoman Empire.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the Ottoman (Turkish) Air Force, Palestine, Middle East Theater, July, 1917.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Albatroswerke GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany<br /><b>Power plant:</b> One Mercedes D III, 6 cylinder inline liquid cooled piston engine of 160 hp (119 kW)<br /><b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 82 mph (132 km/h)
Ceiling: 9,842 feet (3,000 m)
Endurance: 2 hours 30 minutes 
Empty Weight: 1929 pounds (875 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,615 pounds (1,140 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 42 feet 4 inches (12.90 m) 
Length: 25 feet 9 inches (7.85 m) 
Height: 10 feet 4 inches (3.14 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.9mm (0.31 inch) LMG 08/15 machine guns mounted on forward fuselage, one 7.9mm (0.31 inch) Parabellum machine gun in flexible mount in rear cockpit, 220 lbs (100 kg) of anti-personal fragmentation bombs
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

