<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="113" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Rumpler  <i>Taube</i> (Dove)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Rumpler  <i>Taube</i> was one of the earliest aircraft types in military service. In the decade following the Wright brothers' 1903 flight at Kitty Hawk, North Carolina, numerous aircraft manufacturing companies sprouted up across Europe. Each built aircraft for sale on the civilian market supporting wealthy sportsmen in their desire to fly. While these early aircraft were not designed for military purposes, military leaders of the pre-World War I era recognized the potential value of "flying machines" as reconnaissance platforms. The German aircraft industry was very active in the design and production of civilian machines. Five German firms Albatroswerke, Etrich-Flieger-Werke, Gotha Waggonfabrik, Harlan Verkaufs und Betriebs, and E.Rumpler Luftfahrzeugban all built aircraft which, because of their overall appearance and the configuration of their wings, came to be called “ <i>Tauben</i>” (doves). Of these, the Albatros and Rumpler  <i>Tauben</i> were acquired by the German Air Force.

All  <i>Tauben</i> were large single-winged monoplanes that used wing-warping for lateral control –a system which required a maze of wing-mounted cables and bracing wires. The Rumpler  <i>Taube</i> modeled here first flew in the summer of 1913. It was built from wood framing and doped fabric covering, except for metal sheeting around the engine in the forward fuselage. Configuration of these aircraft varied considerably, even among those built by the same manufacturer, as new innovations, engines and customer desires were incorporated into individual aircraft. As a result the specification information provided below should be considered nominal rather than definitive for all  <i>Tauben</i>. 

Like all of its early contemporaries, the Rumpler  <i>Taube</i> was unarmed. Furthermore, its construction, especially its under-carriage, was poorly suited for the rigors of military service on aerodromes -which were converted from farmers' fields- and so breakage was common. Worse, absent proper hangars, the machines sat in the open when not flying. There, the elements took their toll on the  <i>Tauben</i>' wood framing and fabric skins. 

Records show that a total of 60 Rumpler  <i>Tauben</i> were built, a number of which appeared on the rosters of the German Air Force at the beginning of World War I.  <i>Tauben</i> were noted for their stability and some quipped that a pilot could step out of the cockpit and lie down on the wing to nap and the aircraft would continue to fly along safely. However, by late 1915,  <i>Tauben</i> were no longer listed in the German Air Force inventory of aircraft, having likely been replaced by more modern and better performing machines. ]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Aufklarungsgruppe 3, German Air Force, August, 1914.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Rumpler-Werke A.G.
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany<br /><b>Power plant:</b> One Argus, 4 cylinder liquid cooled inline piston engine of 100 hp (75 kW)<br /><b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 59 mph (93 km/h)
Ceiling: Not documented
Endurance: 1 hour 45 minutes
Weight Empty: 1,102 pounds (500 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,342 pounds (609 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Dimensions
<b>Armament:</b> None
<b>Crew:</b>1 or 2<br/>]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

