<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="114" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Rumpler C.I (Typ 5A2)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Rumpler C.I occupies a special place in military aviation history. It represents the first airplane to fly photographic reconnaissance missions. It also claims one of the longest terms of active employment of any World War I aircraft. Because of its success, it remained deployed in an active combat role from early 1915 until February of 1918.

Design of the machine began shortly after the outbreak of the war by E. Rumpler Flugzeugwerke GmbH. Designed to be an armed reconnaissance craft, the C.I performed well from its introduction. It proved to be tough, well-armed, possessed of great endurance and, most importantly, difficult to shoot down. Over 2000 were built from mid 1915 until June of 1917 when production was terminated. 

In addition to flying for the German Air Force, Rumpler C.Is were employed by the Ottoman (Turkish) Air Force in Palestine and Macedonia. They provided great service during the battles for Gaza. Numbers of these machines remained in civilian service as light transports for several years after the war. Compared to its success, the Rumpler C.I has received little note in the history of World War I.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an armed reconnaissance aircraft of an unidentified reconnaissance unit, German Air Force, Western Front, June1917.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Rumpler-Werke A.G.
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Mercedes DIII, 6 cylinder liquid cooled inline piston engine of 160 hp (119 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 95 mph (152 km/h) 
Ceiling: 16,400 feet (6,000 m)
Range: Endurance: 4 hours 
Empty Weight: 1,745 pounds (793 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,867 pounds (1,333 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 39 feet 10 inches (12.15 m) 
Length: 25 feet 9 inches (7.85 m) 
Height: 10 feet 1 inch 3.06 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> One forward-firing 7.9mm (0.31 inch) drum-loading Spandau machine gun mounted atop upper wing, one 7.9mm (0.31 inch) Parabelum machine gun in flexible mount in rear cockpit
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

