<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="115" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Rumpler C.IV (Type 6A5 & 6A7)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The German aircraft firm E. Rumpler Flugzeugwerke GmbH built the C.IV as a long range reconnaissance platform to replace the earlier C.I model. The C.IV was a single-engine, two seat aircraft; it was larger than the C.I and was equipped with a more powerful engine. Aside from the size of the airframe and engine, the C.IV's construction did not differ much from its predecessor. Solidly constructed of metal and wood framing with a fabric covering, it could withstand considerable damage and remain airworthy. The C.IV also exhibited excellent performance characteristics and was able to outrun most allied scouts while flying at 15,000 feet.

Aside from its parent firm, the C.IV was also produced under license by the German company Pfalz. Although they were exactly the same aircraft, the Pfalz machines were given the designation Pfalz C.I. Their considerable virtues and excellent performance not withstanding, only 100 of both the Rumpler C.IV and the Pfalz C.I variants were ever built. The excellent performance of the C.IV allowed the aircraft to remain in service until the Armistice. For several years following WWI, modified C.IVs functioned as mail planes and small civilian passenger transports. By the mid 1920s they had all disappeared.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified reconnaissance unit, German Air Force, Western Front, October, 1917.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Rumpler-Werke A.G.
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> Power Plant: Mercedes D IIIa, 6 cylinder liquid cooled inline piston engine of 180 hp (134 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 104 mph (167 km/h) 
Ceiling: 16,500 feet (5,029m)
Endurance: 3 hours, 30 minutes
Empty Weight: 2,439 pounds (1106 kg)
Loaded Weight: 3439 pounds (1,558 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 44 feet 9 inches (13.6 m)
Length: 26 feet 1 inches (7.9 m)
Height: 11 feet 2 inches (3.4 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.9 mm (.311 inch) Spandau machine gun in fuselage nose, one 7.9 mm (.311 inch) Parabellum machine gun in a flexible mount in rear cockpit, 320 lbs (145 kg) bombs
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

