<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="117" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Floatplane]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[AGO Pusher Seaplane (1914)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[In early 1913, the German aviation company, AGO Flugzeugwerke (AGO) designed and built a reconnaissance seaplane for the German Navy. Its mission, in case of war, was to patrol the North Sea and follow the movements of the British Home Fleet based at Scapa Flow in the Orkney Islands. 

The AGO Seaplane is historic. It was probably the first aircraft to ever be constructed with amphibious capabilities. Positioned beneath each of its two pontoons were a pair of wheels and beneath its two tail pontoons were tail skids. These features allowed the AGO seaplane to take off and land from either land or sea. The aircraft was able to taxi into and out of the water on a concrete ramp. This ability proved advantageous by allowed the machine to quickly escape the corrosive effects of sea water when it was not flying. 

A large aircraft, the AGO Seaplane had typical construction for the time. Fabric covered the wood- frame of the aircraft's wings and tail surfaces while its fuselage and pontoons were covered with wood veneer. Two large petrol tanks were suspended beneath the upper wing endowing it with substantial operational endurance. 

At the outbreak of World War I in August of 1914, AGO Seaplanes of II.SFA patrolled the North Sea from their base at Wilhelmshaven. The patrols provided the German fleet -also based at Wilhelmshaven- intelligence on the movements of the British Navy, which was then the most powerful naval force in the world. Records indicate that during the opening weeks of the War, AGO Seaplanes played a role in following British ships involved in the naval blockade of Germany. 

The operational effectiveness of the AGO Seaplanes is unclear. Neither, is there reliable information available as to their duration of service. However, it is known that as of 1917, AGO Seaplanes were no longer listed in the inventory of operational German Naval aircraft.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of II Seefliegerabteilung (II.SFA) German Naval Seaplane Base, Wilhelmshaven, Germany, August, 1914.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> AGO Flugzeugwerke GmbH (AGO)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Argus, 8 cylinder inline V liquid-cooled piston engine of 150 hp (112kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 62 mph (100 km/h) 
Ceiling: Not documented
Range: Endurance 4+ hours
Empty Weight: 1804 pounds (817 kg)
Loaded Weight: Not documented
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 61 feet (18.59 m) 
Length: 39 feet (11.89 m) 
Height: 11 feet 10 inches (3.61 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> None
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

