<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="118" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[AGO C.II]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[Built by the German firm AGO Flugzeugwerke, the  AGO C.II, was among a group of flying machines designed and built in immediate response to the out break of World War I. Three variants -the AGO C.I, C.II, and C.III- were built by AGO Flugzeugwerke. All were similar in their external appearance, but the C.II was the most successful and was built in the largest numbers. All  AGO variants had wood framing with a varnished wood veneer covering the central gondola-like fuselage and the two laterally placed tail booms. The wings and tail were fabric covered. The machine was a "tail dragger" but had a pair of wheels forward of the fuselage to counter the possibility of a "nose-over" when taking off and landing on the rough surfaces of the airfields from which it operated. 

The AGO C.II was one of the few German aircraft types with a "pusher" configuration -the engine being at the rear of the machine's fuselage with its propeller pushing the aircraft through the air. German aircraft designers largely regarded this configuration as being inferior to the "tractor" type in which the machine's engine and propeller were positioned at the front of the aircraft thus pulling the machine through the air. 

The AGO C.II worked well, and proved to be maneuverable and relatively fast with a good operational range. Its crews, in general, regarded it favorably. Like all of the aircraft deployed during the earliest phases of the War, the C.II served as a reconnaissance platform. But the AGO C.II differed from other aircraft of the time in that it was armed with a machine gun in its forward cockpit manned by its observer. This was unique because, during the early phases of World War I, almost all military reconnaissance machines were unarmed. 

AGO C.IIs operated over the Western and Eastern Fronts during the later half of 1915 and most of 1916. By late 1916 they began to be replaced by more modern reconnaissance aircraft.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the German Air Force, Western Front, August, 1915.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> AGO Flugzeugwerke GmbH (AGO)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Benz Bz IV, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engine of 220 hp (164 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 86 mph (137 km/h) 
Ceiling: 14,764 feet (4,500 m)
Range: 360 miles (580 km) 
Empty Weight: 2,992 pounds (1,360 kg)
Loaded Weight: 4,281 pounds (1,946 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 47 feet 7 inches (14.50 m) 
Length: 32 feet 3 inches (9.84 m) 
Height: 10 feet 5 inches (3.18 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One Maxium IMG Parabellum 7.9mm (0.31 inch) machine gun in a flexible mount in the forward cockpit
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

