<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="121" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Harlan <i>Pfeiltaube</i>]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[Germany's first mass-produced military aircraft were called <i>Tauben</i> (Doves) -so named because of the bird-like shape of their wings. Austrian designer, Igo Etrich developed the first prototype <i>Taube</i>, before licensing the design the Rumpler aircraft. Variants of Etrich's design were soon being produced by at least 54 German and Austrian aircraft firms, including Harlan-Flugzeugwerke (modeled here), which produced at least four known variants. 

This aircraft was in that group of "flying machines" which were a part of the German Air Force when World War I erupted in August of 1914. Most <i>Tauben</i> featured a single aileron and unique split rudder configuration. Most variants, including this Harlan model were two-seat monoplanes. The <i>Taube</i> modeled here was a <i>Pfeiltaube</i> (Arrow Dove) variant, likely designed during 1912. <i>Pfeiltauben</i> were distinguished by their swept-back wings.

The Harlan <i>Taube</i> flew unarmed except for sidearms carried by pilots and served primarily in a reconnaissance role. The German Air Force acquired several of these machines in 1913 and they were available at the outbreak of World War I. The precise number of Harlan <i>Taube</i> aircraft deployed by Germany is unknown -probably very few because the initial 1913 acquisition was never augmented. It is known that during the first days of War, Germany flew <i>Tauben</i> during reconnaissance sorties in support of advancing German ground troops. 
The aircraft proved to be poorly suited to the rigors of combat service and their careers were very short lived. Their frail wood and fabric construction could not hold up to the rough fields and cow pastures from which they operated. Undercarriage damage and mechanical failures were common. By early 1915 the Harlan <i>Taube</i> had disappeared having been replaced by far better, more modern and more robust reconnaissance aircraft.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> Most Harlan <i>Tauben</i> displayed the manufacturer's name in large letters on the fuselage. This model depicts an aircraft repainted for military use.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an early civil aircraft adapted to use in WW I as a Reconnaissance Aircraft.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Harlan Werke GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Argus/Mercedes, 4 cylinder in line liquid cooled piston engine of 100 hp (75 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Speed: 62 mph (100 km/h)
Ceiling: 9,000 feet (2,750 m)
Endurance: 2 hours 15 minutes 
Empty Weight: 980 pounds (445 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,254 pounds (570 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 46 feet 9 inches (14.30 m)
Length: 34 feet 8 inches (10.6 m)
Height: 10 feet 10 inches (3.30 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>2
]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

