<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="122" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[LFG Roland <i>Pfeil</i> (Arrow) Biplane]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[First constructed in 1913, the Roland Arrow biplane included a very unusual feature in early aircraft design -swept back wings. At the time, the wings of most aircraft were fitted perpendicular to the aircraft's fuselage. Only a few rare models, often referred to as <i>Pfeilen</i> (arrows) featured swept wings. In fact, swept wings would not become the norm until the advent of jet-powered aircraft in the 1950s. 

The Roland Arrow was constructed by the Berlin-based manufacturing firm, Luftfahrzeug Gesellschaft (L.F.G.), which used the trade name, "Roland" to avoid confusion with another German firm, L.V.G. Aside from the unconventional wing configuration, L.F.G. utilized typical materials and construction methods when creating the Arrow. The aircraft was a two-seater consisting of a wood-framed fuselage covered in doped fabric and powered by a 100 h.p. Mercedes or Argus engine.

Like most pre-World War I aircraft, the Roland Arrow had been built for the civilian market. However, the type was counted among the aircraft in the German Air Service's inventory when World War I broke out in August of 1914. Like most of the earliest aircraft adopted for military use, the Roland Arrow was likely employed as a reconnaissance platform.

Records are silent as to the operational achievements of the Arrow biplane during World War I. Just before the War, however, a specially fitted Roland Arrow piloted by Bruno Langer made a non-stop flight of 16 hours duration. While the aircraft possessed excellent qualities for a pre-war design, its slow speed and lack of armament must surely have made military use untenable by 1915 when armed Allied fighters appeared in the skies over the Western Front.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified unit of the German Air Force, Western Front, August, 1914.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Luftfahrzeug Gesellschaft Roland (LFG)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Argus, 6 cylinder inline liquid cooled piston engine of 100 hp (75 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 59 mph (95 km/h) 
Ceiling: 9,900 feet (3,010 m)
Range: Endurance 2 hours 15 minutes 
Empty Weight: not documented
Loaded Weight: not documented 
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 42 feet 2 inches (12.85 m) 
Length: 26 feet 4 inches (8.03 m) 
Height: 10 feet 10 inches (3.30 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

