<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="124" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Otto B]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[When World War I broke out in August of 1914, Bavaria (the southern region of Germany) had its own air force. Although a part of the overall German air service, the Royal Bavarian Flying Corps had a surprising degree of autonomy. Bavaria also had its own aircraft manufacturing industry, which included the Munich-based company, Flugmaschinen-Werke Gustav Otto. 

In early 1913 the firm designed the biplane modeled here. In addition to marketing the new machine to wealthy sportsmen desiring to fly, Otto also sold several to the Royal Bavarian Flying Corps, which designated the aircraft the Otto B. With the onset of war, Bavaria deployed the aircraft on reconnaissance sorties in support of ground forces. 

The aircraft's construction was typical for the era -wood framing throughout with doped fabric covering its wings and tail surfaces and varnished plywood veneer covering its fuselage nacelle. An open strut framework supported the Type B's tail structures. The aircraft was configured as a "pusher", with its engine and propeller mounted on a steel framework at the rear of the fuselage. This was a design feature favored by Otto at a time when most other German firms considered pusher aircraft to be old fashioned. 

Unarmed, Otto's biplanes were confined largely to reconnaissance duties and artillery spotting, though some records suggest a few participated in at least one night raid on Dunkirk. The Type B's service period was brief. As the War progressed it became abundantly clear that the open-framed pusher aircraft, such as this one, were hopelessly obsolete. 

By early 1916 Otto Bs were no longer listed on Bavarian Flying Corps manifests. It is presumed that by that time they had all been struck from service. When Germany retired older combat aircraft from active service it often sent them to its ally, Bulgaria. Otto Type Bs may well have been among these, but, there is inadequate historical evidence to definitively confirm this.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> This model depicts an aircraft equipped with an Argus engine. Other sources indicate that Otto Bs were outfitted with Mercedes engines of similar horse-power.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Flieger-Abteilung 2, Royal Bavarian Flying Corps, Eastern Front, August, 1914.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Flugmaschinen-Werke Gustav Otto
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Argus, 4 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engine of 100 hp (75 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 69 mph (111km/h) 
Ceiling: not documented
Endurance: 2 hours, 45 minutes
Empty Weight: 1,013 pounds (460 kg)
Loaded Weight: not documented
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 48 feet 9 inches (14.86 m) 
Length: 35 feet 5 inches (10.80 m)
Height: 11 feet 5 inches (3.48 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>2
]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

