<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="126" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Gotha G.V]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Gotha twin-engine bombers entered service in 1916 just as the German High Command realized that using large, slow-moving Zeppelins for bombing missions over England was no longer practical. The Gotha G.IV and G.V (modeled here) bombers represented a viable replacement for the airships. The Gotha bombers proved so successful that all German twin-engine bombers were commonly called "Gotha" regardless of their manufacturer.

The G.IV and G.V differed little in their appearance and configuration. The chief difference between the two was the location of their fuel tanks -the IV's were located in the bottom of the engine nacelles, while the V's were in the center of the fuselage. The shift to the fuselage was to reduce the risk of fire due to the proximity of engine heat.

The Gotha machines included unique defensive armament modifications. Metal screens were mounted on either side of the rear gun position to prevent the gunner from accidentally shooting into the machine's "pusher" propellers. Gothas also had a "gun tunnel" the bottom of the rear fuselage immediately behind the gun position. This opening allowed the rear gunner to defend the traditional "blind spot"- that area behind and below the aircraft.

The first Gotha daylight raids on England began on May 25, 1917 and continued until September. During a single raid on June 13, 1917, Gotha G.V bombers dropped nearly 4,536 kg (10,000 pounds) of bombs on London killing 162 and wounding another 450 and causing great consternation among the British public. Early Gotha daylight raids experienced little opposition, but as Allied warning systems, anti-aircraft ground fire and fighter aircraft defenses improved, they began sustaining serious losses. Gotha operations were then shifted to night raids when opposition was less formidable.

Overall, the Gotha bombers were quite successful in creating discomfort among Allied civilian populations, especially Londoners. They were deployed in this role until the War's end.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> German daytime bombers were often painted in a light blue color, night bombers in a dark lozenge pattern. This model represents an aircraft configured for daytime operation.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Bombengeschwader 3 (Bomber Wing of the Army High Command), Ghent, German Occupied Belgium, May, 1917.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Gothaer Waggonfabrik AG
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> 
<b>Power plant:</b> Two Mercedes D IVa, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engines of 260 hp (194 kW) each
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 87 mph (140 km/h) at 12,000 feet (3,658 m) 
Ceiling: 21,320 feet (6,498 m)
Range: 305 miles (491 km) 
Empty Weight: 5,280 pounds (2,395 kg)
Loaded Weight: 7,997 pounds (3,627 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 77 feet 9 inches (23.70 m) 
Length: 40 feet 7 inches (12.37 m) 
Height: 14 feet 1 inch (4.29 m)
<b>Armament:</b> 7.9mm (0.31 inch) Parabellum machine guns in flexible mounts, (one in nose, one in dorsal rear fuselage) optional 3rd similar weapon in lower rear fuselage, 500 kg (1,102 pounds) of bombs
<b>Crew:</b>3
]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>


