<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="127" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Siemens-Schuckert Steffen R.I]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[Just four months after the outbreak of World War I, German aircraft manufacturer, Siemens-Schuckert (SSW) began construction on a series of seven highly unusual three-engine bombers designed by Bruno and Franz Steffen. The biplane aircraft incorporated an unconventional "forked" tail configuration designed to allow a clear field of fire to the rear. The planes were driven by two propellers mounted between the wings and powered by a series of three engines mounted in the fuselage. The machines also featured an enclosed cabin -another unusual feature for the time- giving the nose a distinctly bus-like appearance.

The first in the series, designated R.I (modeled here), took its maiden flight on May 24, 1915 and, after testing, arrived on the Eastern Front by October of that year. Unfortunately, it soon became apparent that the R.I was unfit for frontline service, and the machine was re-assigned as a trainer for future R-type crews. The following six versions of the aircraft, designated R.II-VII, featured improved engines and a redesigned forward fuselage. These aircraft also required modification after delivery before they were fit for combat. Like their predecessor, R.II and III were relegated to training duties but RIV-VII saw active duty on the Eastern Front with Riesenflugzeug-Abteilung 501 (Giant Aircraft Division 501), where they conducted bombing raids against Russian military and industrial targets.

In August of 1917, Rfa 501 was reassigned to the Western Front and re-equipped with the larger Zeppelin Staaken heavy bomber. The SSW R-series remains noteworthy as some of the first heavy bombers in aviation history. ]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents the prototype of the SSW R-series bombers. It served with a training unit of the German Air Force at Doeberitz, Germany, 1915.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Siemens-Schuckert Werke
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> Three Benz, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engines of 150 hp each (112 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 81 mph (130 km/h) 
Ceiling: 12,500 feet (3,810 m)
Range: 320 miles (515 km) 
Empty Weight: 11,910 pounds (5,402 kg)
Loaded Weight: not documented
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 92 feet (28.04 m)
Length: 57 feet 4 inches (17.48 m)
Height: 16 feet 1 inch (4.90 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One or two 7.9mm (0.31 inch) Maxim Parabellum machine guns in flexible mounts, 376 kg (830 pounds) of bombs
<b>Crew:</b>4 to 7]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

