<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="128" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Friedrichshafen G.III]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Friedrichshafen G.III was a large, fixed-wing bomber used to carry out nighttime bombings of Allied cities and military installations. The German aviation firm Flugzeugbau Friedrichshafen GmbH manufactured a total of 338 of these large machines. Unlike most bombers of the era, both of its engines were "pusher" mounted rather than the more common "tractor" type. The G.III could also carry a heavier bomb load than most aircraft of the era.

The G.III was developed as an alternative to the lighter-than-air Zeppelins first used on strategic bombing missions of Allied cities. The Allies responded to the early airship raids by developing night fighters capable of intercepting the slow-moving Zeppelins. The highly flammable airships proved to be easy targets for the fighters and German planners were forced to rethink their approach. Heavy bombers, like the G.III, as well as the Gotha G.V and the Zeppelin Staaken were created to replace the more vulnerable airships. The Friedrichshafen G.III first went into service with three bomber groups of the German Air Force in February of 1917. The G.III achieved considerable success in the nighttime bombing of Allied supply depots at Dunkirk, France, which disrupted Allied efforts on the Western Front. 

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> The prototype of the Friedrichshafen G.III modeled here was painted in a stippled dark overall coloration for its role as a night bomber.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Kampfgeschwader der Obersten Heeresleitung I, Western Front, June 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Flugzeugbau Friedrichshafen GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> Two Mercedes D IVa, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engines of 260 hp (194 kW) each
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 88 mph (142 km/h) at 3,280 ft (1,000 m) 
Ceiling: 14,700 feet (4,511 m) 
Endurance: 5 hours 
Empty Weight: 5,929 pounds (2,689 kg)
Loaded Weight: 8,686 pounds (3,940 kg) 
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 78 feet (23.77 m) 
Length: 42 feet (12.80 m) 
Height: 12 feet 3.66 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> Two 7.9mm (0.31 inch) Spandau machine guns in flexible mounts in nose and one in a dorsal position in mid fuselage, 1,497 kg (3,300 pounds) of bombs
<b>Crew:</b>0
<br />]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

