<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="129" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Albatros D.I (L15)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Albatros D.I was introduced in an attempt to wrest air superiority from the Allies' Nieuport 11 and D.H.2 fighters. The design of the D.I continued to refine Albatroswerke's pioneering development of all-wood fuselages. The aircraft exhibited very clean lines, broken only by the boxy radiator protruding above the engine. The fuselage was made of a semi-monocoque plywood construction, the surface of which was coated with a glossy varnish finish. Its wings and tail surfaces were of wood framing with fabric covering but intra-wing struts and wire bracing were kept to a minimum. The result of these features was a marked reduction in wind resistance. Powered by a large 160 hp engine, the D.I could carry the weight of twin machine guns and was very fast for the time. However, a rather high wing loading detracted from the aircraft's maneuverability. 

Following trials in August of 1916 the German High Command ordered 50 of the new machines, which began equipping fighter units on the Western Front the following November. Though it is unclear exactly how many D.Is entered service, reports indicate that total numbers on the front declined steadily from the initial delivery in November 1916. The Albatros D.I was almost immediately overtaken by its successor the Albatros D.II, the design and construction of which had begun very shortly after that of the D.I. Indeed, D.II production aircraft were arriving at the front only weeks after the arrival of the D.Is, and the latter aircraft soon appeared in much greater numbers. The two fighters differed only slightly in their external appearance, their performance, their speed and their firepower. However, the D.IIs were preferred by pilots due to the improved visibility afforded by their reduced intra-wing gap. 

Although manufactured in relatively small numbers, the Albatros D.I was a significant aircraft of World War I, if for no other reason, than it was the first in the lineage of the fine Albatros fighters, which became a mainstay of The German Air Force throughout the War.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents and aircraft of Jagdstaffel (squadron) 16, German Air Force, Western Front, December, 1916.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Albatroswerke GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Mercedes D III, 6 cylinder inline liquid cooled piston engine of 160 hp (119 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 110 mph (177 km/h) at sea level 
Ceiling: 17,000 feet (5,182 m)
Endurance: 1 hour, 30 minutes
Empty Weight: 1,488 pounds (675 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,976 pounds (896 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 28 feet 4 inches (8.64 m) 
Length: 24 feet 4 inches (7.42 m)
Height: 9 feet 8 inches (2.95 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.9mm (0.31 inch) LMG 08/15 machine guns mounted on upper forward fuselage 
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

