<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="130" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Albatros D.III (L20)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[British pilots nicknamed April of 1917, "Bloody April" in reference to the incredibly high losses they suffered during the course of the month. The German Albatros D.III fighter played a significant part in the British air losses that April. Several German aces flew the D.III that April, including Manfred von Richthofen -better known as, "the Red Baron"- Werner Voss, Ernst Udet, Eduard von Schleich and Bruno Lorzer.

The Albatros D.III was designed as a successor to the D.II and was built by its parent company Albatroswerke GmbH at Schneidemuhl, Germany. The project utilized data gathered from captured Nieuport Scouts and was launched in an effort to restore air superiority to the Central Powers.

Design and production of the new Albatros machine took place under the direction of Robert Thelen, an Albatros senior engineer. He adapted the sesquiplane style 11/2 V-strut wing of the highly successful French Nieuport Nie.17. He combined this wing with the semi-monocoque varnished plywood fuselage of his earlier Albatros D.II and installed within his new D.III fighter the Mercedes D.IIIa supercharged engine. The new engine gave the D.III excellent power and performance at high altitudes. 

The prototype D.III first flew in August of 1916, but wing failures due to excessive flexibility of its lower wing required structural alterations. These delays meant that the new aircraft did not reach operational combat units until the following December. The first unit to receive the D.III was Jasta 1, commanded by Manfred von Richthofen. By the spring of 1917, thirty-seven Jasta had been supplied with the D.III. The presence of the new aircraft shifted the balance of air superiority to the Central Powers. 

Production of the D.III continued until early 1918 after some 800 had been built. Manufacturing at Albatros was then shifted to their newer Albatros D.V and D.Va variants. Although given an even more powerful engine and improved aerodynamic styling, the D.V and D.Va were only marginally better than the D.III from which they were derived. The Albatros D.III remained competitive and served alongside its successors until the last day of World War I.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents a fighter of Jadgstaffel (Jasta) 5, Western Front, March, 1917.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Albatroswerke GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Mercedes D.IIIa, 6 cylinder inline liquid cooled piston engine of 180 hp (134 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 103 mph (165 km/h) 
Ceiling: 18,045 feet (5,500 m)
Endurance: 2 hours 
Empty Weight: 1,457 lbs (661 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,953 lbs (886 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 29 feet 8 inches (9.05 m)
Length: 24 feet 1 inch (7.33 m) 
Height: 8 feet 10 inches (2.98 m)
<b>Armament:</b> 2 fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.9mm (0.31 inch) LMG 08/15 machine guns mounted on upper forward fuselage 
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

