<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="134" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Fokker Dr.I Triplane (F.I)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Fokker Dr.I ('Dr.' standing for <i>Dreidecker</i>-or triplane) is perhaps the most famous aircraft of World War I.  Inspired by the success of the the British Sopwith Triplane, German military leaders commissioned several aviation firms to construct a comparable triplane aircraft. The Dr.I represents Fokker Flugzeug-Werke's response to this call. The Fokker Dr.I went into production and entered service in the skies of the Western Front in late 1917. The design proved very successful, achieving 21 victories during its first three weeks of operation. Some speculate that a number of these early victories occurred when allied pilots and gunners confused the new Dr.I for a British Sopwith Triplane, which it closely resembled. By the time the Dr.I was recognized as an enemy German fighter, it was too late.

The Fokker Dr.I Triplane's fame doubtless comes from its association with World War I's leading air ace, Baron Manfred von Richthofen -better known as the "Red Baron". Although he achieved the majority of his eighty air victories while flying in Albatros D. IIs, IIIs and Vs, it was while flying the Fokker Dr.I, during the last months of his career, that he garnered his greatest fame.

The Baron commanded Jagdstaffel 1, Germany's best and most feared fighter unit. Because the unit painted their aircraft in a variety of bright colors, it become known as the 'Flying Circus". Von Richthofen earned the nickname "Red Baron" from his Fokker Dr.I, which was painted a vivid red. While flying this red Fokker Dr.I (Nr. 425/17), he was shot down and killed over Sailly-le-Sec in the Somme Valley of France on the morning of April 21, 1918. It remains unclear whether he was killed by a bullet from an opposing Allied fighter aircraft with which he was engaged or by fire from Australian ground forces known to have been shooting at his low flying Dr.I. 

Despite its operational success, the Dr.I was plagued by structural problems throughout its career; problems which modifications in construction and retrofitting of existing machines did not totally correct.

Approximately 320 Dr.I's were built, far less than several other German fighter types. The "heyday" of the Dr.I was short - perhaps from February to June 1918 and the machine's overall impact on the air war over the Western Front was minimal. In the end, Dr.Is were replaced in German fighter units by the far superior Fokker D.VII aircraft. Nonetheless, the fame of the Fokker Dr.I lives on in the imagination of the public.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Jagdstaffel (squadron) 1, Western Front, April, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Fokker Aeroplanbau GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Thulin-built Le Rhône, 9 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 110 hp (82 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 103 mph at 13,125 feet (165 km/h at 4000 m)   
Ceiling: 19,685 feet (6000 m)
Endurance: 1 hour 30 minutes
Empty Weight: 695 pounds (406 kg)    
Loaded Weight: 1,289 pounds (585 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 23 feet 7 inches (7.19 m)
Length: 18 feet 11 inches (5.77 m)
Height: 9 feet 8 inches (2.95 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.92mm (.312 inch) LMG 08/15 machine guns   
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

