<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="135" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Fokker D.VII]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Fokker D.VII began arriving on the Western Front at the end of March, 1918. The immediate successor of the famous Fokker Dr.I triplane, the D.VII shared many characteristics of its predecessor. Both aircraft exhibited the same basic construction of wooden cantilever wings without bracing wires and a welded steel fuselage. The D.VII also retained the unique "one-piece" lower wing which slid through a cutout in the lower longerons allowing the wing's frame to pass all the way through the fuselage. The most obvious difference between the D.VII and its predecessor is that the Dr.I had three wings to the D.VII's two. The intra-wing struts also show some variation between the two aircraft.

Prior to the end of the War in November of 1918, some 775 machines reached 30 German fighter units. More than 3000 Fokker D VIIs were produced during the aircraft's entire production run both during and after World War I. The D.VII proved so formidable in combat that, after the War, the Treaty of Versailles specified that all of Germany's Fokker D.VII's be surrendered to the Allied Air Forces. The United States military sent many of these aircraft to the United States for analysis and they continued to fly in the United States throughout the 1920s. Builder Anthony Fokker continued to build and sell them in Holland after the conclusion of the war and more that 3000 were built during and after the war. 

This model of the Fokker D.VII replicates the aircraft flown by German World War I ace, Bruno Loerzer who scored 44 victories in combat over the Western Front.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> The aircraft of Bruno Loerzer upon which this model is based was painted in an unusual pattern of black and white stripes -certainly not a camouflage scheme by any stretch of the imagination.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Jagdstaffel (squadron) 26, Western Front, June, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Fokker Aeroplanbau GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Mercedes D III, 6 cylinder liquid-cooled inline piston engine of 160 hp (119kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 118 mph (189km/h)
Ceiling: 19,685feet (6000 m)
Endurance:: 1 hour 30 minutes
Empty Weight: 1,540 pounds (698 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1.940 pounds (880 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 29 feet 2 inches (8.90 m)
Length: 22 feet 10 inches (6.95 m)
Height: 9 feet 0 inches (2.75 m)
<b>Armament:</b> two 7.92 mm (.31 inch) LMG Spandau machine guns
<b>Crew:</b>1
<br />]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

