<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="137" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Albatros C.III (L10)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Albatros C.III succeeded the Albatros C.I as the manufacturer's operational armed reconnaissance aircraft. Designed by Ernst Heinkel, chief designer for Albatroswerke GmbH, the new C.III resembled its predecessor with a number of refinements. The C.III was slightly smaller than its predecessor, but was equipped with the same 150 or 160 h.p. power plant, resulting in better speed and rate of climb. Like the C.I, the C.III had wood framing. The fuselage was covered with a thin varnished plywood veneer, the wings and tail with doped fabric. Metal sheet surrounded the forward fuselage and engine. 

Flight trials of the new C.III in late 1915 were highly successful and the machine was immediately placed into mass production with its operational deployment beginning in the first weeks of 1916. Demand for the C.III was so great that in addition to its parent company it was also built under license by several other German firms. After reaching the Front, the C.III served with great distinction. Allied pilots found it robust and difficult to shoot down. Later deliveries of the C.III were also fitted with a propeller-synchronized machine gun, making the C.III the first two-gun operational C-type (German armed reconnaissance aircraft) and further adding to its defensive capability.

In the early summer of 1917 the C.III began to be replaced by a series of more advanced Albatros C-types. Albatros. Yet of all these C-type variants, the C.III was built in the greatest numbers and was deployed by the most units of the German Air Force. 

Following its withdrawal from frontline service the machine continued to be manufactured. Unarmed and fitted with dual controls, these later C.IIIs were widely used as trainers at German flight schools. Their deployment in this role continued until the war’s end. Of all Germany’s World War I C-type aircraft built by Albatros and other German manufacturers, the Albatros C.III was one of the most ubiquitous and most successful.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified unit of the German Air Force.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Albatroswerke GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Mercedes D III, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engine of 160 hp (119 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 87 mph (140km/h)
Ceiling: 12,140 feet (3,700 m)
Endurance: 4 hours 
Empty Weight: 1,876 lbs (851 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,983 lbs (1,353 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 35 feet 4 inches (16.69 m)
Length: 26 feet 3 inches (8.00 m)
Height: 10 feet 2 inches (3.10 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.9 mm (0.31 in) Spandau LMG 08/15 machine gun mounted on forward fuselage, one 7.9 mm (o.31 in) Parabellum LMG 14 machine gun in flexible Schneider mount in rear cockpit, 220 lbs (100 kg) of bombs carried in a fuselage bomb bay
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

