<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="138" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Floatplane Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Albatros W 4]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Albatros W.4 fulfilled the need for a German Naval fighter to counter the British flying boats in the North and Baltic Seas. Inspired by the earlier Albatros D.I and D.II, the W.4 retained the fuselage and the power plant of the Albatros D.II, but included new wings and tail structures. Twin floats replaced the wheels to equip it for marine operations. Fabric covered the majority of the fighter's wooden frame, except for the engine housing and floats, which were covered with thin metal sheeting. 

Design flaws plagued early W.4s. A transparent Cellon panel, mounted in the center upper wing section to improve the pilot's vision, proved to be brittle and prone to tearing off in flight. These were soon replaced by traditional fabric. The W.4 also experienced problems with its engine's two radiators. The radiators, which were uniquely positioned on either side of the fuselage, often boiled over in warm weather. Later versions of the W.4 switched to a single flush mounted radiator located in the center of the upper wing. This arrangement proved to be more satisfactory.

The German Air Force employed the W.4 to counter naval reconnaissance and U-boat hunting missions conducted by British flying boats in the North Sea and Baltic Sea. World War I records are vague about the success or failure of the operations of the W.4. With 128 machines built in all, it can be assumed that they were reasonably successful. At the War's end, various seaplane stations on the Baltic coast still listed 65 of these machines in active service.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft from Windau Air Station, German Air Force, Baltic Coast, February 1917.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Albatroswerke GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Daimler D III, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engine of 160 hp (119 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 99 mph (159 km/h) at sea level 
Ceiling: 9,840 feet (2,999 m) 
Endurance: 2 hours 15 minutes 
Empty Weight: 1,738 pounds (788 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,356 pounds (1,069 kg) 
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 31 feet 2 inches (9.47 m) 
Length: 27 feet 10 inch (8.48 m) 
Height: 11 feet 11 inches (3.63 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> : Two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.9mm (0.31 inch) LMG 08/15 machine guns 
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

