<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="141" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Pfalz D.IIIa]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Pfalz D.IIIa was a single bay biplane designed by Rudolf Gehringer, the senior engineer at the German firm, Pfalz Flugzeugwerke. The D.IIIa added modified wing tips and a new and more powerful engine to the original D.III model. The D.IIIa also somewhat resembled the earlier German L.F.G. Roland D.I and D.II fighters. 

The D.IIIa's structure allowed for an aerodynamic, efficient, and sturdy aircraft. The craft's wooden fuselage frame was covered by a thin wood veneer, allowing for a smooth, varnished finish. The machine's wings and tail also incorporated wood framing. These components, however, were covered with a doped fabric - a common construction technique of the time. 

The Pfalz D.III served as one of the main German fighters from late 1917 until summer 1918. The D.IIIa did not enter service until 1918. The D.IIIa reached its peak deployment on the Western Front in April 1918. At that time, German fighter units employed 433 of these machines. These aircraft, however, were gradually phased out in favor of the vastly superior Fokker D.VII. About 600 D.IIIs were manufactured during World War I, and about 350 remained in service in August 1918.

The aircraft modeled here was flown on the Western Front during the last months of World War I by Carl von Degelow, a member of the Jadgstaffel (squadron) 40, Germany Air Force.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Jadgstaffel (squadron) 40, German Air Force, Western Front, June 1918  ]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Pfalz Flugzeugwerke GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Daimler D.IIIa, 6 cylinder inline liquid cooled piston engine of 180 hp (119 kW)  
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 102 mph at 9,842 feet (164 kW at 3000 m) 
Ceiling: 17,060 feet (5200 m)
Endurance: 2 hours, 30 minutes  
Empty Weight: 1,521 pounds (690 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,061 pounds (935 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 30 feet 10 inches (9.40 m)
Length: 22 feet 9 inches (6.93 m)
Height: 8 feet 9 inches (2.67 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing 7.92 mm (0.310 inches) LMG 08/15 synchronized machine guns. 
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

