<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="142" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Pfalz D.XII]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Pfalz D.XII represents one in a line of fighters built by Pfalz Flugzeugwerke, a Bavarian aviation company formed by three brothers of the Evertbusch family before World War I. This firm acquired the rights to build aircraft from the French company, Morane-Saulnier and later from the firm LFG Roland. With the experience gleaned from these early efforts, Pfalz Flugzeugwerke began to design and manufacture its own fighter aircraft after the outbreak of World War I. 

The Pfalz D.XII, modeled here, improved upon its immediate predecessor, the D.III. Like its predecessor, the new D.XII was also a biplane. It possessed all wood construction with a thin plywood veneer over its fuselage. The D.XII's wings, tail surfaces and all of its control surfaces were fabric covered. Because of its sturdy construction, the D.XII could dive faster and steeper than most all of its contemporaries. After competitive trials with other new fighter designs in mid 1918, the German military contracted for 500 D.XIIs to be built. 

The D.XII did have a drawback. It was not able to make a tight turn in flight and was far more sluggish in combat than the other new German fighter to arrive in mid 1918-the Fokker D.VII. The poor control response made the new Pfalz D.XIIs unpopular with German fighter pilots, who preferred the new Fokker D.VIIs. 

Notwithstanding their shortcomings, by the end of the War nearly 800 Pfalz D.XIIs had been built and placed into front-line service on the Western Front.  Following World War I, numbers of these Pfalz D.XIIs were taken in hand by the victorious Allied air services. After evaluation, they deemed these aircraft to be inferior to other German fighters and the most modern Allied fighters. Four Pfalz D.XII aircraft have survived into the 21st Century and are on display in air museums in the United States, Australia and France.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Jagdstaffel (squadron) 77, Bavarian Air Service, Western Front, October 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Pfalz Flugzeugwerke GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> Power plant: One Daimler D IIIa, 6 cylinder liquid-cooled, inline piston engine of 180 hp (134 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 112 mph (180 km/h)   
Ceiling: 18,500 feet (5,650 m)
Endurance: 2 hours, 30 minutes    
Empty Weight: 1,590 pounds (722 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,990 pounds (902 kg)    
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 29 feet 6 inches (9.00 m)  
Length: 20 feet 10 inches (6.35 m) 
Height: 8 feet 10 inches (2.70 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing 7.9mm (0.31 inch) LMG 08/15 synchronized machine guns in fuselage nose    
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

