<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="143" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[A.E.G. D.I]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The German firm, Allgemeine Elektizitäts Gesellschaft (A.E.G) designed the D.I as a new fast and highly maneuverable fighter aircraft for the German Air Force. The new machine was the product of a collaboration between George Konig, A.E.G.'s chief design engineer, and Walter Hohndorf, a decorated German World War I ace and famous test pilot who brought his considerable flying and combat experience to the project. 

The A.E.G. D.I incorporated a number of unique features in its design. Its airframe was built entirely of steel tubing, rare at a time when almost all aircraft framing was wood. Further, a single steel spar supported the entire length of its wings making it possible to greatly reduce the supplemental wing bracing so common on other contemporary biplane aircraft. At Hohndorf's insistence, the aircraft also included an enormous exhaust pipe exiting the engine along the starboard side of the fuselage and extending behind the cockpit. The pipe was included in order to reduce distracting and deafening engine noise. 

The new fighter made its first appearance in May of 1917 and formal flight evaluations began at the German Air Force's test facility at Adlershot, Germany on June 28, 1917. The aircraft exhibited excellent maneuverability coupled with a speed of nearly 130 mph in level flight -among the fastest of all World War I aircraft. On August 21, 1917, in the course of its evaluation, a prototype D.I was placed into strenuous flight maneuvers by the highly skilled test pilot Lieutenant Julius Hendricks. During these maneuvers the machine went into a steep uncontrolled dive and crashed, killing Hendricks. Since the new fighter had displayed significant promise, testing of the D.I continued despite the crash. 

To further evaluate the A.E.G. D.I under actual combat conditions on the Western Front, at least one prototype was sent to Jasta 14, a fighter unit commanded by Hohndorf himself. On September 5, 1917, when flying the fighter he had helped design (No. D 4400 modeled here), Hohndorf crashed and was killed. An investigation revealed he crashed due to a mechanical failure of the aircraft. 

With the death of two outstanding and experienced pilots blemishing its record, Idflieg (the German Air Force High Command) canceled the A.E.G. D.I program. The remaining airframes were relegated to German Air Force flight schools as grounded hulks in the training of maintenance crews -an inauspicious end to the racy little fighter, which had initially looked so promising.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents a WW I single seat biplane fighter, which underwent flight testing with Jagdstaffel (squadron) 14.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Allgemeinen Electrizitäts Gesellschaft (A.E.G.)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Mercedes D.III, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engine of 160 hp (119 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 127 mph (205 km/h)
Ceiling: 16,400 feet (5,000 m)
Range: 290 miles (465 km)
Empty Weight: 1,510 pounds (685 kg)
Loaded Weight 2,072 pounds (940 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 27 feet 11 inches (8.50 m)
Length: 20 feet (6.10 m)
Height: 8 feet 8 inches (2.65 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.9 mm (0.31 in) LMG 08/15 machine guns mounted atop upper forward fuselage 
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

