<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="145" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Albatros C.X (L25)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Albatros C.X represents the pinnacle of a successful lineage of "C" class reconnaissance aircraft developed by German manufacturer, Albatroswerke. From the first weeks of the War until the Armistice, the series of Albatros reconnaissance aircraft was deployed in large numbers on all fronts by the German and Austro-Hungarian Air Forces. As the lineage progressed, its successive variants were equipped with ever more powerful engines, improved internal framing, along with increases in weight, size, and wing span. Despite these alterations, all the variants retained the same general appearance and the same excellent flight characteristics.

The C.X entered service in 1917 on the heels of its predecessor, the C.VII. The C.X included a larger fuselage, which provided space for the installation of an oxygen system in the pilot's forward cockpit, and radio equipment in the rear cockpit. The aircraft was powered by a 260 hp Mercedes engine -a significant increase in power over its predecessor. The C.X's wingspan was also extended, and ailerons were added to all four wingtips in order to maintain its level of maneuverability.

By October of 1917, some 300 Albatros C.Xs were in operation with multiple German reconnaissance units. The aircraft continued to operate until the end of the War. The final variant in the Albatros lineage, the C.XII began to appear in late 1917. However, because the C.XII provided only minor improvements over the C.X and because the earlier aircraft had a substantially longer operational career, the C.X has been chosen to represent the entire Albatros lineage in this collection.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified reconnaissance unit of the German Air Force, Western Front, June, 1917.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Albatroswerke GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Mercedes D IVa, 6 cylinder liquid-cooled inline piston engine of 260 hp (194 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 109 mph (175 km/h) at seal level 
Ceiling: 16,405 feet (5,000 m)
Endurance: 3 hours 25 minutes
Empty Weight: 2,176 pounds (987 kg)
Loaded Weight: 3,410 pounds (1,547 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 47 feet 1 inch (14.35 m) 
Length: 30 feet 1 inch (9.71 m)
Height: 11 feet 2 inches (3.40 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.9mm (0.31 inch) Spandau machine gun mounted on starboard side of forward fuselage, one Maxium 7.9mm (0.31 inch) IMG Parabellum machine gun in flexible mount in rear cockpit, 100 kg (220 pounds) of bombs 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

