<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="147" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Infantry Support Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Halberstadt CL.II]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Halberstadt CL.II was unique among its World War I contemporaries. In late 1916 the Idflieg (the German Air Force General Staff) conceived a machine which could function as a reconnaissance platform (a C-type), an infantry support aircraft (a J-type) and at the same time have sufficient attributes to be completive as a fighter (a D-type). Such an amalgamation of features was an ambitious order for aeronautical designers of the time. But German firm, Halberstädter Flugzeug-Werke GmbH, created an aircraft that exceeded expectations. 

The CL.II was constructed of wood framing with a thin plywood veneer covering its fuselage. Plywood also covered the center section of the upper wing which contained a flush-fit radiator for the machine's liquid-cooled engine. All of its other surface areas were covered with a doped fabric. The CL.II had a powerful engine and aerodynamically smooth appearance. The plane had only two sets of thin metal intra-wing struts and a minimum of bracing wires. This greatly reduced wind resistance and gave the CL.II outstanding performance. 

After wildly successful flight trials on May 17, 1917 the CL.II was ordered into production. It entered service on the Western Front in August of 1917 where it achieved immediate acclaim due to its excellent maneuverability, speed and climb rate. These features combined with the wide field of fire provided by the configuration of the machine's design, allowed the rear gunner to effectively engage enemy single seat fighters on equal terms. The CL.II also became the mainstay of the <i>Schlachtstaffeln</i> (close air-support squadrons). Seven-hundred CL.IIs were built by Halberstadt and demand for the aircraft became so great that a further 200 were produced, under license, by the German firm Bayerisvhe Flugzeugwerke (BFW). The machines remained in active front line service until the War's end. 

The colorful Halberstadt CL II modeled here was unit #14277/17 which on June 4, 1918 crashed on takeoff at its aerodrome in Bissenghem, Germany, seriously injuring its pilot, Paul Schwarze, and killing its gunner, Franz Schumm. Although not airworthy, a single World War I era CL II survives today on display at the Polish Aviation Museum in Cracow, Poland.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Schlachtstaffel (infantry-support squadron) 26b, Bissenghem Airdrome, Bissenghem, Germany, June, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Halberstädter Flugzeug-Werke GmbH
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Mercedes DIII, 8 cylinder liquid-cooled inline piston engine of 160 hp (119 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 102 mph (165 km/h) 
Ceiling: 16,400 feet (5,000 m)
Endurance: 3 hours 
Empty Weight: 1,704 pounds (773 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,498 pounds (1,133 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 35 feet 4 inches (10.76 m) 
Length: 23 feet 11 inches (7.30 m) 
Height: 9 feet 0 inches (2.75 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.9mm (0.31 inch) LMG 08/15 machine gun mounted on the port side of the forward fuselage, one 7.9mm (0.31 inch) Parabellum LMG 14/17 machine gun in flexible mount in rear cockpit, 110 lbs (50 kg) of bombs.
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

