<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="149" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Escort Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Hannover CL.IIIa]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[In the early summer of 1917 the <i>Idflieg</i> (German Inspectorate of Flying Troops) issued a specification to the German aircraft industry for a new "CL" class of aircraft which could serve as escorts for the larger C-class reconnaissance planes. The Hannover based firm Hannoversche Waggonfabrik AG responded with a new machine designated the Hannover CL.II. Two further variants of the aircraft soon followed and differed only in their engines and wingtip design. These were the CL.III and the CL.IIIa (modeled here). 

The CL.IIIa was a compact, two-seat biplane. It featured a plywood-covered fuselage that was highly resistant to battle damage. The aircraft's wings and tail structures had wood framing with a doped fabric covering. The Hannover aircraft also included an unusual biplane tail. This configuration was adopted to reduce the span required when only a single tail plane was employed. The tail design reduced blind spots and gave the observer/gunner a broader field of fire. The crew's visibility was also aided by the position of the top wing, which was almost level with the top of the fuselage.

Prototype flight trials were completed in November of 1917. While the new machine had average speed, its robustness, handling, and rate of climb were outstanding. The new model was given rave reviews by its test pilots and manufacture of the aircraft was immediately ordered by the Idflieg. 

Production aircraft equipped schutzstaffeln (protection squadrons) of the German Air Force by January of 1918. Allied pilots often mistook the two-seat escorts for single-seat fighters, not realizing their mistake until the rear gunner fired off a stream of bullets from his Parabellum machinegun. The CL.IIIa proved to be a formidable opponent even after the allies knew what they were dealing with. The aircraft's plywood skin made it bullet resistant and very difficult to shoot down.

Although they arrived quite late on the scene, 537 CL.IIIa's were placed into service with the German Air Force during the final ten months of the War. During that interval they were among the most numerous reconnaissance and escort aircraft deployed by the Germans on the Western Front, the only theater over which the Hannover CL.IIIa operated.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Flieger Abteilung 7, German Air Force, Western Front, October, 1918. ]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Hannoversche Waggonfabrik A.G.
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Opel Argus AS III, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engine of 180 hp (134 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 108 mph (174 km/h) 
Ceiling: 24,600 feet (7,500 m)
Endurance: 3 hours 
Empty Weight: 1653 pounds (750 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,447 pounds (1110 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 38 feet 5 inches (11.71 m) 
Length: 24 feet 10 inches (7.57 m)
Height: 9 feet 2 inches (2.79 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.9 mm (.31 inch) LMG 08/15 machine guns mounted atop forward fuselage, one 7.9 mm (.31 inch) Parabellum machine gun in flexible mount in rear cockpit 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

