<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="154" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Floatplane Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Brandenburg KDW]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[In early 1916, the German Navy issued a specification for a seaplane defensive fighter. The German firm Hansa-Brandenburg based at Warnemunde-Rostock responded with the Brandenburg KDW. The new seaplane was essentially a modified version of an existing land based fighter -the Hansa-Brandenberg D.I. 

The land-based D.I was deployed almost exclusively by Germany's ally, the Austro-Hungarian Empire. Although reasonably fast, the D.I had experienced very limited success. The aircraft suffered from poor stability and flight qualities, which rendered it inferior to its Allied opposition. Except for two pontoons in place of wheels, the new KDW shared the same construction as the D.I. Like its predecessor, the KDW utilized a unique system of intra-wing struts with four sets of triangular posts meeting at their apex giving the struts a "star-like" appearance. This arrangement eliminated the need for additional bracing wires thus reducing wind resistance and, like it did for the D.I, gave the KDW excellent speed. However, the KDW also inherited the D.I's poor stability and handling, which were only made worse by the added weight of its pontoons. 

When KDW seaplanes became operational in late 1916, they were able to engage reconnaissance seaplanes and large slow moving bombers with a reasonable chance of success, but they were at a distinct disadvantage in combat with contemporary land-based fighters. KDW No. 748, modeled here was the first prototype built, but records indicate it also saw operational service. This particular aircraft was based at the German Seaplane facility at Angernsee. The KDW's finest moment occurred on September 23, 1916 when No. 748 flown by Lieutenant Fritz Hammer engaged a Russian Sikorsky Ilya Muromets heavy bomber. Making repeated passes, Hammer severely damaged the bomber, forcing it to crash land in a nearby meadow. During all of World War I only two of Sikorsky's giant bombers were ever shot down, making this air victory a very historical event. 

The KDW was eventually replaced by the Albatros W.4 -another German seaplane fighter- which had far superior flight capabilities and armament. Of the nearly 2,500 aircraft deployed by the German Naval Air Service during the War, only 58 were Brandenburg KDWs.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> This model depicts a KDW equipped with a chimney-style exhaust stack. While this was a common configuration for KDWs, aircraft No. 748 was constructed with stubbier exhaust pipes on the port side of the nose.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of I Seefliegerabteilung (I.SFA), Seeflugstation Angernsee, Baltic Coast, September, 1916.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Hansa und Brandenburgische Flugzeugwerke AG
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Benz Bz. III, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engine of 150 hp (112 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 106 mph (171 km/h) at sea level 
Ceiling: 9,900 feet (3,010 m)
Endurance: 2 hours, 30 minutes 
Empty Weight: 2,068 pounds (931 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,662 pounds (1.198 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 30 feet 4 inches (9.25 m) 
Length: 26 feet 3 inches (8.0 m) 
Height: 10 feet 11 inches (3.3 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.9 mm (0.31 inch) LMG 08/15 machine gun mounted on starboard side of forward fuselage. The last 20 production aircraft mounted twin LMG 08/15 guns. 
<b>Crew:</b>0
<br />]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

