<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="155" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Floatplane Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Brandenburg W 29]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Hansa-Brandenburg W 29 seaplane was developed as a replacement for the earlier W.12, which had seen some success during combat patrols over the North Sea and English Channel. The W 29 made use of the W 12's fuselage, but switched to a low-winged monoplane configuration. The prototype W 29's also sported a new 195 hp Benz engine. This was replaced in production models by the 150 hp Benz, which powered late-model W.12s. The W 29's fuselage was of wood framing covered with a smooth plywood veneer. Thin metal alloy surrounded its engine and radiator. Its wings and tail surfaces were fabric covered and its pontoons were metal. Like its predecessor the W.12, the W 29 had an unconventional inverted rudder, designed to provide the gunner with a clear rearward field of fire.

Despite its unorthodox appearance, the seventy-plus known W 29 floatplane fighters, which were manufactured, delivered very impressive performance and became a significant factor in the skies over the North Sea. W 29s flying from Zeebrugge disabled the British submarine C25, sank several torpedo boats and downed a number of British flying boats. These successes lead Allied flying boat crews to regard the Hansa-Brandenburg W 29 with a healthy respect. ]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Seeflugstation, German Naval Air Station Flanders, North Sea, May 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Hansa und Brandenburgische Flugzeugwerke AG
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Benz Bz.III, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engine of 150 hp (112 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 109 mph (175 km/h) 
Ceiling: 16,405 feet (5000 m)
Endurance: Over 4 hours 
Empty Weight: 2,205 pounds (1000 kg)
Loaded Weight: 3,296 pounds (1495 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 44 feet 4 inches (13.51 m)
Length: 30 feet 8 inches (9.35 m)
Height 9 feet 11 inches (3.02 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.92 mm (0.312 inch) LMG 08/15 machine guns, one mounted on each side of forward fuselage, one 7.92 mm (0.312 inch) Parabellum machine gun in a flexible mount in the rear cockpit 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

