<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="156" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Floatplane Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Brandenburg W 12]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Brandenburg W 12 was a two-seat seaplane fighter which began replacing the single-seat Albatros W.4 beginning in the spring of 1917. Designed by Ernst Heinkel, for aviation firm, Hansa und Brandenburgische Flugzeugwerke , the W 12 was distinguished by its unique tail configuration -the vertical stabilizer on the W 12 extended below the fuselage instead of above. This configuration provided the aircraft's gunner with a clear field of fire. This unorthodox tail structure would be repeated on several later seaplane designs.

The W 12 first appeared in early 1917 and began equipping the German seaplane station at Zeebrugge, Belgium where they engaged in patrols over the English Channel. On December 11, 1917 a W 12 piloted by station commander, Friedrick Christiansen downed the British Airship C27. 

A total of 145 W 12s had been built when production ended in June of 1918. They remained in combat until the last day of WWI. They remained in combat until the end of the War later that year.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the German Imperial Naval Air Service, Zeebrugge, Belgium, March, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Hansa und Brandenburgische Flugzeugwerke AG
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> One Benz Bz III, 6 cylinder inline liquid cooled piston engine 150 hp (112kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 100 mph (161 km/h)
Ceiling: 16,406 feet (5000 m)
Endurance 3 hours 30 minutes
Empty Weight: 2,193 pounds (995 kg)
Loaded Weight: 3206 pounds (1,454 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 36 feet 9 inches (11.2 m)
Length: 31 feet 6 inches (9.6 m)
Height: 10 feet 10 inches (3.1 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One or two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.9mm (.311 inch) LMG 08/15 machine guns, one 7.9mm (.311 inch) Parabellum machine gun in a flexible mount in rear cockpit 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

