<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="157" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[A.E.G. G.IV]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The A.E.G. G.IV represents the final model in the Allgemeinen Elektrizitäts Gesellschaft (A.E.G.) line of twin-engine bombers to serve in WWI. The G.IV was the first aircraft in the line to be produced in significant numbers. The aircraft utilized the same Mercedes D.IVa powerplants as Germany's heavy bombers, the Gotha G.III and Friedrichschafen G.III, but lacked the range and carrying capacity to make it effective as a heavy bomber. As such, the G.IV was largely used for short-range tactical bombing raids.

The G.IV included a number of advanced design features. The aircraft were equipped with radios, and the pilots wore electrically heated flight suits to keep warm. The G.IV also utilized balanced controls, welded steel tubular framing and steel wing spars and tail structures. The steel construction gave the G.IV great strength but also increased its weight, which dramatically reduced its bomb load and operational range. 

A total of 542 A.E.G. G-type bombers were built. The bombers saw service in France, Greece, Romania and Italy. While they initially flew both day and night missions, as the war progressed, the G.IVs were largely restricted to nighttime operations. Fifty of the aircraft remained in service until the end of the War.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft thought to be of Kampfstaffel (battle squadron) 17, German Air Force, Western Front, December, 1916.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Allgemeinen Electrizitäts Gesellschaft (A.E.G.)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> Two Mercedes D IVa, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engines of 260 hp (194 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 103 mph (166 km/h)
Ceiling: 14,760 feet (4,499 m)
Range: 231 miles (372 km)
Empty Weight: 5,280 pounds (2,395 kg)
Loaded Weight: 7,130 pounds (3,240 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 60 feet 4 inches (18.4 m)
Length: 31 feet 10 inches (9.7 m)
Height: 12 feet 9 inches (3.9 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two 7.9mm (.311 inch) Maxim IMG Parabellum machine guns in flexible mounts -one in the nose of the fuselage, one in the rear fuselage position, up to 880 pounds of bombs
<b>Crew:</b>3]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

