<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="159" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Zeppelin-Staaken R.VI]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Zeppelin-Staaken R.VI represents the largest fixed-wing aircraft of World War I. It could carry two 2,200 lb bombs; no other bomber had been capable of carrying even one before that time. Its wingspan measured over 138 feet. It weighed over 12 and a half tons when empty, requiring 12 or, on some machines, 16 wheels to support this weight. Each of its four engines powered an enormous 14 foot 5 inch propeller.

The Zeppelin-Staaken R.VI was designed to bomb major Allied cities, especially London. The bomber was huge, relatively slow and not very maneuverable. To make its missions more effective, the R.VI operated at night when it would be less vulnerable to Allied attack. Its paint scheme consisted of an overall dark mottled blue or a dark lozenge pattern, designed to camouflage the machine during night operations. Even the German black iron-cross insignias were applied without their usual white backgrounds to enhance the machine's stealth. 

With their large size, the Zeppelin-Staakens were time-consuming and costly to manufacture. Only 18 were built in all. Of those 18, the last two of the series added a fifth engine to the original design. Mounted in the fuselage behind the enclosed crew cabin, the fifth engine powered superchargers for the aircraft's four propeller-driving engines. This new revolutionary advance allowed these two Zeppelin-Staakens to reach a height of almost 20,000 feet even when carrying a full bomb load. Since Allied fighters and anti-aircraft ground fire could not function efficiently at such altitudes, the five-engined R.VIs were almost immune to Allied defenses. This model represents one of these five-engine versions.

Despite their few numbers, these bombers caused considerable damage. During the final months of World War I, Zeppelin-Staaken R.VIs flew 52 raids over London dropping 2,772 bombs weighing a total of 196 tons. On the night of February 16, 1918, a Zeppelin-Staaken dropped the first 2,200 lb bombs ever deployed in warfare. One hit the Royal Hospital in Chelsea, killing or injuring much of the medical staff and many of the institution's patients, the majority of whom were wounded soldiers from the Western Front. To date, the Zeppelin-Staaken R.VI remains the largest bomber ever to have attacked England.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents a heavy bomber of the Reisenflugzeugabteilungen 500, German Flying Corps, operating from Northern Occupied France.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Zeppelin-Staaken Flugzeugwerke
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> Five Mercedes D IVa, 6 cylinder liquid-cooled piston engines of 260 hp each (194 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 84 mph (135 km/h) 
Ceiling: 12,467 feet (supercharged variants- 19,686 feet) (3,800 m/6,000 m)
Endurance: 7 - 10 hours depending on bomb load 
Empty Weight: 17,426 pounds (7,921 kg) 
Loaded Weight: 27,778 pounds (12,600 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 138 feet 6 inches (42.21 m) 
Length: 72 feet 6 inches (22.25 m) 
Height: 20 feet 8 inches (6.60 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Up to four Spandau 7.9mm (0.31inch) IMG Parabellum machine guns in flexible mounts- in the nose, in ventral and dorsal positions, mid fuselage, 4,409 lbs. (2,000 kg) of bombs 
<b>Crew:</b>7]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

