<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="160" cos="Germany"> 
<type><![CDATA[Airship Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Zeppelin L 30]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Zeppelin L 30, modeled here, was chosen to represent Germany's fleet of wartime airships within this collection. It was the first of seventeen R-class "super-Zeppelins"-a class of airships larger than earlier machines which could carry larger bomb loads and could fly higher and faster. 

Five decades before the outbreak of World War I, Count Ferdinand von Zeppelin, an officer in the Prussian Calvary, ventured to the United States to serve as an Army observer during the American Civil War. There, he witnessed tethered balloons being used for battlefield observation. Deeply impressed, he returned to Germany where he began the development of the world's first rigid and propeller driven airships. So profound was the Count's influence that the name Zeppelin was commonly applied to all such aircraft. 

Though originally designed for civilian transport purposes, Zeppelins were soon adapted for military use. With the outbreak of World War I, many civilian airships were pressed into service. After initial sorties as tactical bombers and observation platforms proved impractical, Zeppelins were instead assigned to bomb civilian population centers, particularly London and Paris. The Zeppelin raids on these cities during World War I mark some of the first examples of strategic bombing missions -attacks against population centers intended to disrupt industry and demoralize an enemy.

Lifted by multiple gas cells filled with flammable hydrogen, Zeppelins primarily relied on their ability to climb above the range of enemy aircraft and ground fire. While early raids encountered little resistance, the British and French soon modified selected fighters to fly higher and armed their machine guns with incendiary bullets. Hydrogen filled Zeppelins began to be shot from the sky in flames. Zeppelin bombing raids were also largely conducted at night, but even though they were painted black for stealth, their huge size made them easy targets.

Super Zeppelins like the L 30 were developed in an effort to stay ahead of Allied defensive capabilities by climbing ever higher. Unfortunately, the continued advancement of aircraft technology met the airships step for step. Nevertheless, the L 30 had a long and successful career. It conducted 31 reconnaissance flights and 9 raids over England and was one of the few German airships to survive the war unscathed. After the War ended, Zeppelin L 30 was seized by the Allies and delivered to Belgium for examination.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> The building of this Zeppelin L 30 model was a collaboration between Dr. H. Logan Holtgrewe, and Museum of Flight volunteer, Mr. Alex "Sandy" Morton. The  Zeppelin model was built entirely from scratch in 1/48 scale (one inch of the model equals 4 feet of the prototype) -the same scale as all the fixed wing aircraft models. This sameness of scale allows the viewer to appreciate the relative size of the various aircraft represented and to appreciate the huge size of the  Zeppelin L30. The illuminated gondola's overhead white lights allow the viewer to see the airship's interior details. Such lighting would have been extinguished during bombing raids over enemy territory being replaced by dim red night lights -this was to enhance nighttime stealth.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an airship of the Luftschiffe (German Naval Airship Division), German Naval Airship Airdrome, Nordholz, Germany, August, 1916.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Luftschiffbau Zeppelin
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Germany
<b>Power plant:</b> Six Maybach CX, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engines of 240 hp, each driving a 16 foot (4.9 m) propeller
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 62.2 mph (100 km/h) 
Ceiling: 13,125 feet (4,000m) fully bomb loaded, over 20,000 feet (6,100 m) after release of bombs
Endurance: 55 hours at top speed; 110 hours at cruising speed  
Weight (Empty): 79,600 pounds (36,106 kg)
Weight (Loaded): 141,200 pounds (64,047 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Length: 649 feet 6 inches (198 m)
Diameter: 78 feet 6 inches feet (23.94 m)
Gas Volume: 1,949,600 cubic feet (55,207 cubic meters)
<b>Armament:</b> Ten Parabellum 7.9 mm (.31 inch) drum fed machine guns in flexible mounts (two in both forward and aft gondolas, one outboard in both mid ships engine gondolas, three in gun platform atop forward fuselage, one in gun platform atop rear fuselage), 10,000 lbs (4,536 kg) of high explosive or incendiary bombs
<b>Crew:</b>23-30
<br />]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

