<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="205" cos="France"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[SPAD VII (S.7)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The first SPAD VII appeared over Europe in 1916 and shifted the balance of airpower in favor of the Allied Forces. The aircraft is part of a lineage of fighters designed by Louis Bechereau, the chief engineer of the French firm Société Anonyme Pour L'Aviation et ses Dérivés (SPAD). With its heavy 150 hp (112 kW) inline engine, the SPAD VII was less maneuverable than its opponents. Its robust design, however, allowed it to escape enemy fighters by entering a high speed dive which the Central Powers' lighter built rotary engine fighters could not match. Soon, a more powerful 180 hp (134 kW) engine was added to the SPAD VII's design, improving its performance. This improved version was designated the SPAD VII C1. 

More than 3,800 SPAD VIIs were built in France during the war. England and the Russia constructed hundreds more under license. Most French fighter Escadrilles flew S.VIIs at one time or another from 1916-1917, and many French aces achieved their air victories during World War I while flying a SPAD VII. The air services of England, the United States, Italy, Russia, Poland and Belgium also employed the S.7s.

By late 1917, Louis Bechereau had again redesigned his machine and produced the improved SPAD XIII. While similar externally to the S.7, the S.13 incorporated a more powerful engine, a slightly greater wingspan, a longer fuselage, and a second machine gun mounted on the nose. The new SPAD XIIIs began replacing the S.7s by the summer of 1917. After World War I, both the S.7s and S.13s remained in active service through the mid 1920s in the air forces of various countries.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> The prototype of this model was the SPAD VII C1 flown by the French ace Sgt. Georges Guynemer on the Western Front in late 1916.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified escadrille, Aviation Militaire (French Air Force), Western Front, September 1916. ]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Société Anonyme pour l'Aviation et ses Derives (SPAD)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Hispano-Suiza, 8 Ac, 8 cylinder liquid-cooled inline piston engine of 180 hp (134 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed 119 mph (191.5 km/h) at 6,560 ft (1,994 m) 
Ceiling: 18,000 feet ((5,486 m)
Endurance: 2 Hours, 15 minutes 
Empty Weight: 1,100 pounds (495 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,552 pounds (704 kg) 
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 25 feet 8 inches (7.82 m) 
Length: 19 feet 11 inches (6.07 m) 
Height: 7 feet 2 inches (2.18 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.7mm (0.303 inch) Vickers machine gun 
<b>Crew:</b>1
<br />]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

