<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="207" cos="France"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[ Blériot XI-2]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[Blériot XIs equipped eight squadrons of the Aviation Militaire (French Air Force) at the beginning of World War I in 1914. Constructed entirely of wood and fabric except for a small amount of metal sheeting about the engine in the forward fuselage, the Blériot XI was designed, built and first flown in 1909. The aircraft received world wide acclaim in July of that year when its designer, Louis Blériot, personally flew the machine across the English Channel from France to England -a substantial feat for the time. 

Several variants of the Blériot XI were built. They were all shoulder-winged monoplanes, with the exception of a parasol-winged variant designed for artillery spotting. The variants differed primarily in their power plants, their internal framing and their crew capacity. Among them were the XI-Ecole Militaire a trainer with a 35 hp engine, the XI-2 Genie (modeled here) a twin-seater with a 70 hp (52 kW) engine and the XI-3 a three-seater with a 100 hp engine. 

The aircraft began service with the French military in 1909. When the British Expeditionary Force was deployed to France in 1914, seven squadrons of Blériot XIs were sent in support. Blériot XIs, built under license by the Italian aircraft firm Societa Italiana Transaerea (S.I.T.), equipped six squadrons of the Italian Air Force when Italy entered World War I. Blériot XIs served primarily as reconnaissance aircraft. However, the first aerial night bombardment of the war was conducted in late 1914 by unit BL 18 who flew Blériot XIs to attack German factories at Metz.

By the summer of 1915, the Blériot XI was rendered obsolete by the appearance of more modern spotter aircraft with better handling characteristics and downward visibility. Blériot escadrilles were converted to Moraine-Saulnier Type Ls or Caudron G.3s while the aging Blériots were reassigned as trainers.

An authentic surviving World War I Blériot XI was filmed in the 2006 World War I Hollywood movie <i>Fly Boys</i>, a film centered around the exploits of American aviators flying for the French in the Lafayette Escadrille. Although not airworthy, the Blériot XI was frequently seen in the background during scenes shot in a replicated World War I French aerodrome. In addition to rental fees, a condition for its use was that the producers of the film to take out a huge insurance policy on the rare old aircraft. 

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> The vertical stabilizer in this model features a static upright with a movable rudder attached. Production Blériot XIs typically had a single-piece stabilizer that rotated on a pivot point.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified unit of the Aviation Militaire (French Air Force), Western Front, August, 1914.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Blériot-Aéronautique 
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Gnôme, 7 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 70 hp (52 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 68 mph (109 km/h) at sea level 
Ceiling: 3,280 feet (1,000 m)
Endurance: 3 hours, 30 minutes 
Empty Weight: 770 pounds (349 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,838 pounds (835 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 33 feet 11 inches (10.34 m) 
Length: 27 feet 10 inches (8.48 m)
Height: 8 feet 5 inches (2.57 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>2
<br />]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

