<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="208" cos="France"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Deperdussin Type TT (1914 Monoplane) Epervier (Sparrowhawk)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[Deperdussin Type TT aircraft were manufactured by the French aviation firm Société Pour L'Aviation et ses Dérivés (S.P.A.D.). First flying in 1912, the machine was a shoulder-wing monoplane, built with wood framing covered by doped fabric. Metal sheeting surrounded the engine and forward fuselage. The Deperdussin Type TT employed wing warping for lateral control, which required extensive wire bracing and control cables on the upper and lower wing surfaces.

When World War I broke out in August of 1914, the Aviation Militaire (French Air Force) had 138 airworthy aircraft in its inventory. Among this mixed bag of "flying machines" were two escadrilles equipped with Deperdussin Type TT aircraft such as the one modeled here. Most of France's 138 aircraft had originally been intended for sale on the civilian market, but were acquired and modified by the Aviation Militaire for use as reconnaissance platforms in support of French Army ground forces. French military leaders, like the leaders of all the combatant nations of the War, were initially skeptical about the usefulness of aircraft as weapons. Their potential as reconnaissance platforms was, however, universally recognized and early World War I aircraft were used solely in this capacity. 

Deperdussin Type TT aircraft proved frail and unsuited to the rigors and stresses intrinsic to wartime conditions. The slow, poorly maneuverable and unarmed machines often did not survive operational sorties once German and Austro-Hungarian fighter aircraft arrived over the Western Front in mid 1915. In an effort to give the Deperdussin Type TT some armament, a machine gun was mounted on a stand atop the forward fuselage with the gun firing over the propeller arc. This experimental arrangement proved unstable and the gun was impossible to reload. The concept was abandoned. Unacceptable losses coupled with the availability of more modern and armed reconnaissance machines allowed the Aviation Militaire to withdraw all of its Deperdussin Type TT aircraft by the end of 1915. The machine is, however, historically significant as one of the first aircraft to be deployed in military service.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified reconnaissance escadrille, Aviation Militaire (French Air Force), Western Front, August, 1914. ]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Société Anonyme pour l'Aviation et ses Derives (SPAD)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Gnôme Monosoupape, 9 cylinder air cooled rotary piston engine of 80 hp (60 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 71 mph (114 km/h) 
Ceiling: not documented
Endurance: 2 hours 20 minutes
Empty Weight: 1,600 pounds (753 kg)
Loaded Weight: not documented
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 36 feet (10.97 m)
Length: 26 feet (7.92 m) 
Height: 8 feet 10 inches (2.69 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

