<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="211" cos="United States"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[LePère 11 (C-11, C II)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[When the United States entered World War I in 1917, it did not possess any American-built military aircraft aside from the line of maritime reconnaissance flying boats built by Glenn Curtiss. The American military instead purchased all its fighters and bombers from England and France. The LePère 11 was commissioned by the United States Army Air Service in an effort to meet the need for an American-made fighting aircraft. 

The LePère 11 -also known as the LUSAC 11-was actually designed by a French aeronautical engineer named Capt. Georges LePère who was working for the U.S. Army. According to the Smithsonian Directory of Airplanes, the name "LUSAC" stands for "LePere United States Aircraft Corp". LePère designed the machine around the American Liberty engine. A two-seat biplane, the LUSAC 11 was intended to serve as a fighter, light bomber and reconnaissance platform for the U.S. Army Air Service.

Construction of the aircraft was undertaken by the Packard Motor Car Company of Detroit, Michigan. After favorable test flights, the U.S. Bureau of Aircraft Production ordered as many as 3,525 of the machines. However, as of the Armistice only 28 LUSACs had been delivered, two of which had made it to France for operational trials. With the cessation of hostilities, the Army immediately canceled the remainder of the order.

The completed aircraft continued to fly in the Army Air Service and a specially modified LUSAC 11 set a number of altitude records at Wright Field, Ohio in the early 1920s.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft believed to have been stationed at Wright Field, Dayton, Ohio, November, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> LePère US Aircraft Corp (LUSAC)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> United States
<b>Power plant:</b> One Liberty 12 A, 12 cylinder inline V liquid-cooled piston engine of 425 hp. (317 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 133 mph (214 km/h) 
Ceiling: 20,800 feet (6,340 m)
Range: 320 miles (515 km)
Empty Weight: 2,561 pounds (1,162 kg)
Loaded Weight: 3,746 pounds (1,699 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 41 feet 7 inches (12.67 m) 
Length: 25 feet 3 inches (7.69 m) 
Height: 10 feet 7 inches (3.22 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 0.30 inch (7.62 mm) Browning machine guns in forward fuselage, a single or twin 0.30 inch (7.62 mm) Lewis machine gun in flexible mount in rear cockpit 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

