<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="215" cos="France"> 
<type><![CDATA[Escort Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Breguet BR.5]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[With a wingspan of nearly 60 feet (18.3m), the Breguet BR.5 was exceptionally large for a single engine machine of the era. Louis Breguet and his company SA des Ateliers d'Aviation Louis Berguet began design of an aircraft in late 1914 with the specific purpose of providing France with a bomber which could strike Essen and other German cities where war materials were being manufactured.

As bomber casualties began to rise with the appearance of armed German fighters over the front, Breguet decided to mount cannons on some of his bombers for use as escort fighters. The escort version was designated the BR.5 and could equip either a bomb load or a 37 mm (1.46 inch) Hotchkiss cannon in the forward cockpit. The BR.5s, however, were not successful in stemming the loss of French Bombers.

The BR.5 had a gondola-like fuselage with a bombardier/gunner in the forward cockpit with the pilot's cockpit behind. Its engine, completely encased in a metal housing, drove a pusher propeller located at the gondola's rear. The rest of the fuselage was of open-strut construction with a maze of bracing wires. Varnished plywood veneer covered the gondola while fabric covered its wings and tail surfaces. The machine included a number of unique features for an aircraft of the time. It had a narrow box-like bomb bay mounted under each lower wing root just outboard of the fuselage. Each bay carried up to 20 fifteen pound bombs. The aircraft also had two cylindrical gravity-feeding fuel tanks suspended beneath its upper wing. Its tricycle landing gear, gave the machine a level horizontal stance when resting on the ground and during takeoff and landing. 

After trials in October of 1915 the aircraft was placed into production with the first machines reaching units of the Aviation Militaire in early 1916. From the beginning the aircraft exhibited two serious design problems: its engine was underpowered for the size and weight of the machine, hindering maneuverability, and the pilot had terrible visibility. This led to multiple accidents during takeoff and landing. Worse, it impeded the pilot's ability to see attacking enemy fighters thus denying him the opportunity to take what little evasive action his sluggish machine might allow. 

After mounting combat losses and an exceptionally disastrous raid on Oberndorf, Germany in October of 1916, all BR.5 aircraft were withdrawn from daytime operations and shifted to nighttime sorties where enemy interception was less of a problem. But the lack of pilot visibility led to numerous crashes during night time landings. Casualities became unacceptable. In early 1917 the Avaition Militaire gave up on the BR.5 and removed all remaining aircraft from service.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents and aircraft of the Aviation Militaire (French Air Force), Western Front, October, 1916.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Société Anonyme des Ateliers d'Aviation, Louis Bréguet
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Renualt 12Fb 12 cylinder inline V liquid-cooled piston engine of 220 hp (164 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 88 mph (142 km/h) 
Ceiling: 14,110 feet (4,300 m)
Endurance: 5 hours 
Empty Weight 3,067 (1,391 kg)
Loaded Weight 4,235 lbs (1,921 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 57 feet 9 inches ( 17.60 m) 
Length: 32 feet 6 inches (9.91 m)
Height: 12 feet 9 inches (3.89 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One 8mm (0.31 inch) Hotchkiss machine gun on a flexible mount in forward cockpit, 661 lbs (300 kg) of bombs 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

