<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="216" cos="France"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Breguet Bre.14 B2]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[Some World War I historians consider the Breguet Bre.14 to be the most successful French bomber of the war. Designed by the Société des Avions Louis Breguet, the frame of the Bre.14 was constructed from duralumin (aluminum) tubing. The use of aluminum gave the aircraft great strength and was advanced for a time when aircraft of wood and cloth construction were more common. 

Prototypes for two variants, the Bre.14 A2 armed reconnaissance version and the Bre.14 B2 light bomber (modeled here), flew for the first time in November, 1916 and entered service with the Aviation Militaire on the Western Front early in the summer of 1917. The machines proved to be fast and maneuverable with a good rate of climb. Breguet produced 5,500 of both variants during the war and an additional 2,500 before 1926. The United States purchased 376 Bre.14 B2 aircraft for service in the last year of the war on the Western Front. Although they could carry only a small bomb load, this aircraft was among the more successful light bombers during World War I.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents and aircraft of an unidentified escadrille, Aviation Militaire (French Air Force), Western Front, October, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Société Anonyme des Ateliers d'Aviation, Louis Bréguet
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Renault 12 Fox, 12 cylinder liquid-cooled inline V piston engine of 300 hp (224 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 110 mph (177 km/h)
Ceiling: 19,030 feet (5,800 m)
Endurance: 2 hours, 45 minutes
Empty Weight: 2,678 pounds (1,215 kg)
Loaded Weight: 4,220 pounds (1,915 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 47 feet 1 inches (14.35 m)
Length: 9 feet 0 inches (2.74 m)
Height: 10 feet 10 inches (3.30 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 0.303 inch (7.7mm) Vickers machine guns mounted on forward fuselage, one 0.303 inch (7.7mm) Lewis machine gun of a flexible mount in rear cockpit, 661 pounds (299 kg) of bombs
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

