<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="218" cos="France"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Farman (Maurice) M.F.7]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[When World War I broke out in August of 1914, the French Aviation Militaire had 138 airworthy flying machines in its inventory. Among these were a number of Maurice Farman M.F.7 aircraft. These aircraft were designed in early 1913 by the young French aeronautical engineer, Maurice Farman. Although they were originally intended for sale on the civilian market, the Aviation Militaire (French Air Force) bought a number of the machines to serve as reconnaissance aircraft.

The M.F.7's construction was similar to that of many aircraft designed in the years immediately prior to the war. The plane was designed as a biplane with a forward canard wing, which connected to and acted in concert with its tail control surfaces. A central gondola-like fuselage seated the crew and housed a copper petrol tank and the aircraft's pusher engine. Its framing was made entirely of wood and it was covered with doped fabric except for the top of its gondola which was covered with a varnished wood veneer. The machine was a maze of wooden spars and struts, steel bracing wires and control cables. This gave the M.F.7 a fragile appearance, although it was a rather robust machine. 

Six escadrilles fielded the M.F.7 at the start of the War. While the aircraft began as reconnaissance machines, some escadrilles also used them as bombers and even fighters. The M.F.7 remained in front-line service until early 1915 when is began to be replaced by the improved M.F.11. Many of the aircraft, which were known for their easy handling, were redeployed as trainers and served in this capacity until 1917. The Maurice Farman M.F.7 remains noteworthy in the annals of military aviation history because it was one of the first aircraft to be deployed in warfare.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the Aviation Militare (French Air Force), Western France, August, 1914.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Société Henri et Maurice Farman
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Renault, 8 cylinder air-cooled inline V piston engine of 70 hp (52 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 59 mph (95 km/h)
Ceiling: 13,123 feet (4,000 m)
Endurance: 3 hours, 30 minutes 
Empty Weight: 1,280 pounds (581 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,890 pounds (857 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 51 feet 0 inches (15.54 m) 
Length: 37 feet 3 inches (11.51 m)
Height: 11 feet 0 inches (3.35 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

