<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="221" cos="France"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Salmson 2 A2]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Salmson 2 A2 was the best reconnaissance aircraft placed in service by the French during World War I. Its advanced design finally provided the French with the reconnaissance aircraft for which they had been searching during the first three years of the War. Upon its entry into service, the new Salmson machine quickly replaced the older British-designed Sopwith 11/2 Strutters and the French built Farman, Breguet and Dorand machines, which had previously constituted the majority of the reconnaissance aircraft deployed  by the French. 

Designed in 1917 by the French aviation Société de Moteurs Salmson, the aircraft entered service with the Aviation Militaire at the beginning of 1918. By the War's end, eleven months later, over 3,200 had been manufactured by Salmson and under license by several other French companies. The aircraft equipped no fewer than 28 French reconnaissance escadrille and some 705 of the aircraft were in service with units of the United States Army Air Force. 

The aircraft was essentially designed around the Salmson 9 cylinder 230 hp liquid-cooled radial piston engine. The machine's circular radiator was positioned immediately behind the propeller in front of the engine, giving the power-plant complex a very compact and aerodynamically efficient configuration. Not only was the Salmson 2 A2 a fine reconnaissance platform, but its aerodynamic properties and armament made it relatively competitive as a fighter or light bomber. 

Overall, the Salmson 2 A2 was a highly successful and respected aircraft. Numbers remained in service with the Aviation Militaire and with the air services of other nations into the mid 1930s. ]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified reconnaissance escadrille, Aviation Militaire (French Air Force), Western Front, August, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Société de Moteurs Salmson
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Salmson 9Za, 9 cylinder liquid-cooled radial piston engine of 230 hp (172 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed:  117 mph  (188 km/h)
Ceiling:  20,500 feet    (6,250 m)
Range:  310 miles   (500 km)
Empty Weight: 1,720 pounds    (780 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,844 pounds  (1.230 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 38 feet 7 inches    (11.75 m)
Length:  27 feet 10 inches   (8.50 m)
Height:  9 feet 6 inches  (2.90 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing synchronized 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Vickers machine gun mounted atop forward fuselage, twin 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine guns on flexible mount in rear cockpit, bomb load of up to 330 lbs (150 kg) (optional)
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

