<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="222" cos="France"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Voisin 3]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Voisin 3 was one of the earliest flying machines to be deployed in military service and holds a number of historical "firsts" among early warplanes. Designed by the pioneering French aeronautical engineer, Gabriel Voisin, and built by his company, Société Anonyme des Aéroplanes G. Voisin, the light bomber first flew in 1913. The Voisin 3's construction consisted of a wood framework covered by fabric along its wings and tail surfaces and varnished wood veneer around its fuselage. The aircraft's design also included several unique features. Its power plant, which drove a pusher propeller, was a liquid cooled radial engine at a time when rotary air cooled engines were almost universal. The Voisin 3's undercarriage was laid out in an unusual four wheeled arrangement, which gave the machine a level horizontal stance when resting on the ground. This afforded the pilot greatly enhanced forward visibility compared to more traditional "tail dragging" aircraft. The Voisin 3 was also one of the first aircraft to be fitted with armament -in this case, a machine gun on a flexible mount in front of the forward cockpit. These features combined to make the Voisin 3 one of the heaviest aircraft in service during the early months of World War I. 

At the outbreak of war, numbers of Voisin 3 were among the 138 airworthy flying machines within the inventory of the Aviation Militaire and over 800 were eventually deployed by the French. The Voisin 3 became the standard bomber of the Aviation Militaire during the first two years of the War and was deployed in both daytime and nighttime bombing sorties. It was also the first French aircraft to achieve an air victory when, on October 5, 1914, a Voisin 3 shot down a German Aviatik biplane.  In addition to those bombers flown by France, over 100 Voisin 3s were flown by the British Royal Flying Corps and over 30 were flown by both the Belgian and Russian Air Forces. The Italian firm Societa Italinia Transaerea also built over 100 under license; these were supplied to the Italian Air Force. In total, well over 1,000 of the bombers saw service during the early stages of World War I, making the Voisin 3 one the most ubiquitous of all aircraft types flying during that period of the conflict.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the Aviation Militaire (French Air Force), Western Front, September, 1914.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Société Anonyme des Aéroplanes G. Voisin
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Canton-Unne, 9 cylinder liquid-cooled radial piston engine 120 hp  (90 kW)  
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed:   74 mph   (119 km/h)
Ceiling:   11,483 feet  (3,500 m)
Range: 310 miles   (500 km)
Empty Weight:    2,140 pounds  (971 kg)  
Loaded Weight:   3,025 pounds  (1,372 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span:  48 feet 4 inches 
Length:   31 feet 2 inches 
Height:   12 feet 6 inches
<b>Armament:</b> One 0.303 inch(7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun in flexible mount in forward cockpit, 110 lbs (50 kg) of bombs
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

