<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="223" cos="France"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Voisin 10 BN.2 (Type LAR)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Voisin 10 LAR was a successful night-bomber developed by French aeronautical engineer, Gabriel Voisin. Like the series of Voisin aircraft that preceded it, the Voisin 10 utilized a unique four-wheeled landing gear configuration. Two forward wheels were mounted on a delicate frame protruding in front of the fuselage nose, while the aircraft's two main wheels were positioned beneath the rear of the fuselage gondola. With this configuration, the aircraft remained horizontal while on the ground or during take-off and landing. This gave pilots greater visibility compared to a "tail dragging" aircraft.

The Voisin night bombers included a number of features designed to aid them in their mission. They were typically painted in an overall dark, flat gray or black for nighttime camouflage. To make night-flying easier, the Voisin 10 LARs also included nose-mounted landing lights, red and green wing tip recognition lights and an illuminated pilot instrument panel. Such lighting was unusual for World War I aircraft since most flying took place during daylight hours. Equally unusual for a World War I military aircraft were the two large torpedo-shaped petrol tanks suspended beneath the upper wing on either side of the fuselage. The machine's bomb load was carried beneath the lower wings.

Voisin-equipped escadrilles provided air support by attacking enemy troop formations and industrial targets during several battles, including Picardie, Flanders, Aisne, Santerre and Saint Mihiel. After the War, however, the Voisin 10 was soon replaced by more advanced aircraft.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of a night bomber escadrille of Groupes de Bombardment 9, Aviation Militaire (French Air Force), Western Front, September 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Société Anonyme des Aéroplanes G. Voisin
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Renault inline V 12 cylinder liquid-cooled piston engine of 300 hp (223 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 77 mph (124 km/h) at sea level 
Ceiling: 15,000 feet (4,572 m) 
Endurance: 4 hours 45 minutes 
Empty Weight: 2,893 pounds (1,312 kg)
Loaded Weight: 4,103 pounds (1,861 kg) 
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 61 feet 8 inches (18.80 m) 
Length: 36 feet 2 inches (11.02 m) 
Height: 11 feet 5 inches (3.48 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> One or two 7.7 mm (0.303 inch) Lewis machine gun in flexible mount(s) in rear cockpit, 295 kg (650 pounds) of bombs 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

