<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="225" cos="France"> 
<type><![CDATA[Escort Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Caudron Type R.11 (R XI)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Caudron Type R.11 was designed by Paul Deville of the French aviation firm Société Anonyme des Avions Caudron to meet the Aviation Militaire's requirements for a long-range escort fighter. Some evidence suggests that the R.11 may have originally been intended as a multi-purpose reconnaissance, light bombing and escort platform, but operational units used the aircraft exclusively as an escort fighter.

The R.11 was of standard wood and fabric construction except for its engine housings and the forward and dorsal aspects of its fuselage, which were covered with aluminum sheeting. A biplane, the R.11's two engines were completely enclosed in unusual triangular housings mounted between its wings. The R.11 had three crew cockpits. The pilot flew the plane from the center position below the wing, while the two gunners occupied the fore and aft positions. The R.11's twin gun emplacements allowed the aircraft to bring considerable firepower to bear on attacking fighters without having to take evasive maneuvers.

The aircraft first entered service in early 1918, though production delays slowed delivery of the aircraft. R.11s were often assigned to specific groupes de bombardement (bomber groups) to provide escort services. It is unclear how successful the aircraft were against German fighters, but the at the time of the Armistice six escadrilles were each equipped with 15 Caudron Type R.11 aircraft. This suggests that they proved to be a useful asset.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Escadrille C 46, Aviation Militaire (French Air Force), Western Front, October, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Société Anonyme des Avions Caudron
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> Two Hispano-Suiza 8 cylinder inline V liquid-cooled piston engines of 235 hp (175 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 118 mph (190 km/h) at sea level
Ceiling: 19,520 feet (5,950 m)
Endurance: 3 hours
Empty Weight: 3,135 pounds (1,422 kg)
Loaded Weight: 4,777 pounds (2,167 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 58 feet 9 inches (17.92 m)
Length: 36 feet 11 inches (11.25 m)
Height: 8 feet 10 inches (2.70 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Twin 0.303 inch (7.7mm) Lewis machine guns in flexible mount in nose of fuselage, similar weapons in flexible mount in dorsal mid fuselage, one 0.303 inch (7.7mm) Lewis machine gun firing downwards and rearward from beneath the forward gunner's position, 265 pounds (120 kg) of bombs
<b>Crew:</b>3]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

