<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="228" cos="Italy"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Hanriot HD 1]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Hanriot HD 1 machine was the first fighter designed and built by the French aviation firm Avions Hanriot & Co, where Pierre Dupont served as the chief engineer. The small machine first flew in the summer of 1916 and proved to be an agile, maneuverable and excellent fighter. By this time, however, the French Aviation Militaire (the French Air Force) had already committed itself to the mass production of SPAD and Nieuport fighters. The French showed little interest in the Hanriot HD 1 as a result. Italy, however, did adopt the machine. Under license, the Italian firm Società Nieuport-Macchi supplied 125 HD 1s to the Italian Air force in 1917 and an additional 706 in 1918. The Italian Air Force later adopted the Hanriot HD 1 as its standard fighter aircraft. At the time of its greatest use, the Hanriot HD 1 equipped no less than 16 of 18 Italian fighter units. 

Belgium also expressed interest in the Hanriot fighter and acquired 79 of the aircraft from its parent company in France. The machine achieved equal success when it entered service with Belgian forces in August 1917. Belgian airmen even preferred the Hanriot HD 1 to the newer Sopwith Camel. When offered Camels in early 1918, they rejected them in favor of the HD 1s they were already flying. The brilliant Belgian ace Willy Coppens de Houthulst also operated an HD 1. He achieved most of his 37 victories in this machine.

The Hanriot HD 1 gave an outstanding account of itself during combat. One battle in particular exemplifies the worth of the Hanriot HD 1. At the air battle of Istrana on December 26, 1917, Hanriots of the Italian 6th group shot down 11 German reconnaissance aircraft without loss. Numbers of the Hanriot HD 1s remained in active service long after World War I with the Italian, Belgian and Swiss Air Services-the Swiss having purchased 16 war surplus aircraft following the war. Some HD 1s remained with front line units of these three nations until 1930, a testimony to the excellent performance of this machine.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified unit of the Italian Air Force, Northern Italian Front, 1917.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Avions Hanriot & Co
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Le Rhone 9JB, 9 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 110 hp (82 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 114 mph (184 km/h) at sea level 
Ceiling: 20,670 feet (6,300 m)
Endurance: 2 hours 30 minutes 
Empty Weight: 908 pounds (412 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,334 pounds (605 kg) 
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 28 feet 6 inches (8.69 m) 
Length: 19 feet 2 inches (5.84 m) 
Height: 9 feet 7 inches (2.92 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> One or two fixed forward firing synchronized 7.7mm (0.303 inch) Vickers machine guns 
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

