<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="229" cos="Russia"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Nieuport 21]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Nieuport 21 was one aircraft in the continuing lineage of machines designed and built during World War I by the French aviation company Société Anonyme des Établissements Nieuport. The aircraft incorporated the airframe of its predecessor, the Nieuport 11 and the wings of the Nieuport 17, but was equipped with the smaller, less powerful Le Rhône 9C 80 hp (60 kW) engine. The smaller engine was included because the Nieuport 21 was never intended to be a combat fighter. Rather, it was designed and built as an advanced trainer for fighter pilots. 

Most Nieuport 21 aircraft were employed by the French Aviation Militaire in its flight schools, however a few were assigned to front line units alongside Nieuport 17s. Beginning in early 1917 the French supplied substantial numbers of Nieuport 21s to the Imperial Russian Air Force, which used the aircraft as front-line fighters. Sixty-eight additional machines were built under license by the Russian firm, Dux, in St. Petersburg. The Nieuport 21 was the most numerous Nieuport aircraft serving with the Imperial Russian Air Force. The machine was very popular with Russian pilots despite its relatively small power plant, due to its excellent maneuverability and reliability. In addition to their French and Russian service, one hundred ninety-seven Nieuport 21 aircraft were purchased by the United States Army Air Force for use as trainers, while five aircraft were briefly deployed by the British Royal Naval Air Service. 

The prototype of this model was an active fighter with the Imperial Russian Air Force on the Eastern Front during the weeks immediately prior to the Russian Communist Revolution, an event which forced Russia's withdrawal from World War I. Following the Russian revolution, the machines remained a part of the Red Air Force and were not retired until 1926.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> This model replicates the insignia and markings employed by the Imperial Russian Air Force during its involvement in World War I.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified unit of the Imperial Russian Air Force, Eastern Front, January 1917.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Société Anonyme des Établissements Nieuport
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Le Rhône, 9 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 110 hp (82 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 93 mph (150 km/h) 
Ceiling: 16,600 feet (5060 m) 
Endurance: 2 hours 
Empty Weight: 705 pounds (320 kg) 
Loaded Weight: 1,091 pounds (495 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 26 feet 9 inches (8.16 m)
Length: 19 feet 8 inches (6.00 m)
Height: 7 feet 10 inches (2.40 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing synchronized 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Vickers machine mounted in forward fuselage, one fixed, forward-firing 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun mounted on top of upper wing firing over propeller arc 
<b>Crew:</b>1
]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

