<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="231" cos="Russia"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Lebed VII]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[Though Russia had the largest air force among the belligerent nations at the start of World War I, it also had the least developed aircraft industry, having relied primarily on imported designs to build its forces. With the onset of war, the country continued to import foreign aircraft and focused on building proven British and French airframes under license.

The Russian aircraft manufacturer, Aktzionernoe Obshchestvo Vozdukhoplavania V.A. Lebedeva (V.A. Lebedev Joint-Stock Aeronautics Company), which was founded by Vladimir A. Lebedev was just one of the firms producing foreign designs for the Russian Air Force. The Lebed VII modeled here was one such design and was based on the Sopwith Tabloid aircraft.

Lebedev modified Sopwith's original design for the Lebed VII. Realizing that his aircraft would be flying from rough and poorly maintained landing fields, he increased the strength of its internal framing and fitted their undercarriage with anti-nose over struts. The aircraft was otherwise very similar to its British counterpart. Like the Tabloid, the Lebed VII featured biplane wings of equal span and chord; it employed wing-warping for lateral control, and included the same distinctive engine cowling. The exact number of Lebed VII aircraft produced is unclear, though the manufacturer ordered and received sixteen tachometers from the Sopwith Company, which suggests that the production run was quite limited. 

The aircraft flew unarmed and was deployed strictly for reconnaissance and training purposes. A few may have been fitted with a machine gun thus theoretically making them reconnaissance fighters, but no official documents or photographic evidence has been found to support this claim. Records indicate that several Lebed VII aircraft crashed during takeoff and landing resulting in non-combat losses. The aircraft served with the Imprial Russian Air Force from 1914 until early 1916 and were removed from service by the time of the 1917 Russian Revolution. ]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of 21st Corp Detachment, Imperial Russian Air Force, Grodnensky Fortress, Eastern Front, June, 1915.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Aktzionernoe Obshchestvo Vozdukhoplavania V.A. Lebedeva (Lebed)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Russia
<b>Power plant:</b> One French Gnôme Monosoupape, 7 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 80 hp (60 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 86 mph (138 km/h) 
Ceiling: 15,000 feet (4,575 m)
Endurance: 2 hours 30 minutes
Empty Weight: 1,620 pounds (735 kg)
Loaded Weight: not documented
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 25 feet 8 inches (7.82 m) 
Length: 22 feet 8 inches (6.91 m) 
Height: 9 feet 9 inches (2.97 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

