<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="232" cos="United States"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Floatplane]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Hanriot HD 2]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Hanriot HD 2 was the maritime version of the Hanriot HD 1 and was designed and built by the French aviation firm Société Anonyme des Appareils ď Aviation Hanriot

France's Aviation Militaire mostly rejected the HD 2s, though several of the planes, configured with wheels, flew from the battleship <i>Paris</i> at Toulon -launched from a 40ft (12m) platform above the turret of the battleship. Other countries, however, utilized the HDs during the war. The Italian Société Nieuport-Macchi company built many under license, and the HD 1 became the standard fighter of the Italian Air Force. The Belgian Air Force also flew the HD 1. Belgium's leading World War I ace Willy Coppens scored most of his 37 victories in this aircraft. The United States also purchased 10 of the HD 2s when it entered the war in 1917. They were flown from the United States Navy Facility at Dunkerque, France, in a reconnaissance-fighter role.

After the war, many of the HD 2s remained in service with the United States Navy Air Service. The Naval Aircraft Factory replaced the floats with wheels, and the planes became trainers at Langley Field. One of these wheeled versions participated in early United States Navy experiments involving aircraft flights from ships. It flew off a temporary platform built over the guns of the battleship <i>USS Mississippi</i>.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[Unidentified United States Navy Air Squadron, U.S. Navy Facility, Dunkerque, France, April, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Avions Hanriot & Co
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> 130 hp (100kW) Clerget 9B rotary engine
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 114 mph (183km/h) 
Ceiling: 15,750ft (4,800m)
Range: 186 miles (300 km)
Empty Weight: 1091 pounds (496 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1594 pounds (723 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 28 feet 6.5 inches (8.7 m)
Length: 22 feet 11.5 inches (7.0 m)
Height: 10 feet 2.0 inches (3.10 m)
<b>Armament:</b> two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.7 mm (0.303 inch) Vickers machine guns
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

