<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="233" cos="United States"> 
<type><![CDATA[Trainer]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Standard E-1]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[When the United States entered World War I in April of 1917, it lacked any domestically produced combat aircraft except for a line of flying boats built by Glenn Curtiss. The U.S. instead equipped its pilots with French and British models, while working to develop its domestic aviation industry. American military leaders put out a call for an American built fighter. Two firms responded with original designs: the Packard Motor Car Company of Detroit, Michigan with their LUSAC-11, and the Standard Aircraft Company of Elizabeth, New Jersey with the Standard M-Defense. 

The Standard's design began in May of 1917. Two prototypes of the new fighter, called the Standard M-Defense, were delivered to the Army Air Corps the following summer. During preproduction flight trials it became apparent that the new aircraft lacked the performance characteristics necessary for a fighter. It was underpowered, slow, lacked maneuverability and had a sluggish rate of climb. The little biplane would be unable to compete with the latest German fighters then in service on the Western Front. 

With minor changes the aircraft was instead adopted as an advanced trainer, the Standard E-1 which is modeled here. 168 production E.1s were manufactured and assigned to flight Schools within the continental United States. A total of 130 E-1 aircraft were eventually produced for the U.S. Army Air Corps.

After the War, Lawrence Sperry converted a number of E.1s to unmanned "aerial torpedoes" as part of a series of military tests now recognized as one of the earliest manifestations of guided-missle technology.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the United States Army Air Service Flight School, Wright Field, Dayton, Ohio, September, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Standard Aircraft Company
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> United States
<b>Power plant:</b> One Le Rhône, 9 cylinder rotary air-cooled piston engine of 80 hp (60 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 100 mph (161 km/h) 
Ceiling: 14,800 feet (4,511 m)
Endurance: 2 hours 
Empty Weight: 828 pounds (376 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,144 pounds (519 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 24 feet (7.32 m)
Length: 18 feet 10 inches (5.74 m)
Height: 7 feet 10 inches (2.39 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

