<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="234" cos="United States"> 
<type><![CDATA[Trainer]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Thomas-Morse S-4C]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Thomas-Morse S-4C was one of the few World War I aircraft independently designed and manufactured in the United States without the assistance or influence of French, British or Italian engineers. While otherwise purely American, it did have a French-designed power plant. A very sturdy aircraft built of wood framing with a fabric covering painted with aluminum colored dope, it had a circular metal cowling surrounding its engine. Built by the Thomas-Morse Aviation Company, the small, compact and aerodynamically sophisticated aircraft was intended to be an advanced trainer for the development of American fighter pilots. 

The S-4C was developed as an alternative to the American built Curtiss JN-4 "Jenny". While the Jenny was probably the finest elementary trainer of its era, its flight characteristics were "tame" compared to those of the French S.P.A.D.s, Nieuports and the British Sopwith fighters the American airmen flew in Europe. The United States Army Air Force needed a trainer with properties more closely resembling those of an actual combat fighter. The Thomas-Morse trainer was created to fill this need and began being deployed at flight schools in June of 1917. Since the young airmen who would be flying it had successfully completed their primary training and were certified pilots, the Thomas-Morse trainer had no instructor's cockpit. While not quite possessing the speed and maneuverability of a combat fighter, it approached that degree of performance thus giving the pilot the necessary transitional experience needed before flying "the real thing" over the Western Front. 

The machine proved so successful in its role as a transitional advanced trainer that production continued past the end of World War I and was not finally terminated until 1920. A total of 497 S-4Cs were built. and remained in active service at United States Army Air Force flight training schools until the late 1920s. Following their military careers a number of the former trainers were sold on the civilian market where their racy appearance and outstanding performance made them very popular with aerial sportsman. Many hobbyists continued to fly a number of them into the 1950s. While their airframes remained unchanged, those machines flying after the mid 1930s usually had their original rotary engines replaced with more modern radial power plants.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the United States Army Air Force Flight Schools, Wright Field, Dayton, Ohio, November, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Thomas-Morse Aircraft
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> United States
<b>Power plant:</b> One Le Rhône 9C, 9 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 80 hp (60 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 95 mph (153 km/h) at sea level 
Ceiling: 15,000 feet (4,572 m)
Endurance: 2 hours 30 minutes 
Empty Weight: 961 pounds (436 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,354 pounds (614 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 26 feet 6 inches (8.08 m) 
Length: 19 feet 10 inches (6.05 m) 
Height: 8 feet 1 inch (2.46 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Usually none, but a few were fitted with a single fixed forward firing synchronized 7.62 mm (0.30 inch) Marlin machine gun mounted atop the forward fuselage for use in the training of aerial marksmanship
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

