<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="235" cos="Russia"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Flying Boat]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[FBA Model C]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[Prior to World War I, Franco-British Aviation (F.B.A.) acquired the patent for the Donnet-Lévêque flying boats from which the company developed a series of maritime patrol aircraft. The first of these aircraft, the F.B.A. Model A, was heavily influenced by the earlier Donnet-Lévêque. Developed prior to World War I, the Model A did not see extensive military service. However, the F.B.A. Model B and Model C (modeled here) were produced in significant numbers for the French and British navies.

The F.B.A. Model B and C were larger, two-seat versions of their predecessor, The B and C differed only in their powerplants. The Model B employed a 100 hp Gnôme engine, while the Model C utilized a more powerful 130 hp Clerget engine. Both aircraft were two-seat biplane flying boats with their respective engines in a "pusher" configuration. The lower wing of the F.B.A. flying boats did not mount directly to the fuselage. Rather, it was elevated on four steel struts which dramatically raised the wings above the body of the craft.

First produced in France, manufacture of F.B.A. flying boats was also carried out under license by the SIAI company in Italy and the Lebedev factory in Russia. During the course of the war no less than 982 F.B.A. flying boats were built, the largest number of any World War I flying boat type. The machines were widely used and saw most of their service with the French and British navies. A few were also sent to Russia where they were primarily deployed over the Black Sea to monitor the assets of the Ottoman Empire. This model replicates one of these Russian F.B.A. flying boats. 

Little is known about the operational history of the Russian F.B.A. flying boats, but they apparently remained in active service with the Russian Navy until the Russian Revolution and the overthrow of the Czar; events which took Russia out of World War I. ]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an unidentified unit of the Imperial Russian Naval Air Force, Odessa, Black Sea, February, 1917.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Franco-British Aviation (F.B.A.)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Clerget, 9 cylinder rotary air-cooled piston engine of 130 hp (97 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 68 mph (109 km/h) 
Ceiling: 11,480 feet (3,500 m)
Range: 186 miles (300 km) 
Empty Weight: 1,411 pounds (640 kg) 
Loaded Weight: 2,072 pounds (940 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 44 feet 11 inches (13.67 m)
Length: 28 feet 10 inches (8.79 m)
Height: 11 feet 2 inches (3.40 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun on flexible mount in forward cockpit 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

