<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="236" cos="Russia"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Anatra Model DS <i>Anasal</i> (Anatra-Salmson)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[While the Imperial Russian Air Service began World War I with more aircraft than France or Germany, many of the machines were imported models already considered obsolete by the other nations. Furthermore, The Russian aviation industry was underdeveloped compared to those of the War's other major combatant nations. Recognizing the situation as a business opportunity, Russian banker, Artur Antonovich Anatra founded the Anatra Aircraft Company in Odessa. It was this firm that designed and produced the Anatra DS modeled here. 

The Anatra DS developed from the earlier Anatra D and appeared very similar to its predecessor. The primary difference between the DS and the earlier aircraft was the inclusion of a 150 hp liquid-cooled Salmson radial engine. The inclusion of this engine led to the plane's nickname, "<i>Anasal</i>" -a combination of "Anatra" and "Salmson". The radial engine was unique at a time when virtually all aircraft had either rotary air-cooled engines or inline liquid-cooled engines. Aside from this, the <i>Anasal</i> was of standard construction for the era -wood framing, plywood veneer over the fuselage, metal sheeting about its engine and fabric covering of its wings and tail surfaces. 

Approximately 70 production <i>Anasal</i>s were built and delivered to the Imperial Russian Air Force before the end of hostilities. Little is recorded about the operational history of these machines but it is known that at the time of the Russian Revolution and the overthrow of the Imperial government that Anatra DS aircraft were listed on the rosters of the Imperial Russian Air Force. 

While the chaotic events of the Russian Civil War, which began in 1917 are still being sorted out by historians, it is thought that some of these aircraft remained operational with both the "White" and "Red" air forces. The aircraft modeled here bears post-revolution Bolshevik markings.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the Russian Bolshevik "Red Air Force", Western Russia, Summer 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> A. A. Anatra Aircraft Company
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Russia
<b>Power plant:</b> One French-built Salmson, 9 cylinder radial liquid-cooled piston engine of 150 hp (112 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 89 mph (143 km/h)
Ceiling: 14,108 feet (4300 m)
Endurance: 3 hours 30 minutes 
Empty Weight: 1,781 pounds (808 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,557 pounds (1160 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 40 feet 7 inches (12.37 m)
Length: 26 feet 6 inches (8.08 m)
Height: 10 feet 5 inches (3.18 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing synchronized 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Vickers machine gun mounted on the starboard side of the forward fuselage, one 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun in flexible mount in rear cockpit 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

