<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="237" cos="Russia"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Lebed XII]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Lebed XII and its immediate predecessor, the Lebed XI, were designed by Vladimir A. Lebedev, founder of the Russian firm Aktzionernoe Obshchestvo Vozdukhoplavania V.A. Lebedeva (V.A. Lebedev Joint-Stock Aeronautics Company). Both aircraft were largely based on a captured German Albatros B.II. Russian officials felt that it was more efficient to replicate proven designs than to develop all new aircraft.

The Lebed XII was a single-engine, two-seat biplane constructed of a plywood-covered wooden frame. While this construction method resulted in a very strong structure, it added considerable weight to the airframe. The aircraft utilized a French Salmson liquid-cooled radial engine- a very unique power plant. The Salmson was the only radial liquid-cooled engine used during the War. Liquid cooling of a radial engine was soon abandoned in favor of air cooling since experience revealed that coolant added weight to the radiator and imposed a needless drag on performance. 

After successful test flights in January of 1916, the Central Military Technical Board placed an order for 225 machines, which began replacing the Voisin as the standard corps aircraft. Unfortunately, operational Lebed XIIs proved problematic. The exhaust pipes were situated in such a way that the exhaust threatened to asphyxiate the observer in the rear cockpit. Furthermore, the pilots reported that it was difficult to pull out of a dive, and the aircraft was also prone to catch fire while in flight. Nevertheless, the Lebed XII was considered superior to the Voisins it was designed to replace.

Records indicate that Lebed XIIs were still active with the Imperial Russian Air Force at the time of the Russian Revolution and the country's withdrawal from World War I. Following the Revolution, a few remained flying for the Bolshevik controlled "Red Air Force" and some even participated in the 1919 Russian Civil War between White and Red Russian factions. ]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft from an unidentified unit of the Imperial Russian Air Force, Eastern Front, November 1916.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Aktzionernoe Obshchestvo Vozdukhoplavania V.A. Lebedeva (Lebed)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Russia
<b>Power plant:</b> One French-built Salmson, 9 cylinder liquid-cooled radial piston engine of 150 hp (112 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 83 mph (134 km/h) 
Ceiling: 11,482 feet (3500 m)
Endurance: 3 hours 
Empty Weight: 1,900 pounds (862 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,674 pounds (1213 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 43 feet 1 inch (13.13 m)
Length: 26 feet 1 inch (7.95 m)
Height: 10 feet 7 inches (3.23 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun in flexible mount in rear cockpit, 220 pounds (100 kg) of bombs 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

