<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="238" cos="United States"> 
<type><![CDATA[Trainer]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Curtiss JN-4 <i>Jenny</i>]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Curtiss JN-4, more commonly known as the "<i>Jenny</i>" was the most widely used training aircraft in the United States during World War I. The aircraft was stable, reliable, rugged and easy to fly -perfect for training young pilots. Virtually every American airman and many Canadian pilots who flew during World War I first learned to fly in the <i>Jenny</i> and over 6,400 <i>Jennies</i> of several different variants were produced in the United States and Canada.

The <i>Jenny</i> combined the best features of two earlier Curtiss aircraft, the model J and the model N. The JN-4, was a biplane in a tractor configuration, like its predecessors. The <i>Jenny</i> was a two-seater, and could be configured with either wheels, or a float undercarriage. As such, the aircraft could provide for the needs of both the Army Air Corps and the Navy.

Though the <i>Jenny</i> was originally designed as a military trainer, the aircraft type was used successfully in a much broader capacitiy. In March of 1916, eight early <i>Jennies</i> of the First Aero Squadron under Capt. Benjamin Foulois participated in the Mexican punitive expedition in search of the rebel Pancho Villa. After World War I, many of the surplus machines were sold on the civilian market to serve again as trainers, barnstormers, air show participants, crop dusters and in the air-mail service; several even starred in movies

When the Air Commerce Act of 1926 established rules and regulations regarding construction and maintenance of aircraft, and the training of pilots, the <i>Jenny</i> could not fulfill the new stringent requirements. However, the <i>Jenny</i> surely remains one of the most interesting historical aircraft on record. Several still reside in places of honor in museums and private collections around the world.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the Signal Corps Aviation School, United States Army, Wright Field, Dayton, Ohio, March 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Curtiss Aeroplane and Motor Co.
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> United States
<b>Power plant:</b> One Curtiss OX-5, 8 cylinder liquid-cooled inline V piston engine of 90 hp (67 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 75 mph (121 km/h) 
Ceiling: 11,000 feet (3,353 m)
Endurance: 2 hours 15 minutes
Empty Weight: 1,580 pounds (717 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,130 pounds (966 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 43 feet 7 inches (13.28 m)
Length: 27 feet 4 inches (8.33 m)
Height: 9 feet 10 inches (3.00 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

