<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="239" cos="Italy"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Ansaldo S.V.A. 5 (SV.5)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[In the summer of 1916 Italian aircraft designers Umberto Savoia, Rodolfo Verduzio and Celestino Rosatelli set out to design a new high-performance fighter aircraft for the Italian Corpo Aeronautico Militare. The task of manufacturing the aircraft was assigned to the Societa Giovanni Ansaldo. When the single-seat biplane was finished, it received the designation Ansaldo S.V.A. 5 (Savoia-Verduzio-Ansaldo) in recognition of its manufacturer and chief designers.

The first S.V.A. 5 flew on March 19, 1917. Biplanes with wood framing, the S.V.A. had varnished plywood covering the fuselage, doped fabric covering the wings and tail surfaces and a metal alloy surrounding the engine. The aircraft's intra-wing bracing arrangement was unusual and employed a Warren truss triangular configuration of thin steel struts, devoid of bracing wires. 

The new S.V.A. aircraft exhibited exceptional speed but lacked the maneuverability desirable in combat fighters. However, it was recognized that they would make exceptional high speed reconnaissance bombers, a role to which they were immediately assigned and in which they excelled. Despite carrying a bomb load, two machine guns and two reconnaissance cameras, the S.V.A. 5 was one of the fastest aircraft of War and was probably one of the conflict's finest reconnaissance platforms. Its speed alone made it largely immune to interception and once released from its bomb load, it became competitive with Austro-Hungarian fighters. 

Of the 1,248 aircraft of the S.V.A. series manufactured during the War, the Ansaldo S.V.A. 5, modeled here, was built in the largest numbers. A two-seat variant of the S.V.A. 5 was soon developed and designated the S.V.A. 9 The Ansaldo S.V.A.'s greatest moment came on August 8, 1918 when 10 S.V.A. 5's lead by a single S.V.A. 9 over-flew Vienna, Austria for over a half hour dropping bombs and leaflets all while taking photographs of the city. This constituted a nonstop round-trip flight of over 6 hours, covering 620 miles (998 km) from their base in Pelagio, Italy -an exceptional feat for the time. Ansaldo S.V.A. 5 aircraft rendered impressive service until the end of the War and numbers of them continued flying with the Italian Corpo Aeronautico Militare until the mid-1930s.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Squadrigilia 87a, Corpo Aeronautico Militare (Italian Air Force), Pelagio, Italy, August, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Aeronáutica Ansaldo SA
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Italy
<b>Power plant:</b> One Isotta-Fraschini, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engine of 250 hp (188 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 143 mph (230 km/h) at sea level 
Ceiling: 19,685 feet (5,906 m)
Endurance: 6+ hours 
Empty Weight: 1,500 pounds (681 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,315 pounds (1,051 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 29 feet 10 inches (9.09 m) 
Length: 26 feet 6 inches (8.08 m) 
Height: 10 feet 6 inches (3.70 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.7 mm (0.303 inch) Vickers machine guns enclosed in the upper forward fuselage between the engine and cockpit and firing through gun tubes, 150 kg (330 pounds) of bombs 
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

