<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="243" cos="United States"> 
<type><![CDATA[Trainer]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Curtiss N-9]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The N-9 seaplane, which began development in late 1916, was essentially a float-equipped variant of the JN-4 Jenny training aircraft. The N-9 was a quite large machine for a training aircraft of the World War I era. Built of wood framing, it had a plywood veneer over its fuselage with doped fabric covering of its wings and tail surfaces. A thin metal alloy surrounded the engine. Its central pontoon and bilateral wing floats were also of metal construction. Aside from the floatplane undercarriage, The N-9 differed from its landplane equivalent primarily in its wingspan and the shape of its airfoil -the wing having been extended to generate the extra lift necessary to compensate for the weight of the float.

Four hundred-fifty N-9s were produced during World War I. Entering service at United States Navy flight schools in April, 1917 they served as the standard seaplane trainer. In its initial configuration, the N-9 proved adequate for basic training. However, in order to meet the power needs for advanced gunnery and bomber training, later models were outfitted with a more powerful Hispano-Suiza engine. After World War I, the N-9 remained the Navy's principle seaplane and flying boat training aircraft for the next decade. 560 aircraft were produced before the type was retired.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the United States Navy Flight School, United States Naval Air Station, North Island, San Diego, California, August 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Curtiss Aeroplane and Motor Co
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> United States
<b>Power plant:</b> One Curtiss OX-6, 8 cylinder V inline liquid-cooled piston engine of 100 hp (75 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 80 mph (129 km/h) 
Ceiling: 9,850 feet (3002 m)
Endurance: 2 hours 
Empty Weight: 2,145 pounds (3002 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,765 pounds (1254 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 53 feet 3 inches (16.23 m)
Length: 30 feet 10 inches (9.40 m)
Height: 10 feet 8 inches (3.25 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

