<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="244" cos="France"> 
<type><![CDATA[Flying Boat]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Borel Aeroyacht Type Denhaut I]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Borel Aeroyacht was one of several flying boats designed by French aviation pioneer, Francis Denhaut. He developed the Aeroyacht in 1912 for the French firm, Etablissements Borel, which entered the aircraft in the 1913 Paris-Deauville competition. The competition consisted of a race along the river, Seine from Paris to the city of Deauville on the English Channel followed by sea trials. It was set up to select two seaplane designs to enter production for the French Navy.

The Aeroyacht, one of two Borel aircraft entered in the competition, featured a wood-framed hull covered with a varnished wood veneer. The aircraft's two crewmen sat side-by-side in its open cockpit. The sesquiplane wings and tail surfaces were framed in wood and had a doped fabric covering. Two outrigger stabilizing pontoons were mounted beneath each lower wing tip. A single 100 h.p. engine was mounted high on a steel framework behind the upper wing in a position intended to help avoid sea spray during takeoff and landing. Publications from the time indicate that the Aeroyacht was considered quite advanced and expectations were high.

Unfortunately, the Aeroyacht's performance at the Paris-Deauville trials did not live up to expectations. The aircraft failed to finish the race and was subsequently disqualified from the sea-trials portion of the event. In the aftermath of the Aeroyacht's poor performance, Denhaut was fired from Borel. Two years later, however, he formed his own company, Donnet-Denhaut in partnership with Jerome Donnet. This endeavour proved more successful and the new firm went on to produce a series of seaplanes for the French Navy.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> This model depicts an Aeroyacht as it might have looked in service with the French Navy. The model's configuration most closely resembles plan drawings of the Borel Aeroyacht Type Denhaut I, which appeared in 1913 issues of the aviation journals, <i>Flugsport</i> and <i>Aero and Hydro</i>. Photos of the Aeroyacht taken at the Paris-Deauville competition suggest the design had been further modified by the time of the race. These later versions are often referred to as Type II and III, respectively.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model depicts an aircraft painted in the markings of the Aviation Maritime (French Naval Air Service), 1915.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Société Anonyme des Établissements Borel
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Gnôme Monosoupape, 9 cylinder air cooled rotary piston engine of 100 hp (75 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 65 mph (105 km/h) 
Ceiling: not documented
Range: Endurance 2 hours, 45 minutes
Empty Weight: 980 pounds (431 kg)
Loaded Weight: not documented
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 49 feet 2 inches (14.99 m) 
Length: 29 feet 6 inches (8.99 m) 
Height: 10 feet 1 inch (3.07 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>2
<br />]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

