<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="245" cos="Italy"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Flying Boat]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Macchi L.1]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[On May 27th, 1915, shortly after Italy entered World War I, the Italian Navy captured a stranded Austro-Hungarian Lohner flying boat. The Italian Naval Air Service commissioned the firm, Societa Anonima Nieuport-Macchi to create a similar aircraft based on the captured Lohner. Italy's first flying boat, the Macchi L.1 was the result. 

The L.1 was almost and exact copy of its Lohner predecessor. The term "flying boat" was very appropriate for the L.1 since its wood veneer fuselage closely resembled the hull of a boat. The aircraft's wings and tail planes utilized wood framing but were covered with doped fabric and were decorated with the green, white and red markings of Italy. The machine's tail surfaces were raised high on a delicate metal frame to avoid sea spray during take-off and landing. The L.1's single engine, driving a "pusher" propeller, was in an elevated position between the wings. The Macchi L.1 was armed with a single machine gun mounted on the starboard side of the cockpit roof. 

Macchi produced a total of 139 L.1s, which were employed in reconnaissance, bombing and maritime patrol missions over the Mediterranean and Adriatic seas. An improved version dubbed the L.2 was produced in small numbers beginning in 1916, The L.1 and L.2 were eventually phased out with the arrival of the improved Macchi M.3.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified unit of the Italian Naval Air Service, Mediterranean Sea, December 1915.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Societa Anonima Nieuport-Macchi
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Italy
<b>Power plant:</b> One Isotta-Frachini V4.A, 6 cylinder liquid-cooled inline piston engine of 150 hp (112 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 68 mph (109 km/h) 
Ceiling: 14,760 feet (4500 m)
Endurance: 4 Hours 
Empty Weight: 2756 pounds (1250 kg)
Loaded Weight: 3,747 pounds (1700 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 53 feet 10 inches (16.41 m)
Length: 33 feet 8 inches (10.26 m)
Height: 12 feet 8 inches (3.86 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One flexible forward firing 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun on cockpit roof 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

