<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="246" cos="Italy"> 
<type><![CDATA[Flying Boat Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Macchi M.5 Mod]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[In 1917, the Societa Anonima Nieuport-Macchi began developing a single-seat flying boat fighter to compete with Austrian maritime fighters. The new aircraft, designated the M.5, featured a boat-shaped fuselage made of wood framing with a smoothly sanded plywood veneer. The aircraft used the same sesquiplane wing and v-strut configuration as its land-based Nieuport contemporaries. To avoid sea spray, the M.5's engine and radiator were mounted between its wings on a tubular steel frame above the pilot's cockpit. Later refinements to the M.5 design resulted in the M.5 Mod (modeled here). The new variant featured a more powerful engine and redesigned wingtip floats.

The M.5 proved to be fast, maneuverable and very competitive with the best Austro-Hungarian naval fighters then in service. A total of 350 were produced and issued to five different squadrons of the Italian Naval Air Service. Italian ace, Orazio Pierozzi achieved five of his six confirmed kills while flying an M.5. The aircraft had brilliant careers and were so highly regarded that they remained in service for years after the War. When the World War I Italian Navy "Regia Marine" was reorganized and merged into the new Italian Air Force the "Regia Aeronautica" in 1923, sixty-six Macchi M.5 Mod flying boat fighter aircraft were still in active service.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the 260a Squadriglia, Regia Marina (Italian Naval Air Service), Venice Seaplane Base, July 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Nieuport-Macchi
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Italy
<b>Power plant:</b> One Isotta-Fraschini V.6b, 6 cylinder liquid-cooled piston engine of 250 hp (186 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 127 mph (205 km/h) 
Ceiling: 16,405 feet (5000 m)
Endurance: 3 hours 40 minutes 
Empty Weight: 1,664 pounds (755 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2381 pounds (1080 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 32 feet 7 inches (9.93 m)
Length: 26 feet 7 inches (8.10 m)
Height: 9 feet 8 inches (2.95 m)
<b>Armament:</b> 2 fixed, forward-firing 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Vickers machine guns mounted and completely enclosed within the forward fuselage thus protecting them from sea spray- they fired through forward protruding gun tubes 
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

