<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="247" cos="Italy"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Flying Boat]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Macchi M.9]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Macchi M.9 (modeled here) was the last flying boat produced by Nieuport-Macchi during World War I. The M.9 was intended to provide the Italian Naval Air Service with a new long-ranged armed reconnaissance bomber which could patrol the Adriatic and Mediterranean Seas keeping track of, and attacking, the naval assets of the Austro-Hungarian and Ottoman Empires.

Design of the new flying boat began in early 1918 and borrowed much from previous Macchi aircraft, particularly its immediate predecessor, the M.8. The hull-shaped fuselage was formed from wood framing covered by a plywood veneer. The area above the waterline was finished with a high gloss varnish, the area below the waterline with anti-fouling paint. The aircraft's wings and tail surfaces had wood framing with doped fabric covering and outrigger stabilizing floats positioned beneath the wingtips. The machine's single engine was enclosed in a metal housing mounted above the fuselage on a steel framework. Its enclosure and elevated position were intended to protect it from sea spray during takeoff and landing. 

Unfortunately for the Allies, Macchi M.9 aircraft did not begin equipping Italian naval squadrons until the autumn of 1918, only a few weeks before the end of hostilities. As a result, they saw very limited action and their contribution to the war effort was minimal. Military production of the M.9 was terminated with the end of the War, by which time only 30 had been completed and delivered. However, Macchi converted the aircraft type for civil transport with the M.9 bis variant. The civilian version had a range of 340 miles and included an enclosed cabin capable of seating a pilot and four passengers.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of 262a Squadriglia, Italian Naval Air Service Sea Plane Base, Venice, Italy, October, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Nieuport-Macchi
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Italy
<b>Power plant:</b> One Fiat A.12 bis, six cylinder liquid cooled inline piston engine of 280 hp (208 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Speed: 116 mph (187 km/h) 
Ceiling: 18,050 feet (5,500 m)
Endurance: 4 Hours 
Empty Weight: 2,756 pounds (1,250 kg)
Loaded Weight: 3,968 pounds (1,800 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 50 feet 6 inches (15.39 m) 
Length: 31 feet 10 inches (9.50 m)
Height: 10 feet 4 inches (3.15 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun on flexible mount in a forward fuselage gun position, up to 440 pounds (200 kg) bombs or anti-submarine mines
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

