<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="249" cos="Italy"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Caproni Ca.42 (Military Ca.4)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Italian firm Societ Ingegneri Caproni e Faccanoni built a line of progressively larger bombers during World War I, culminating with the Ca.42. The Ca.42 represents one of the largest aircraft of the Great War, second in wingspan to only three other machines: two massive Soviet Sikorsky bombers and the even larger Zeppelin Staaken R.VI German heavy bomber. 

The Ca.42 featured a separate bomb bay compartment attached to the lower wing of the craft. This compartment was mounted directly beneath the gondola-like central fuselage containing the pilot, a nose gunner and a third "pusher" engine. To support its long, thin wings, the machine required a maze of struts and bracing wires. Despite these structures, the aircraft's wings drooped when taking-off, landing and sitting on the ground. Skids placed beneath the tips of the lower wings prevented damage should the wing tips hit the ground. During flight, the lift of the wings reversed this drooping and the wings took on a slight upward or "dihedral" angle. 

The Ca.42 primarily carried out bombing raids on the larger cities of the Austro-Hungarian Empire during World War I. These missions often required clear weather, as this enabled the crew to visually navigate through the peaks of the Alps; these peaks rose higher than the Ca.42's operational ceiling of just over 9,800 feet (3,000 m). Ca.42s also carried out a few night bombing missions, but did not fly over the Alps for these missions. Ca.42s also saw action in the Battle of Vittorio Veneto and six of the aircraft were loaned to the British Royal Naval Air Service for use as maritime reconnaissance aircraft. 

Overall, the Ca.42s performed well, but they were complex, time-consuming and expensive to construct. Only 23 were produced before the war's end, and none were manufactured afterward. Italian aeronautical designers, however, continued to favor its three-engine design until after World War II.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified unit of the Italian Air Force, September 1918.
]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Societ Ingegneri Caproni e Faccanoni
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Italy
<b>Power plant:</b> Three Isotta-Fraschini 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engines of 270 hp (201kW) each
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 78 mph (140 km/h) 
Ceiling: 9,842 feet (3,000 m) 
Endurance: 7 hours 
Empty Weight: 8,800 pounds (3,992 kg) 
Loaded Weight: 16,500 pounds (7,484 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 98 feet 1 inch (29.90 m) 
Length: 42 feet 11 inches (13.08 m) 
Height 20 feet 8 inches (6.30 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> : Four 7.7 mm (0.303 inch) Lewis machine guns- one twin mount in nose of fuselage, one single mount in center of each tail boom, up to 1,451 kg (3,200 pounds) of bombs 
<b>Crew:</b>4]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

