<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="300" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Nieuport X Sesquiplane]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Nieuport X (Nie. X) was the first aircraft in a lineage of fighters developed by the French aviation firm Établissements Nieuport. The Nie. X was not originally designed as a military aircraft but was, rather, intended to be the French entry in the 1914 International Gordon-Bennett Air Race. When the race was cancelled at the outbreak of World War I, Nieuport modified the aircraft into a fighter. Despite the War, the Aviation Militaire (French Air Force) initially showed little interest in the Nie. X, but the British Royal Naval Air Service did. The British purchased and placed 24 of the machines into service. 

The first military versions of the Nie. X were two seat aircraft with a pilot and an observer/gunner. The airframe consisted of fabric-covered wood framing except for a thin metal cowling about the engine and forward fuselage. The aircraft was of sesquiplane design -its lower wing having less than half the area of its upper wing. Nieuport eventually converted the Nie. X into a single seat fighter with a single machine gun mounted atop the upper wing to fire over the propeller arc. With the development of the single-seat version, and after the pressures of war had clearly demonstrated the need for fighter aircraft, the Aviation Militaire changed its attitude and placed a sizeable order for the single-seat Nieuport X. 

The Nieuport X not only equipped British and French squadrons, but was also flown by the Belgians, Italians and Russians who built the fighter under license. However, the "heyday" of the Nie. X was brief. It entered combat service in May of 1915, but was gradually being replaced by its immediate successor, the Nieuport 11, by the early months of 1916. Nevertheless, the Nieuport X holds a special place in the historical annals of World War I as the first in the distinguished lineage of famous Nieuport fighters. 

The Nie. X modeled here was flown by Flt. Commander Reginald Bone, commanding officer of RNAS Detling. While flying his Nie. X, on March 19, 1916, Bone shot down one of the six German Friedrichshafen bombers that were attacking the English coastal cities of Dover, Deal and Ramsgate. For this action he received the Distinguished Service Order.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of Royal Naval Air Station (RNAS) Detling, Royal Naval Air Service, March, 1916.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Société Anonyme des Établissements Nieuport
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Le Rhône, 9 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 80 hp   (60 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed:  91 mph   (146 km/h)  
Ceiling:  13,123 ft   (4,000m)
Endurance:  2 hours, 45 minutes  
Empty Weight:  904 pounds  (410 kg)
Loaded Weight:  1,455 pounds  (660 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 26 feet 0 inches   (7.92 m)
Length: 23 feet 2 inches  (7.07 m)  
Height:  8 feet 9 inches  (2.67 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing 0.303 inch (7.62 mm) Lewis machine gun mounted atop upper wing firing over the propeller arc.   
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

