<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="301" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Nieuport 11 (XI) Bébé Sesquiplane]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Nieuport 11 was the second in the lineage of fighters designed for the Aviation Militaire (the French Air Force) during World War I by the French aviation firm Société Anonyme des Établissements Nieuport and its chief engineer Gustave Delage. The Nie.11 was one of the outstanding landmarks in the evolution of fighter aircraft. The machine was built in very large numbers in France by its parent company, in Italy under license by Nieuport-Macchi and in Russia under license by Dux. It was a smaller refinement of its immediate predecessor the Nieuport X. A sesquiplane, its upper wing had twice the surface area of its lower wing. The Nie.11 was constructed of wood framing covered with fabric except for the forward fuselage and engine cowling which were covered with thin aluminum sheet. The aircraft's small size led to the acquisition of its nickname, "Bébé" (baby). 

The Nie.11 entered service with the Aviation Militaire on January 5, 1916 at a time when the French had not yet developed synchronization between a fighter's forward firing machine gun and its propeller. Thus, the Nie.11's single machine gun was mounted atop the upper wing firing over its propeller arc. By the time of the battle of Verdun, which began on February 21, 1916, nine French Fighter Escadrilles were equipped with Nie.11s. 

The fighter proved to be fast, maneuverable and more than a match for the German Fokker and Pfalz "Eindeckers" (monoplanes), which were creating what Allied airman called the "Eindecker scourge". For several months the Nie.11 brought air superiority to the Allies. Some of France's most famous aces (Guynemer, De Rosa and Nungesser, among others) scored early victories while flying the Nie.11. 

In addition to equipping French fighter units, the Nie.11 was deployed by the air forces of Great Britain (modeled here), Belgium, Russia, Romania, Serbia, the Netherlands and the Ukraine. American volunteer pilots, flying for France before the entry of the United States into the war, formed, within the Aviation Militaire, the famous Lafayette Escadrille. They also flew the Nieuport 11. 

Although it remained in active service with the Italians until the late summer of 1917, by mid-summer 1916 it was being replaced on the Western Front by its faster and better armed successor, the Nieuport 17. Following their withdrawal from active combat, Nie.11s were employed as trainers by various Allied Air Forces.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 7 Squadron, Royal Naval Air Service, Dardanelles, Middle East Theater, 1916.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Société Anonyme des Établissements Nieuport
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> France
<b>Power plant:</b> One Le Rhône 9C, 9 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 80 hp (60 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 97 mph (156 km/h) 
Ceiling: 15,090 feet (4600 m)
Endurance: 2 hours, 30 minutes 
Empty Weight: 705 pounds (320 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1058 pounds (480 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 24 feet 9 inches (7.54 m)
Length: 19 feet 1inch (5.82 m)
Height: 8 feet 1 inch (2.46 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) fixed, forward-firing Lewis machine gun mounted atop the upper wing 
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

