<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="302" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Bristol Scout C]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Bristol Scout series of aircraft, originally designated the Scout "A", began as a sporting aircraft designed by Bristol's chief engineer, Frank Barnwell prior to the outbreak of World War I. The Scout was a single-seat biplane built from conventional wood framing covered with doped fabric and an aluminum sheet over the forward fuselage. The first Scouts deployed with the Royal Flying Corps received the designation Scout "B", though they differed from the "A" model in detail only. Similarly, the "C" model (displayed here) differed from its predecessor only in its internal arrangements and the reinforcement of its engine compartment. 

The Scout C was dispatched to the Royal Flying Corps and the Royal Naval Air Service beginning in March of 1915. There they provided protection for two-seat reconnaissance aircraft. Because synchronized machine gun technology was not yet available, the Scout was officially unarmed. However, pilots carried pistols and rifles; Ranken darts were also carried to be dropped on the enemy. Captain Lanoe G. Hawker won the first Victoria Cross for air-to-air combat when he downed three machine gun-equipped enemy aircraft in a Scout C armed with only a single shot carbine rifle mounted on the starboard side of the fuselage. The later "D" model Scout was the first of the line to carry machine guns.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the British Royal Naval Air Service, Eastchurch, Isle of Sheppey, England, March, 1915.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> British & Colonial Aeroplane Co
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Le Rhône, 7 cylinder, air-cooled rotary piston engine 80 hp (60 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 100 mph (161 km/h) 
Ceiling: 15,500 feet (4,724 m) 
Endurance: 2 hours, 30 minutes
Empty Weight: 760 pounds (345 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1250 pounds (567 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 24 feet 7 inches (7.5 m)
Length: 20 feet 8 inches (6.3 m)
Height: 8 feet 6 inches (2.5 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

