<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="303" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Trainer]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Bristol M.1C Monoplane Scout]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Bristol M.1C first flew in July 1916. As a monoplane, the Bristol M.1C was unique for its time. Virtually all of its contemporaries were biplanes or triplanes. Frank Barnwell designed this aircraft with a drag-reducing propeller spinner, few bracing wires to detract from the aircraft's speed and performance, and a smooth, aerodynamic fuselage. Barnwell also discard the wing warping method of lateral control used in previous monoplanes in favor of standard aileron control. These features created an aircraft capable of speeds up to 132 mph.

Despite its attributes, the British showed little interest in the 125 Bristol M.1Cs, perhaps stemming from a bias against monoplanes. Two other monoplane fighters were used in the war by the French and British, but neither of these achieved much acceptance with their respective air forces. The British War Office largely delegated its Bristol M.1Cs to a training role. No British Royal Flying Corps squadrons operating in France were equipped with the Bristol M.1C aircraft. The RFC No. 150 Squadron, however, flew 35 of these machines in Salonika, Greece. Still, most of the Bristol M.1Cs not sent to the Middle East spent the war as trainers, and their speed and performance were not used to their full potential.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 150 Squadron, British Royal Flying Corps, Salonika, Greece, June, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> British & Colonial Aeroplane Co
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Le Rhône 9J nine cylinder rotary engine 110 hp (82 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed:  130 mph (209 km/h) at sea level, 127 mph (204 km/h) at 5,000 ft (1,525 m) 
Ceiling: 19,750 feet (6020 m)
Endurance: 1hour 45 minutes
Empty Weight: 896 pounds (406 kg) 
Loaded Weight: 1348 pounds (611 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 30 feet 9 inches (9.37 m)
Length: 20 feet 51/2 inches (6.23 m)
Height: 7 feet 91/2 inches (2.37 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing synchronized 0.303 inch Vickers machine gun
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

