<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="306" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Trainer]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Grahame-White Type XV Boxkite]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Grahame-White Box-kite was first developed in 1912 by Claude Grahame-White, founder of Britain's first flying school at Hendon. The aircraft served as a trainer for students at the school before being converted for military use. The Box-Kite appeared in several different variants as time progressed and there is some debate as to how that progression should be characterized. Some scholars refer to the Box-Kite as the predecessor to the Grahame-White Type XII and Type XV, while others state that all the variants of the machine were eventually renamed to the Type XV.

The earliest version of the aircraft resembled the Farman biplane of 1909. It included both fore and aft elevators, a pusher engine and was controlled from an exposed position directly over the mid-point of the lower wing. Later variants, like the one modeled here, included a pilot's nacelle, more powerful engines and wings with a staggered span.

In November of 1913, a Box-kite piloted by Marcus Manton participated in an air-firing test at Bisley, England. The plane was equipped with a Lewis machine gun and the gunner, Lieutenant Stellingwerf, successfully managed to hit ground targets during two passes of the target range, thus demonstrating the potential for the airplane as a weapon of war.

The Grahame-White XV began equipping flight schools for the Royal Flying Corps and the Royal Naval Air Service in December of 1913 and served as a basic training aircraft. The Grahame-White Type XV modeled here is based on a late variant in the series -likely from 1916. The aircraft depicted was based at the Royal Flying Corps aerodrome at Hendon, north of London. 

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> This model incorporates a compilation of features from several Grahame-White variants. The pilot nacelle and staggered wings suggest it is a later model, but the large anti-nose-over skids on the aircraft's undercarriage were mostly used in early versions. The model also shows a 9 cylinder engine consistent with the 1913 version but with an installation appropriate for the 1916 model. ]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents a two-seat trainer, Hendon, England.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Grahame-White Aviation Co, Ltd
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Gnôme Le Rhône, 7 cylinder rotary air-cooled piston engine of 80 hp (60kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 59 mph (95 km/h)
Ceiling: 8,530 feet (2,600)
Endurance: 3 hours, 15 minutes 
Empty Weight: 1,445 pounds (655kg)
Loaded weight: not documented
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 27 feet 8 inches 
Length: 23 feet 5 inches 
Height: 11 feet 2 inches
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>2
]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

