<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="307" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Vickers F.B.5 Gunbus]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Vickers F.B.5 Gunbus features a machine gun positioned in the fuselage's forward cockpit, which allows its gunner a clear field of forward fire. The pilot flew the plane from the rear cockpit and a pusher engine and propeller were positioned behind the pilot. 

The F.B.5 was ordered into production by the Royal Flying Corp on August 14, 1914, just two weeks after the outbreak of World War I. The first production Vickers F.B.5s reached the Western Front in early February of 1915. The following July the No. 11 Squadron was the first fighter combat unit of any air force to enter service flying a single aircraft type - the Vickers F.B.5. A total of 241 F.B.5s were built in England by Vickers. Another 99 were built in France under license by the Société Anonyme Darracq and twelve were built in Denmark by the <i>Tojhusvaerksted</i>. 

Most F.B.5s were deployed over the Western Front with a smaller number retained in England for home defense. However, F.B.5s suffered from unreliable power plants and from marginal performance, properties. These problems shortened their careers and lead to their withdrawal from the Western Front by the autumn of 1916. A few were briefly relegated to Royal Flying Corps training schools, but most were scrapped.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the Royal Flying Corps, No. 11 Squadron, Western Front, France, July 1915.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Vickers
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Gnôme Monosoupape 9 cylinder air-cooled rotary engine of 100 hp (75 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 70 mph at 5,000 feet (113 km/h at 1525 m) 
Ceiling: 9,000 feet (2743 m)
Endurance: 4 hours and 30 minutes 
Empty Weight: 1220 pounds (553 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2050 pounds (930 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 36 feet 6 inches (11.13 m)
Length: 27 feet 2 inches (8.28 m)
Height: 11 feet 6 inches (3.51 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One flexible forward firing 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

