<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="310" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Royal Aircraft Factory B.E.2a]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Royal Aircraft Factory (R.A.F.) at Farnborough was established from the H.M. Balloon Factory to design, build and test new aircraft. However, the facility drew a great deal of criticism because it often created its "new" designs by essentially rebuilding salvaged aircraft from other manufacturers. During World War I, Geoffrey de Havilland designed a series of "B.E." designated aircraft. The "B.E." acronym stood for "Blériot Experimental", because the aircraft were based on the designs of the famous French aviation pioneer, Louis Blériot. 

The B.E.2 was the second aircraft in the series, but differed little from its predecessor, the B.E.1. The B.E.2a modeled here had wood framing with doped fabric covering except for varnished plywood about the cockpit and metal sheeting about the engine. It employed wing warping for lateral control. The aircraft also
featured an air-cooled inline engine. This saved substantial weight and improved performance over aircraft with liquid-cooled engines. 

The B.E.2a first flew in the second week of August, 1912 when it took part in the British Military Trials on Salisbury Plain in England. It outperformed all its competition and British military leaders immediately placed production orders. Although over 3,100 B.E.2 aircraft were built by the end of World War I, only five prototype B.E.2a's were built by the R.A.F. The majority of the type were built under license by other British aircraft firms, including Armstrong Whitworth, Handley Page, British Colonial and Vickers. 

At the outbreak of World War I, B.E. 2a reconnaissance aircraft were sent to France along with the British Expeditionary Force. Among these was B.E. 2a No. 336, modeled here. A Vickers built machine, it went to France on August 13, 1914 and was one of the first aircraft of the War fitted with wireless communication equipment. 

By late 1916 the B.E.2a had been replaced in France by newer and far more competitive aircraft. Among these replacements were several newer R.A.F. machines designed by Geoffrey de Havilland. The B.E.2s returned to England where they were deployed in home defense and as trainers. By 1918 they had largely disappeared from military service. Some lingered on following the War in a variety of civilian uses. ]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 4 Squadron, British Royal Flying Corps, Western Front, August, 1914.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Royal Aircraft Factory
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Renault, 8 cylinder inline V air-cooled piston engine of 70 hp (53 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 70 mph (113km/h) 
Ceiling: 10,000 feet (3,050 m)
Endurance: 3 hours
Empty Weight: 1,274 pounds (578 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,600 pounds (726 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 38 feet 7 inches (11.76 m) 
Length: 29 feet 6 inches (8.99 m) 
Height: 10 feet 2 inches (3.10 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Usually none. However a few may have been fitted with a single fixed forward firing synchronized 7.7 mm (0.303 inch) Vickers machine gun and/or 45 kg (100 pounds) of bombs
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

