<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="314" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Experimental Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Radley-England Waterplane]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Radley-England Waterplane was one of three aircraft originally entered to compete in the 1913 <i>Daily Mail</i> waterplane race around Britain. Built by early aviators, James Radley and Gordon England, the Waterplane faced stiff competition from machines built by Sopwith and the Short Brothers. Unfortunately, the Radley-England team was forced to withdraw before the race due to engine problems.

The Radley-England design utilized a common overall configuration for seaplanes of its time. The craft was a biplane with two pontoons and a "pusher" propeller. The aircraft did, however exhibit a couple of very unique features. Rather than including a standard cockpit or flying-boat hull, the Radley-England's pilot and passengers occupied separate cockpits positioned in the center of each pontoon. The aircraft was first configured with a single cockpit in each pontoon with the pilot and one passenger occupying the right float and up to three passengers in the left. This configuration was later scrapped in favor of two smaller, tandem cockpits in each pontoon.

In addition to the unusual seating arrangements, the Radley-England Waterplane also utilized a highly unique engine configuration. The aircraft was designed to make use of three 50 hp Gnôme engines mounted in tandem to drive a single propeller. This unusual configuration was later replaced by a more conventional 150 hp Sunbeam engine.

While the Radley-England Waterplane was created at a time when the British Navy was becoming interested in seaplanes for military use, there is no evidence that this plane was mass produced, nor that it ever participated in World War I.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> This model depicts the Radley-England Waterplane in British naval markings. The source for this paint scheme is unclear. The model also depicts the aircraft equipped with a single Gnôme engine and small cockpits in each pontoon, each capable of carrying a single person. Again, the source material for this configuration is unclear, but may represent a blend of the aircraft's two known revisions.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model depicts the Radley-England Waterplane in British naval markings.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> James Radley and Gordon England
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> Three Gnôme rotary air cooled piston engines of 50 hp
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 60 mph (100 km/h) 
Ceiling: Not documented
Endurance: 2 hours 45 minutes 
Weight: Not documented
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 51 feet 6 inches (15.70 m)
Length: 29 feet 2 inches (8.89 m)
Height: 10 feet 1 inch (3.07 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>1 pilot and up to 4 passengers
<br />]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

