<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="315" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Aircraft]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Royal Aircraft Factory F.E.2b]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Royal Aircraft Factory's F.E.2b was designed to provide the British Royal Flying Corps with an armed reconnaissance platform which could also perform as a fighter. Designed in 1914 in the era before engineering technology had established a means for firing a machine gun through a propeller arc without destroying the propeller, the R.A.F. F.E.2b was configured in a "pusher" configuration with the propeller mounted behind the cockpit. The aircraft had its twin machine guns positioned in its forward observer cockpit. The pilot was positioned in the rear of its fuselage, just ahead of the engine and propeller. 

The machine first flew on January 26, 1915, only a few months after the outbreak of World War I. It entered service with squadrons of the Royal Flying Corps the following summer. Interestingly, the Royal Aircraft Factory, which designed the machine, built only 47 of the aircraft out of a total production of over 1,900. The vast majority were built under license by six other British aircraft firms. 

Perhaps the F.E. 2b's greatest moment in World War I came on June 18, 1916 when an F.E.2b shot down the famous German air ace, Max Immelmann. Despite the large number manufactured, the F.E. 2b's operational career as a reconnaissance fighter was relatively brief. By the latter part of 1916 it was becoming painfully clear that the pusher type of aircraft was inferior to that of fighters which had a "tractor" engine which pulled them through the air. The appearance of German Albatros fighters with this tractor configuration vividly proved this point. As a result, after little more than a year's service on the Western Front in the role for which they were designed, the machines were withdrawn to England for home defense or were relegated to night bombing. Despite their obsolescence, numbers of R.A.F. F.E.2bs remained in active duty with the Royal Flying Corps in these secondary roles until the Armistice on November 11, 1918.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 25 Squadron, Royal Flying Corps, Western Front, November 1915.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Royal Aircraft Factory
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Beardmore, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engine of 160 hp (119 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 91 mph (146 km/h) 
Ceiling: 11,000 feet (3353 m)
Endurance: 3 hours
Empty Weight: 2061 pounds (935 kg) 
Loaded Weight: 3,038 pounds (1378 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 47 feet 9 inches (14.55 m)
Length: 32 feet 3 inches (9.83 m)
Height: 12 feet 7 inches (3.84 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Twin 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine guns in a flexible mount in forward cockpit, up to 350 pounds (159 kg) of bombs 
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

