<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="316" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Martinsyde F.4 Buzzard]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Martinsyde F.4 Buzzard was probably the best and most advanced fighter aircraft built in Great Britain during World War I. Yet, only a small number were manufactured and of these even fewer were deployed in combat. As a result, the Buzzard has been essentially lost in the historical annals of the War. 

In the autumn of 1917 the British Air Ministry issued a specification for a new fighter, which could counter Germany's new Fokker and Albatros machines. The British firm, Martinsyde, Ltd. responded with a new aircraft, the F.4 Buzzard. The aircraft's design paid special attention to aerodynamics. In an effort to reduce wind resistance it was given only a single pair of intra-wing struts, reducing the need for bracing wires. Even the aircraft's two machine guns were enclosed within the engine cowling. They fired through gun tubes which traversed the radiator located immediately behind the propeller. The Buzzard's aerodynamically clean airframe was coupled with a 300 hp (224 kw) Hispano-Suiza engine, one of the most powerful aircraft power-plants then available. The result was a fighter which possessed great speed, great maneuverability and a remarkable rate of climb. 

After very successful flight trials in the summer of 1918, the British Air Ministry ordered the building of 50 pre-production aircraft. The United States also contracted to build 1,500 for the Army Air Force. But events doomed the Buzzard, Several months before the Buzzard's test flights, the British Air Ministry settled on the Sopwith Snipe as the Royal Flying Corp's new standard fighter aircraft. By the time the Buzzard completed its flight trials, Snipes were pouring off the assembly lines. 

Some Buzzards were sent to France in the autumn of 1918 but were largely limited to familiarization training flights. Only the original 50 machines were built for the RAF prior to the end of the War, after which, production was discontinued in favor of the Sopwith Snipe. The huge United States order was also canceled. Following the War, some of the aircraft were purchased by Finland, Spain, Portugal and post-revolutionary Russia.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified fighter squadron of the British Royal Air Force Aerodrome, western France, November, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Martinsyde, Ltd
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Hispano-Suiza 8b, 8 cylinder inline V liquid-cooled piston engine of 300 hp (224 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 145 mph (233km/h)
Ceiling: 24,000 feet (7,315 m)
Endurance: 3 hours 
Empty Weight: 1,811 pounds (821 kg) 
Loaded Weight: 2,396 pounds (1087 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 32 feet 9 inches (9.98 m)
Length: 25 feet 6 inches (7.77 m)
Height: 8 feet 10 inches (2.69 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Vickers machine guns enclosed in the forward fuselage 
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

