<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="317" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Short Bomber]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Short Bomber claims the distinction of being the first aircraft, by itself, to attack and destroy a warship. In the early months of World War I, Britain lagged behind other countries in the construction of large heavy bombers capable of carrying large bomb loads over great distances. To address this deficiency, the British aircraft company, Short Brothers, created its "Short Bomber" as a transitional or "stopgap" aircraft. These machines filled the void until the British aircraft industry could produce true heavy bombers like the Handley-Page and Vickers machines. For a "stopgap" aircraft, the Short Bomber had an excellent career, especially considering its construction. With its single-engine design, the Short Bomber closely resembled an oversized fighter. 

Early in the war, the Short Bomber achieved a noteworthy place in the history of military aviation. On August 15, 1915, a land-based Short Bomber of the Royal Navy Flying Service torpedoed and sank a Turkish cruiser in the Dardanelles. This action represented the beginning of the transition of naval power from the large caliber heavy guns of battleships and cruisers to weapons carried and delivered by warplanes.

Nine hundred Short Bombers were built for the British Royal Navy. Most served as torpedo bombers and a few as horizontal bombers and reconnaissance aircraft. The Short Bomber performed well enough that the British Royal Flying Corps took 89 of the machines for use as bombers on the Western front. By the middle of 1917 the Short Bombers were being replaced on the Western Front by more modern and capable multiple engine bombers. The naval variants, however, remained in service until the war's end in November 1918.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents a naval torpedo bomber of the Royal Naval Flying Service in the Middle East Theater of Operations, August 1915.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Short Brothers
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Rolls-Royce Eagle III, 12 cylinder liquid-cooled inline V piston engine of 250 hp (187 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 77 mph (125 km/h)
Ceiling: 9,500 feet (2,696 m)
Endurance: 6 hours 
Empty Weight: 5,000 pounds (227 kg)
Loaded Weight: 6,800 pounds (3,085 kg) 
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 85 feet 0 inches (25.91 m)
Length: 45 feet 0 inches (13.72 m)
Height: 15 feet 0 inches (4.57 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun in flexible mount in rear cockpit, One 1,000 lb (454 kg) torpedo or equivalent weight in bombs carried beneath the fuselage
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

