<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="318" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Vickers Vimy F.B.27A]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[Despite its limited use during World War I, the Vickers Vimy represents the beginning of a long line of British Vickers bombers which served through World War II and even the "Cold War" of the late 20th Century. The Vimy, which was designed to have a range capable of bombing Berlin and other major German cities, entered development in the spring of 1917. The Vimy achieved its long range by relying on two Rolls-Royce engines which could function for hours without difficulty.

The first Vimy prototype flew on November 30, 1917 and the British Air Ministry immediately placed an order for 150 machines and later increased it to1,130. Given the size and the expense of the Vimy, this order was extraordinary. The Royal Flying Corps received only three Vimys, however, prior to the German capitulation in November 1918. These were still completing training with their new crews when the War ended and no Vimys carried out operational bombing raids during the War. After the War's conclusion, the Air Ministry reduced its large wartime order for Vimys to only 221 aircraft. 

No longer needed for the war effort, the Vimy participated in many post-war endurance flights, including the first non-stop trans-Atlantic flight. In June 1919, British pilots John Alcock and Arthur Whitten-Brown flew a specially modified Vimy 1,890 miles (3,042 km) from St. Johns, Newfoundland, to Clifden, Northern Ireland. Six months later, in December 1919, the Australian pilots and brothers Ross and Keith Smith flew a Vimy from England to Australia in a multiple segment flight of 11,130 miles (17,912 km).]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft from an unidentified bomber squadron of the British Royal Flying Corps, September 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Vickers
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> Two Rolls-Royce Eagle VIII, V-12 cylinder liquid-cooled piston engines of 360 hp (269kW) each
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 103 mph (166km/h) 
Ceiling: 10,500 feet (3,200 m)
Range: 900 miles (1,448 km) -specially modified models up to 2,000 miles (3,219 km) 
Empty Weight: 7,100 pounds (3,220 kg)
Loaded Weight: 10,884 pounds (4,937 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 67 feet 2 inches (20.47 m) 
Length: 43 feet 6 inches (13.26 m) 
Height: 15 feet 3 inches 4.65 m) 
<b>Armament:</b> two 7.7 mm (0.303 inch) Lewis machine guns in flexible mounts in nose and waist of fuselage, up to 1123kg (2,476 lbs) of bombs 
<b>Crew:</b>3]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

