<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="319" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Handley Page O/400 (H.P.12)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Handley Page O/400 and its predecessor, the O/100 were the principle British heavy bombers of World War I. British interest in acquiring a large bomber capable of carrying a heavy bomb load over long distances began in 1914 before the outbreak of World War I. The Royal Navy wished to monitor the movements of German U-boats and warships, which could interfere with the shipping lanes through which the greater part of England's food and raw materials were delivered. The aircraft firm, Handley Page Ltd. responded with a twin-engine machine designated the O/100, which proved successful as both a naval patrol aircraft and a land bomber.

Handley Page continued to improve the design of the O/100 and, in 1917, installed a new fuel system. The new system moved the aircraft's fuel tanks out of the engine nacelles, placing them instead in the fuselage and upper wing. This new version was re-designated the Handley-Page O/400 (modeled here). Like the 100, the 400 had wings that folded back against its fuselage, allowing storage in existing hangers. Other improvements and changes were structural in nature and were largely confined to the interior of the aircraft. The biggest difference between the two bombers lay in the more powerful engines of the 400. 

The O/400 first saw combat service in the spring of 1917. It flew U-Boat patrols and bombed German military depots and industrial targets. Over 400 Handley Page O/400 bombers entered service with the British Royal Flying Corps and the Royal Naval Flying Service before the Armistice but only one British O/400 was ever based outside England or France. A single machine was sent to Palestine in July of 1918 to support the campaigns of Colonel T. E. Lawrence -better known as "Lawrence of Arabia". 

The American firm, Standard Aircraft Corporation, was also contracted to build 1,000 Handley-Page O/400s for the United States Army Air Corps. Instead of British Rolls-Royce power plants, the American O/400s were fitted with American Liberty engines. The day before their production began, WWI ended. As a result, the majority of the order was cancelled and only 107 aircraft were completed. The vast majority went straight into storage to be scrapped years later. However, seven were refurbished in 1920 and used in General Billy Mitchell's bombing trials on former German World War I warships anchored in the Chesapeake Bay -trials intended to prove the value of air power in naval warfare.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 97 Squadron, Royal Air Force, Stonehenge Aerodrome, England, September 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Handley Page, Ltd.
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> Two Rolls-Royce Eagle VIII, 12 cylinder V, liquid-cooled piston engines of 360 hp (268 kW) each
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 97 mph (156 km/h) 
Ceiling: 8,500 feet (2591 m)
Range: 650 miles (1041 km) 
Empty Weight: 8,502 pounds (3856 kg)
Loaded Weight: 14,000 pounds (6350 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 100 feet (30.48 m)
Length: 62 feet 10 inches (19.15 m)
Height: 22 feet (6.71 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Up to five 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) single or dual Lewis machine guns in flexible mounts, a maximum of 2,000 pounds (907 kg) of bombs 
<b>Crew:</b>4]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

