<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="320" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Blackburn Kangaroo (R.T.I, Reconnaissance Torpedo I)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[During World War I, Great Britain was slow in the production of large heavy bombers. While its chief enemy Germany and even its Russian ally had such machines in operation in the early weeks of the conflict, it was not until the middle of the War that England had it's first big bombers (The Handley Page O/100 and O/400) and not until the end of the that the Blackburn Kangaroo was put into service.

In retaliation for air raids over English cities, the British High Command was intent on obtaining even better long range bombers which could attack German cities and the German industrial complex. Near the end of the War the Blackburn Kangaroo bomber was designed and built in response to these British War Office specifications. The Kangaroo developed from the earlier G.P. and S.P. seaplanes built by the British Blackburn Aeroplane & Motor Company for maritime reconnaissance. The Kangaroos utilized wheeled undercarriages in place of the seaplanes' pontoons. The Kangaroo had a long and slender fuselage which did not allow for crew movement from one position to another. This was a design concern should the pilot become incapacitated during flight. In this configuration, Kangaroos were delivered to both the Royal Flying Corps and the Royal Naval Air Service. Eleven of fifteen Blackburn Kangaroos were placed into active service prior to the War's end. 

Kangaroos were primarily deployed in maritime patrols over the North Sea. On such missions, Kangaroos were reported as having sunk one German submarine and having heavily damaged four others. The machines also deployed to Belgium with a bomber squadron tasked with attacking land targets within Germany. Many of these aircraft survived the War and were subsequently converted into civilian transports. They were all retired by the late 1920s.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the Royal Flying Corps, Belgium, August, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Blackburn Aeroplane & Motor Company Ltd
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> Two Rolls-Royce Falcon II, 12 cylinder inline V liquid-cooled piston engines of 250 hp (187 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 100 mph (161 km/h) 
Ceiling: 10,500 feet (3,200 m)
Endurance: 8 hours 
Empty Weight: 5,284 pounds (2,397 kg)
Loaded Weight: 8,017 pounds (3636 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 74 feet 10 inches (22.81 m) 
Length: 46 feet 0 inches (14.02 m)
Height: 16 feet 10 inches (5.13 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two 0.0303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine guns in flexible mounts in nose and rear fuselage, Four 230 lb (104 kg) bombs in fuslage bomb bay and up to four additional 230 lb (104 kg) bombs on external racks. 
<b>Crew:</b>3 or 4]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

