<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="321" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Sopwith Tabloid (S.S.)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[On October 8, 1914, just two months after the outbreak of World War I, Lieutenant R.L.G. Marix of the Royal Naval Air Service, destroyed the German airship Zeppelin Z.IX and its storage shed at Dusseldorf while flying a Sopwith Tabloid. This event marked the first significant bombing attack by a British aviator. Marix dropped two small incendiary bombs causing the airship's hydrogen filled gas cells to ignite turning the Zeppelin into an inferno. 

The Tabloid began as a racing and demonstration aircraft in 1913, well before World War I. During its official trials at Farnborough, the aircraft returned performance figures that surpassed aircraft of the time. After a seaplane version blew away the competition at the Schneider Trophy race in April of 1914, the British military took interest. Both the Royal Flying Corps and the Royal Naval Air Service placed orders for the aircraft. 

Tabloids saw extensive service over the Western Front during the early weeks of the War. During this early period military aircraft were usually unarmed with pilots employing their personal pistols and rifles in aerial combat. In the very early spring of 1915 machine guns were fitted to Tabloids in some squadrons. They served with distinction on the Western Front but were also used in the Mediterranean and Middle East theaters of operation. Production of Tabloids ended in the spring of 1915 as they were phased out and replaced by more capable machines. However, a numbers of Tabloids remained deployed on the home front as Zeppelin interceptors and as trainers while others were employed as reconnaissance aircraft on the Western Front and in the Middle East. Some had lingering careers in civilian life following the War.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> The prototype for this model was a Royal Naval Air Service Tabloid, which was fitted with a Lewis gun, mounted on the starboard side of the cockpit to fire through the propeller arc. Metal plates on the propeller deflected any bullets that struck it.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 1 Squadron, Royal Naval Flying Service, Gosport, England, April 1915.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Sopwith Aviation Co Ltd
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Gnôme Monosoupape, 9 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 100 hp (74.5 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 92 mph (148 km/h) 
Ceiling: 15,600 feet (4755 m)
Endurance: 2 hours, 30 minutes 
Empty Weight: 1,200 pounds (454 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,580 pounds (717 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 25 feet 8 inches (7.82 m)
Length: 22 feet 8 inches (6.91 m)
Height: 9 feet 9 inches (2.97 m)
<b>Armament:</b> After March of 1915, one 0.303 inch machine gun fixed to the starboard side of the fuselage firing forward through the propeller arc -the back of the propeller was fitted with protective steel plates to deflect those bullets striking it, after October of 1915 the machine gun was synchronized with the engine. Up to ten 25 lb bombs
<b>Crew:</b>1
<br />]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

