<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="322" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Floatplane Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Sopwith Baby]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[With the outbreak of World War I, the Royal Naval Air Service (RNAS) realized a need for a fast, single-seat seaplane. To meet this need, the RNAS adapted the winner of the 1914 Schneider Trophy (a seaplane race) for military use. The winning aircraft, which was a seaplane variant of the Sopwith Tabloid, became known as the "Schneider". The aircraft was deployed in naval reconnaissance missions, and as a zeppelin interceptor. In September of 1915, a new version of the Schneider was developed. The variant, which was nicknamed the Sopwith Baby, included a more powerful 110 hp engine and redesigned forward fuselage characterized by its horseshoe-shaped engine cowling. 

The Baby also differed from its predecessor in its armament. While Schneiders were typically equipped with a single Lewis gun, angled to fire above the propeller arc, the Babies utilized a propeller-synchronized machine gun. Some later models were also provided a second machine gun. A number of Babies were equipped with Rankin explosive darts in place of guns for making anti-shipping attacks and at least one (the prototype of this model) was armed with 10 Le Prieur rockets. In this last configuration, five rockets were attached to the outboard bracing struts of the machine's wings. 

A total of 286 Babies were manufactured in Great Britain during World War I. Of these, 195 were built, under license, by the British aircraft firm Blackburn. Although identical to the Sopwith machines, they were often referred to as "Blackburn Babies". The Baby was also built, under license, by the Italian firm Ansaldo. Babies saw wide service throughout the War. They operated not only from costal bases, but were among the first aircraft to be deployed from capital ships and from Great Britain's early seaplane tenders and aircraft carriers. Babies were employed in a wide variety of mission roles -as fighters, reconnaissance platforms, anti-submarine and anti-shipping aircraft, and Zeppelin interceptors. The careers of the Babies essentially ended at the conclusion of World War I with a few lingering on in secondary service -all were all gone by 1920.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> The corrosive effect of sea water caused severe weathering of seaborne aircraft, especially to their undersurfaces and pontoons. This model attempts to replicate these changes in a Baby which had seen extensive service.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of an unidentified squadron, Royal Naval Flying Service, British Home Islands, October 1915.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Sopwith Aviation Co Ltd
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Clerget, 9 cylinder, air-cooled rotary piston engine of 130 hp (97 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 100 mph (161 km/h) 
Ceiling: 10,000 feet (3048 m)
Endurance: 2 hours, 15 minutes 
Empty Weight: 1,226 pounds (556 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,715 pounds (778 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 25 feet 8 inches (7.82 m)
Length: 23 feet 0 inches (7.01 m)
Height: 10 feet 0 inches (3.05 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed forward firing 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun mounted on the center of the upper wing- firing above the propeller arc, 10 Le Prieur incendiary rockets. 
<b>Crew:</b>1
<br />]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

