<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="323" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Sopwith Triplane]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Sopwith Triplane initiated an intense but brief vogue in fighter aircraft. Though its three-wing design was radical for the time, its fuselage had been derived from the craft's immediate predecessor, the Sopwith Pup. Both aircrcraft were designed by Herbert Smith, chief engineer of the Sopwith Aviation Company. By adding a third wing to his design, Smith increased the aircraft's lift and gave it greater maneuverability and a higher rate of climb.

The new triplane first flew in May of 1916. After successful pre-production test flights, 400 machines were immediately ordered. The British Royal Flying Corps, however, favored other fighter types and displayed little interest in the triplane. As a result, only pilots of the Royal Navy flew the Sopwith Triplane. With its allocation to only this single service, its total production was limited to just 144 machines. 

The Sopwith Triplane began operations in February of 1917. It achieved great initial success on the Western Front and briefly shifted air superiority to the Allies. Canadian ace Raymond Collishaw, among others, flew the Sopwith Triplane. In May and June of 1917, Collishaw shot down seven enemy aircraft and damaged another seventeen in this machine. 

To compete with this new British fighter, no less than fourteen different German aircraft manufacturers designed and built triplane prototypes. Of these, the Fokker Dr.I performed best in competitive flight trials and became the direct German response to the Sopwith Triplane. The Fokker Dr.I achieved fame through the exploits of German's Baron Manfred von Richthofen, the highest scoring ace of World War I. He flew a Fokker Dr.I during the last months of his life. 

Although their careers were brilliant, the triplanes of both sides were built in relatively small numbers and served in active combat for only a brief period. As early as the summer of 1917, Sopwith Camels succeeded the British triplanes. The German triplanes were also replaced by better and more modern Albatros and Fokker fighters.

This particular model exemplifies the Sopwith Triplane flown by Lt. C.D. Booker of the Royal Navy between April and August of 1917. He achieved 17 air victories during this time.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 8 Squadron, Royal Naval Flying Service, St. Eloi, France, August 1917.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Sopwith Aviation Co Ltd
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Clerget 9B, 9 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 130 hp (97kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 117 mph (187 km/h) @ 6,000 ft (1,830 m)
Ceiling: 20,500 feet (6,248 m)
Endurance: 2 hours, 45 minutes 
Empty Weight: 1,100 lbs (499 kg)
Loaded Weight: 1,541 lbs (699 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 26 feet 6 inches (8.08 m)
Length: 18 feet 10 inches (5.74 m)
Height: 10 feet 6 inches (3.20 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing synchronized 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Vickers machine gun 
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

