<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="328" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[ Sopwith 1 1/2 Strutter Single-Seat Bomber]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Sopwith 1 1/2 Strutter was the first British aircraft to have a machine gun synchronized to fire forward through its propeller arc. Designed and built by the Sopwith Aviation Company, it acquired the name of "1 1/2 Strutter" from its characteristic W shaped cabane wing struts. Though the name was originally unofficial, the Royal Navy Air Service and the Royal Flying Corps later adopted the name after it entered common usage. 

Two variants of the 1 1/2 Strutter existed -a two-seat fighter and a single-seat light bomber (modeled here). The bomber version eliminated the rear crew position in order to carry a bomb load within the machine's fuselage. The single-seat variant was used primarily by the Royal Naval Air Service, though some were delivered to the Royal Flying Corps.

A total of 1,513 of both variants of the 1 1/2 Strutter were built in Great Britain during World War I. British demand for the machines eventually exceeded the ability of its parent company to supply the needed aircraft. Other companies began to manufacture it under license, including the British firms Fairey; Morgan & Co.; Hooper; Westland; Vickers; Mann & Egerton; and Ruston & Proctor. Several French aviation companies also built both the two seat fighter and the single seat bomber version under license. A total of 4,497 of both variants were manufactured by the French, more than three times the number built by the British. 

In the spring of 1916, British units in the Royal Navy Air Service began flying the 1 1/2 Strutter. Later the Royal Flying Corps also ordered the machine to use on the Western Front. However, By the close of 1916, the 1 1/2 Strutter was becoming obsolete and by the middle of 1917 most of the British machines were being withdrawn from frontline combat service. 

The French continued to employ numbers of the aircraft well into 1918 and sold some of the French-built 1 1/2 Strutters to the air forces of the United States, Russia, Belgium, Romania, Japan and Greece. Many of these foreign exported machines fulfilled training roles. By the early 1920s the outdated 1 1/2 Strutters had passed from the scene. <b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> This model depicts an aircraft armed with a forward-firing Lewis gun mounted on the top wing. However, some sources indicate that the bomber variants were more commonly equipped like their fighter counterparts with a propeller-synchronized machine gun mounted on the forward fuselage.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 76 Squadron, Royal Flying Corps, Western Front, June, 1917.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Sopwith Aviation Co Ltd
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Clerget 9Z, 9 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 130 hp
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 96 mph (154.50 km/h) 
Ceiling: 12,700 feet
Endurance: 4 hours 15 minutes 
Empty Weight: 1,316 pounds (596.93 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,342 pounds (1,062.31 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 33 feet 7 inches
Length: 25 feet 1 inch
Height: 10 feet 2 inches
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing 0.303 inch Lewis machine gun mounted on top of upper wing, 600 lbs of bombs 
<b>Crew:</b>1
]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

