<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="330" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Sopwith Snipe (7.F.1)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Sopwith Snipe was the last in Sopwith's lineage of fighters to see combat in World War I. Originally designated the Sopwith 7.F.1, the machine acquired the nickname "Snipe" which stuck and was subsequently officially adopted. Sopwith's senior engineer, Herbert Smith, designed the Snipe, which was intended to replace his earlier design, the ubiquitous ubiquitous Sopwith Camel. The Snipe was built around the powerful new 230 hp (171.5 kW) Bentley B.R.2 rotary engine. Its external appearance was very similar to the Camel; Both aircraft shared the same rounded fuselage, the same raised hump in front of the cockpit, which housed two machine guns, the same two-bay wing bracing (though the Snipe had a slightly longer wing span), and the same tail plane. 

After very successful flight trials in the autumn of 1917, the British Air Ministry designated the Snipe as Great Britain's new standard fighter and ordered it into mass production. In face of the urgent need for the new machine, manufacture of the Snipe was also licensed to Boulton & Paul, Coventry Ordnance Works, Napier and Ruston, Proctor in England, and Nieuport in France. The first production aircraft began equipping operational fighter units of the Royal Air Force on the Western Front in the early summer of 1918. Although the Snipe did not possess exceptional speed, it was highly maneuverable and had a very high rate of climb. Further, it was sturdy and capable of withstanding a great deal of punishment. Many authorities, then and now, regard the Snipe as the best Allied fighter in combat service at the end of World War I. 

In April of 1918, the Royal Flying Corps was merged with the Royal Naval Flying Service. The new combined service was renamed the Royal Air Force (RAF). The Snipe remained its principle fighter. Production continued into the early 1920s with over 1,100 built and the Snipe remained in service until 1926. This model replicates a "factory fresh" Snipe flown on the Western Front during the last days of World War I by Victoria Cross recipient Major W.G. Barker.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 201 Squadron, Royal Air Force, Western Front, October 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Sopwith Aviation Co Ltd
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Bentley B.R.2, 9 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 230 hp (172 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 121 mph (195 km/h) 
Ceiling: 19,500 feet (5943 kg)
Endurance: 3 hours 
Empty Weight: 1,312 pounds (595 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,020 pounds (916 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 31 feet 1 inches (9.47 m)
Length: 19 feet 10 inches (6.05 m)
Height: 9 feet 6 inches (2.90 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Vickers machine guns, four 25 pound (11.3 kg) bombs on external racks 
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

