<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="332" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[de Havilland (Airco) D.H.2]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[This machine was one of the earliest aircraft of World War I designed specifically as a fighter. The D.H.2 was produced by the British firm, Aircraft Manufacturing Company Ltd. (Airco). The aircraft acquired the name, "de Havilland", after its designer, Geoffery de Havilland, who would subsequently go on to develop and head one of England's most distinguished aircraft companies; a company which produced military and civilian aircraft throughout the twentieth century. 

The D.H.2 was a direct descendent of the D.H.1, a two seat reconnaissance machine also designed by de Havilland. The smaller, single-seat D.H.2 was otherwise very similar in both appearance and construction to its predecessor. Its fuselage and wings consisted of fabric stretched over wood framing. The aircraft had a single forward-firing Lewis machine gun in the nose with the engine and propeller in a "pusher" position behind the pilot, thus giving the machine gun a free field of forward fire. 

The first prototype D.H.2 flew on June 1, 1915 and the first production models entered service on the Western Front a month later with the 5th Wing of the British Royal Flying Corps. The D.H.2 proved to be a stable, durable and successful fighter. A machine of No.24 Squadron achieved the first Western Front D.H.2 air victory on August 9, 1915. A total of just over 400 were built and delivered to the Royal Flying Corps. Of these, 266 were deployed with the British Expeditionary Forces in France. By late 1916 and into 1917 these machines were gradually retired from active combat service, having been replaced by more modern and more heavily armed fighter aircraft. The D.H.2s labored on throughout the remainder of the war as training aircraft at Royal Flying Corps flight schools.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 24 Squadron, Royal Flying Corps, Western Front, September, 1915.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Aircraft Manufacturing Co Ltd (Airco)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Gnôme Monosoupape, 9 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 100 hp (75 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 93 mph (150 km/h) 
Ceiling: 12,255 feet (3735 m) 
Endurance: 2 hours 45 minutes 
Empty Weight: 944 pounds (428 kg) 
Loaded Weight: 1,441 pounds (654 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 28 feet 3 inches (8.61 m)
Length: 25 feet 2 inches (7.68 m)
Height: 9 feet 6 inches (2.91)
<b>Armament:</b> One flexible forward-firing 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun with a 47 round drum
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

