<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="333" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[de Havilland (Airco) D.H.4]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The de Havilland D.H.4 was the first British aircraft specifically designed for use as a daylight bomber. In January of 1916 Geoffery de Havilland, chief aeronautical engineer of Aircraft Manufacturing Company, Ltd. (Airco), responded to an official request by British military leaders for such an aircraft and the D.H.4 was the result. Geoffery de Havilland's new machine made its maiden flight in August of 1916 under the control of the designer himself. The powerplant originally specified for the D.H.4 was a 160 hp Beardmore water cooled engine. By the time the D.H.4 design was being prepared, however, this engine had been replaced by a larger, 230 hp version. The first production D.H.4s received this upgraded engine, or a 250 hp Rolls Royce V12, called the "Eagle". The D.H.4s, with their new power plants, fulfilled all performance expectations and in aviation circles the machines quickly acquired the name of its designer. 

The first production D.H.4s were delivered to No. 55 Squadron of the Royal Flying Corps deployed on the Western Front in March of 1917. They immediately gained popularity among their crews and came to be judged the best single-engine bombers then in service. Even with a full bomb load they retained excellent speed and handling qualities. After release of their bombs they could compete on equal terms with enemy fighters. The success of the D.H.4 created a demand that exceed the resources of Airco, and several other British aircraft firms began building the machine under license. Many were also built under license in the United States. The American models were fitted with the American 400 hp (298 kW) Liberty engine leading to their nickname "Liberty Planes".They served with the British Royal Flying Corps, the British Royal Naval Air Service, the Royal Canadian Air Service, the United States Army Air Force and the air services of South Africa and New Zealand. The ubiquitous D.H.4s were widely deployed in a multitude of roles on the Western Front and in other far-flung theaters of operation during the last two years of the War. 

Following World War I the machines were employed by both the Bolsheviks and the White Russians during the Russian Civil War of 1919. Post-war, more than 400 D.H.4s were modified for civilian service and used as transports and mail planes. In these roles they remained flying until 1932. The Airco D.H.4 was, without question, one of the finest and most successful aircraft of the era. ]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 5 Squadron, Royal Naval Air Service, Boulogne-sur-Mer, France, February, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Aircraft Manufacturing Co Ltd (Airco)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Rolls-Royce Eagle VII, 12 cylinder V liquid-cooled piston engine of 375 hp (280 kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 143 mph (230 km/h) at sea level 
Ceiling: 22,000 feet (6,706 m)
Range: 435 miles (700 km) 
Empty Weight: 2,387 pounds (1,082 kg)
Loaded Weight: 3,472 pounds (1,575 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 42 feet 5 inches (12.93 m) 
Length: 30 feet 8 inches (9.35 m)
Height: 11 feet (3.35 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One or two fixed, forward-firing synchronized 7.7 mm (0.303 inch) Vickers machine guns in forward fuselage, one 7.7mm (0.303 inch) Lewis machine gun on flexible mount in rear cockpit, 209 kg (460 pounds) of bombs
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

