<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="335" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Bomber]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[de Havilland (Airco) D.H.9]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The D.H.9 was the last in a series of aircraft designed by Geoffrey de Havilland, chief aeronautical engineer of the Aircraft Manufacturing Company, Ltd. (Airco). Intended to improve upon de Havilland's highly successful D.H.4 bomber, the new D.H.9 was created in response to the British Air Board's plans to expand the country's air forces from 108 to 200 squadrons. 

The D.H.9 differed from its predecessor only in its engine and cockpit configuration. The new bomber positioned the pilot closer to the gunner's position, which greatly improved the crew's ability to communicate in flight. The engine selected for the aircraft was the new new Armstrong Siddeley Puma engine. The new powerplant was originally rated at 300 h.p., but soon downgraded to 230 h.p. after experiencing problems defective cylinder blocks. This downgrade meant that the D.H.9 -intended as an improvement over the D.H.4- actually had less power than its predecessor. 

Following their introduction in January of 1918, fifty D.H.9s were promptly shot down and another 100 were damaged beyond repair, due in large part to their insufficient power. The disparity between the aircraft's original design and its operational performance prompted Major-General Hugh Trenchard, Chief of the British Air Ministry, to initiate an official inquiry. 

Despite deficiencies and combat losses, D.H.9s remained in front line service until the War's end. In an effort to correct the power problem, de Havilland installed the American built 400 hp (298 kw) 12 cylinder Liberty engine into the D.H.9 airframe. Dubbed the D.H.9A, the new variant achieved the performance de Havilland, Airco and the British Royal Flying Corps had been seeking. Unfortunately, the new variant did not reach service until the autumn of 1918 -too late to have an impact on the War. 

Over 2,500 D.H.9As were built, the vast majority during the decade following World War I. Post-War, D.H.9As not only flew for the British but were also sold to the air forces of the United States, Belgium, Canada, Estonia, Latvia, Chile, Peru, Poland, Spain, Switzerland, Ireland, Greece and Romania. D.H.9A's were also deployed by both White and Red Russian forces during the 1917-1919 Russian Civil War. Some South African D.H.9As remained in front line operational service until 1938. 

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> The D.H.9 modeled here (#B 7620) has white fuselage recognition stripes, the markings of No. 211 Squadron Leader J.A. Gray who was shot down over Holland on June 17, 1918 while on a bombing mission in northwest Germany.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 211 Squadron, British Royal Air Force, Pedre Synthe Aerodrome, Northern France, Western Front, June, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Aircraft Manufacturing Co Ltd (Airco)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Armstrong Siddeley Puma, 6 cylinder inline liquid-cooled piston engine of 230 hp (298 kw) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 111 mph (179 km/h) 
Ceiling: 15,300 feet (4663 m)
Empty Weight: 2,415 pounds (1,095 kg)
Loaded Weight: 3799 pounds (1,723 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 45 feet 11 inches (14.00m)
Length: 30 feet 3 inches (9.22 m)
Height: 11 feet 4 inches (3.45 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing synchronized 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Vickers machine gun mounted on forward fuselage, one or two 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun(s) on a flexible mount in rear cockpit, up to 660 lbs (300 kg) of bombs 
<b>Crew:</b>2
]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

