<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="336" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Floatplane]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Avro 503 Seaplane (Type H)]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Avro 503 Seaplane was designed in early 1913 by the British aeronautical engineer, Alliot Verdon Roe, the founder of the Manchester-based aviation firm A.V. Roe & Company Ltd (Avro). At least three production aircraft were purchased by the Royal Naval Air Service, and were active when World War I began in August of 1914. 

The 503 was a two-seat biplane of standard wood and fabric construction. The seaplane undercarriage consisted of two pontoons covered with rubber-proofed cloth and sprung with rubber cord. The tail float attached directly to the bottom of the rudder and would move as the pilot steered. The 503 was able to be quickly dismantled for shipping -a common consideration in Avro designs.

Interestingly, the prototype for the Avro 503 was sold to Germany prior to the start of World War I. The aircraft became the basis for the German, Gotha WD.I seaplane, which appeared in early 1914 and spawned a line of subsequent German seaplanes. Germany's Avro also became the first aircraft to fly between the German mainland and the small archipelago of Heligoland, located on the North Sea.

<b>Model Builder's Comments:</b> This model depicts an aircraft equipped with a 150 hp engine. While later Avro models, including the 510 seaplane sported engines of this type, the standard powerplant for the 503 was a 100 hp Gnôme engine.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 4 Squadron, Royal Naval Air Service, British Royal Navy Base, Scapa Flow, Orkney Islands, March, 1916.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> A. V. Roe & Co Ltd (Avro)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Gnôme Monosoupape, 9 cylinder rotary air cooled piston engine of 150 hp (112kW)
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 50 mph (80.47 km/h) at sea level 
Ceiling: 11,500 feet (3,496 m)
Range: not documented 
Empty Weight: 1,740 pounds (789.25 kg)
Loaded Weight: 2,200 pounds (1,226 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 50 feet (14.48 m) 
Length: 33 feet 6 inches (10.21 m) 
Height: 12 feet 9 inches (3.89 m)
<b>Armament:</b> none
<b>Crew:</b>2
<br />]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

