<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="337" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Fighter]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Avro 504K]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Avro 504 represents the only military aircraft of World War I to serve in frontline combat from the first to the final day of the War. The 504 was designed by the British aviation pioneer Alliot Verdon Roe, founder of the A.V. Roe & Company, Ltd. (Avro). It first flew in 1913 as a participant in a number of air races and in 1914 set a new unofficial altitude record of 15,000 feet. Small numbers of this craft were initially ordered by both the Royal Flying Corps and the Royal Navy Air Service. With the outbreak of World War I, demand for the highly successful aircraft was so great that several additional British aircraft firms besides Avro began production. 

Variants of the Avro 504 encompassed several different roles, serving as a reconnaissance craft, light bomber, trainer, fighter and night fighter. It was built in more different variants than any other British type. In all, over 10,000 were built-more than any other type of British warplane. The largest numbers of 504s served as trainers and in reconnaissance. These were two-seat machines. The fighter and bomber variants had their forward seat removed to allow for increased fuel capacity and to accommodate the added weight of a machine gun and its ammunition, or the weight of a bomb load. The K variant (modeled here) was fitted with universal engine-bearer struts allowing it to accept most of the new more powerful rotary engines which were becoming available.

The Avro 504 participated in several important milestones of the War. On August 22, 1914, an Avro 504 of No. 5 Squadron became the first British aircraft to be brought down by enemy fire. In November of 1914, 504s became the first British aircraft to bomb the Zeppelin sheds at Friedrichshafen, Germany. The 504 also represents the first British machine to function as a dedicated night fighter combating the German nighttime Zeppelin raids over London.

At the end of the War, the Royal Flying Corps possessed 2,999 Avro 504s in active service, more than any other British aircraft type. Following World War I, no fewer than 17 countries acquired and deployed Avro 504 aircraft in their air forces. Some of these aircraft even continued service into World War II. Several machines are airworthy to this day and are part of civilian historical aircraft collections or museums.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents a night fighter of the Royal Flying Corps, May 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> A. V. Roe & Co Ltd (Avro)
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Le Rhône 9J, 9 cylinder air-cooled rotary piston engine of 110 hp 75kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 95 mph (153 km/h) 
Ceiling: 18,200 feet (5,547 m)
Endurance: 3 1/2 hours 
Empty Weight: 1,231 lbs (558 kg) 
Loaded Weight: 1,829 lbs (827 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 36 feet 0 inches (10.97 m)
Length: 29 feet 5 inches (8.97 m) 
Height: 10 feet 5 inches (3.18 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One fixed, forward-firing 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun on a Foster mount fitted on upper wing firing over propeller arc
<b>Crew:</b>1]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

