<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="338" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Floatplane]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Fairey Campania F.22]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Fairey Campania, built by the British aviation firm Fairey, was the first aircraft to be specifically designed for service on an aircraft carrier. The British Royal Navy was the first to undertake the development of aircraft carriers. One of the earliest of these ships was <i>HMS Campania</i>, a converted Cunard transatlantic passenger liner for which Fairey's aircraft was named. 

The new aircraft was a large, single-engine floatplane. Due to shortages of the Rolls Royce Eagle V engine, the first production models were instead equipped with a Sunbeam Maori II powerplant. However, some Campanias, like the one modeled here, would eventually be upgraded to the Rolls Royce Eagle VIII, the most powerful aircraft engine built in Great Britain during the War. The 345 hp (257 kW) engine turned a monster propeller over 12 feet (3.81 m) in diameter. 

The aircraft was intended to launch from the carrier's deck, riding on a wheeled trolley. Upon returning to the carrier, the Campania would land on the water to be hoisted aboard by crane. A steel ring mounted in the center of the upper wing served as an attachment point for the aircraft's retrieval.

Only 62 Campania aircraft were built before their production was terminated with the end of the War. They operated from the Royal Navy's new aircraft carriers, from shore facilities along England's coastline and from the Royal Naval Base at Scapa Flow in the Orkney Islands. A late arrival minimized their impact on World War I, but Campanias helped usher in a new concept in naval warfare-ship-based offensive aircraft.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the Royal Air Force, Aircraft Carrier <i>HMS Campania</i>, Royal Naval Base, Scapa Flow, Orkney Islands, October, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Fairey Aviation Company
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> One Rolls-Royce Eagle VIII, 12 cylinder inline V liquid-cooled piston engine of 345 hp (257 kW) 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 85 mph (137 km/h) at 600 feet (183 m) 
Ceiling: 5,500 feet (1,676 m)
Endurance: 3+ hours 
Empty Weight: 3,874 pounds (1,757 kg)
Loaded Weight: 5,675 pounds (2,574 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 61 feet 7 inches (18.77 m)
Length: 43 feet 1 inch (13.13 m)
Height: 15 feet 1 inches (4.60 m)
<b>Armament:</b> One 0.303 inch (7.7 mm) Lewis machine gun in flexible mount in rear cockpit, two 100 pound (45 kg) depth bombs
<b>Crew:</b>2]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

