<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="339" cos="United States"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Flying Boat]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Curtiss Model H-16 ]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Curtiss line of flying boats was one of only two American built aircraft-types to play a significant role in World War I -The other being the Curtiss JN-4 "Jenny" trainer. The predecessor of the H-16 flying boat was developed in 1914 at the request of Rodman Wanamaker, who was planning to attempt a transatlantic flight. The order for the aircraft, originally named America was cancelled at the outbreak of World War I. However, in 1916, the U.S. Navy ordered a number of flying boats based on the design. The new aircraft were designated H-12s and were the immediate predecessor of the H-16 modeled here.

The Curtiss flying-boats set many of the standards which would be used in flying-boat aircraft throughout the decades to come. The aircraft featured a v-shaped hull, which diverted water away from the cockpit during takeoff and landing and greatly reduced the drag on the underside of the aircraft while on the water. The H-12 and H-16 were twin-engine biplanes, which utilized a "tractor" configuration with forward-facing propellers. This differed from many flying boats of the time, which were configured as "pushers".

The United States Navy initially ordered 19 production H-12s and the British Royal Naval Air Service (R.N.A.S.) ordered an additional 50. In Britain, the aircraft were referred to as "Large Americas" to distinguish them from the smaller Curtiss H.4 flying boats -called "Small Americas"- already in R.N.A.S. service. 

The H-12 proved highly successful as a maritime patrol aircraft. In May of 1917, British H-12s successfully downed a Zeppelin, damaged another and sunk a German U-boat. Similar success stories continued throughout the year and prompted the development of a larger, improved version of the H-12, which became the H-16.

The first H-16s began appearing in the spring of 1918, but production delays meant that only 15 reached operational service before the Armistice. Nevertheless, The United States Navy eventually acquired 274 Curtiss H-16s, some of which remained in service until 1928.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of the United States Naval Air Station, North Sydney, Nova Scotia, Canada, October, 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> Curtiss Aeroplane and Motor Co. 
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> United States
<b>Power plant:</b> Two Liberty, 12 cylinder inline V liquid-cooled piston engines of 360 hp (269 kW) each 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed: 87 mph (140 km/h) 
Ceiling: 12,500 feet (3,810 m)
Range: 378 miles (608 km) 
Empty Weight: 8,250 pounds (3,742 kg)
Loaded Weight: 13,000 pounds (5,897 kg)
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span: 104 feet (31.70 m) 
Length: 46 feet 1 inch (14.05 m) 
Height:17 feet 8 inches (5.38 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Four to six 7.7 mm (0.303 inch) Lewis machine guns on flexible mounts in nose, dorsal mid fuselage and side fuselage waist positions, up to 417 kg (920 pounds) of bombs or depth charges 
<b>Crew:</b>4
]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

