<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<holtPlane>
<mainInfo id="340" cos="Great Britain"> 
<type><![CDATA[Reconnaissance Flying Boat]]></type>
<plnName><![CDATA[Felixstowe F.2A]]></plnName>
</mainInfo>
<history>
<![CDATA[The Felixstowe F.2A was one of the largest flying boats of World War I. Its design and construction borrowed heavily from the American Curtiss H-12 and H-16 flying boats. Despite being complicated, time-consuming and expensive to build, the British Royal Flying Corps received 170 Felixstowe F.2As from November 1917 through March 1918.

The Felixstowe F.2A provided Britain with a long range maritime reconnaissance aircraft. It patrolled the North Sea, monitoring the German High Seas Fleet and attacking German submarines. World War I historical records contain little about the operational successes or failures of the machines overall. Although the outcome of the attack is obscure, Felixstowe F.2A No. 4543 (modeled here) attacked a German U-boat with its bombs on July 9, 1918.

Improvements in German naval fighters, however, threatened these large, slow flying boats. The fighters exploited a flaw in the F.2A's defenses. Machine guns in the rear fuselage could not fire to the rear least they damage the aircraft's tail. British engineers later corrected this defensive "blind spot" by installing an additional dual machine gun mount in the middle of the upper wing. A special cupola provided this upper wing gunner with an ideal 360 degree field of fire.

The Felixstowe F.2A impacted the design of later British aircraft. It represents the first military-built "fortress boat." Its defensive design established a basic formula for British flying boats through World War II. The Felixstowe F.2A's incredibly reliable engines also inspired the design of later British powerplants. These engines were the forerunner of the World War II Rolls-Royce Merlin engines, which powered numerous British aircraft including the Supermarine Spitfire, the Hawker Hurricane, the de Havilland Mosquito and the Avro Lancaster.]]>
</history>
<deployment>
<![CDATA[This model represents an aircraft of No. 230 Squadron, British Royal Flying Corps, North Sea, August 1918.]]>
</deployment>
<technicalSpecs>
<![CDATA[<b>Manufacturer:</b> The Aircraft Manufacturing Co, Ltd
<b>Country of Manufacture:</b> Great Britain
<b>Power plant:</b> Two Rolls-Royce Eagle VIII, 12 cylinder liquid-cooled engines of 345 hp (257 kW) each 
<b>Performance:</b>
Maximum Speed 95 mph (153 km/h) at 200 ft (61 m) 
Ceiling: 9,600 feet (2,926 m)
Endurance: 6 Hours
Empty Weight: 7.549 pounds (3,424 kg)
Loaded Weight: 10,978 pounds (4,980 kg) 
<b>Dimensions: </b>
Span 95 feet 7 inches (29.13 m) 
Length 46 feet 3 inches (14.10 m) 
Height 17 feet 6 inches (5.83 m)
<b>Armament:</b> Four to seven 7.7 mm (0.303 inch) flexible Lewis machine guns (dual mounts in nose, dorsal mid fuselage and upper wing, single mounts in bilateral fuselage waist positions), two 209 kg (460 pound) bombs 
<b>Crew:</b>7]]>
</technicalSpecs>


</holtPlane>

